<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	>

<channel>
	<title>Next Economy &#8211; Radar</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/topics/next-economy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar</link>
	<description>Now, next, and beyond: Tracking need-to-know trends at the intersection of business and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 20:43:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.3.13</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Checking Jeff Bezos&#8217;s Math</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/checking-jeff-bezoss-math/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/checking-jeff-bezoss-math/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 20:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=13748</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[“If you want to be successful in business (in life, actually), you have to create more than you consume. Your goal should be to create value for everyone you interact with. Any business that doesn’t create value for those it touches, even if it appears successful on the surface, isn’t long for this world. It’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>“If you want to be successful in business (in life, actually), you have to create more than you consume. Your goal should be to create value for everyone you interact with. Any business that doesn’t create value for those it touches, even if it appears successful on the surface, isn’t long for this world. It’s on the way out.” So wrote Jeff Bezos in his <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/company-news/2020-letter-to-shareholders">final letter to shareholders</a>, released last week. It’s a great sentiment, one I heartily agree with and wish that more companies embraced. But how well does he practice what he preaches? And why is practicing this so hard by the rules of today’s economy?</p>



<p>Jeff started out by acknowledging the wealth that Amazon has created for shareholders—$1.6 trillion is the number he cites in the second paragraph. That’s Amazon’s current market capitalization. Jeff himself now owns only about 11% of Amazon stock, and that’s enough to make him the richest person in the world. But while his Amazon stock is worth over $160 billion, that means that over $1.4 trillion is owned by others.</p>



<p>“I’m proud of the wealth we’ve created for shareowners,” Jeff continued. “It’s significant, and it improves their lives. But I also know something else: it’s not the largest part of the value we’ve created.” That’s when he went on to make the statement with which I opened this essay. He went on from there to calculate the value created for employees, third-party merchants, and Amazon customers, as well as to explain the company’s <a href="https://sustainability.aboutamazon.com/about/the-climate-pledge">Climate Pledge</a>.</p>



<p>Jeff’s embrace of <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2021/01/klaus-schwab-on-what-is-stakeholder-capitalism-history-relevance/">stakeholder capitalism</a> is meaningful and important. Ever since Milton Friedman penned the 1970 op-ed in which he argued that “<a href="http://umich.edu/~thecore/doc/Friedman.pdf">the social responsibility of business is to increase its profits</a>,” other constituencies—workers, suppliers, society at large, and even customers—have too often been sacrificed on the altar of shareholder value. Today’s economy, rife with inequality, is the result.</p>



<p>While I applaud the goal of understanding “who gets what and why” (which in many ways is the central question of economics), I struggle a bit with Jeff’s math. Let’s walk through those of his assertions that deserve deeper scrutiny.</p>



<h3>How much went to shareholders?</h3>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>“Our net income in 2020 was $21.3 billion. If, instead of being a publicly traded company with thousands of owners, Amazon were a sole proprietorship with a single owner, that’s how much the owner would have earned in 2020.”</em><br></p></blockquote>



<p>Writing in <em>The Information, </em><a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/the-briefing-jeff-bezos-calculates-value-creation-wrong">Martin Peers made what seems to be an obvious catch</a>: “Instead of calculating value by looking at the increase in Amazon’s market cap last year—$679 billion—Bezos uses the company’s net income of $21 billion. That hides the fact that shareholders got the most value out of Amazon last year, far more than any other group.”</p>



<p>But while Peers has put his finger on an important point, he is wrong. The amount earned by shareholders <em>from Amazon</em> is indeed only the company’s $21.3 billion net income. The difference between that number and the $679 billion increase in market cap didn’t come from Amazon. It came from “the market,” that is from other people trading Amazon’s stock and placing bets on its future value. Understanding this difference is crucial because it undercuts so many <a href="https://twitter.com/rbreich/status/1305921198291779584?lang=en">facile criticisms of Jeff Bezos’s wealth</a>, in which he is pictured as a robber baron hoarding the wealth accumulated from his company at the expense of his employees.</p>



<p>The fact that Jeff is the world’s richest person makes him an easy target. What we really need to come to grips with is the way that our financial system has been hijacked to make the rich richer. Low interest rates, meant to prop up business investment and hiring, have instead been diverted to driving up the price of stocks beyond reasonable bounds. Surging corporate profits have been used not to fuel hiring or building new factories or bringing new products to market, but on stock buybacks designed to artificially boost the price of stocks. The state of “the market” has become a very bad proxy for prosperity. Those lucky enough to own stocks are enjoying boom times; those who do not are left out in the cold.</p>



<p>Financial markets, in effect, give owners of stocks the value of future earnings and cash flow today—in Amazon’s case, <a href="https://www.nasdaq.com/market-activity/stocks/amzn/price-earnings-peg-ratios">about 79 years worth</a>. But that’s nothing. Elon Musk is the world’s second-richest person because the market values Tesla at <a href="https://www.nasdaq.com/market-activity/stocks/tsla/price-earnings-peg-ratios">over 1,000 years of its present earnings</a>!</p>



<p>The genius of this system is that it allows investors and entrepreneurs to bet on the future, bootstrapping companies like Amazon and Tesla long before they are able to demonstrate their worth. But once a company has become established, it often no longer needs money from investors. Someone who buys a share of a hugely profitable company like Apple, Amazon, Google, Facebook, or Microsoft, isn’t investing in these companies. They are simply betting on the future of its stock price, with the profits and losses coming from others around the gaming table.</p>



<p>In my 2017 book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/WTF-Whats-Future-Why-Its/dp/0062565710"><em>WTF?: What&#8217;s the Future and Why It&#8217;s Up to Us</em></a>, I wrote a chapter on this betting economy, which I called “supermoney” after <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Supermoney-Adam-Smith/dp/0471786314">the brilliant 1972 book</a> with that title by finance writer George Goodman (alias Adam Smith.) Stock prices are not the only form of supermoney. Real estate is another. Both are rife with what economists call “rents”—that is, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rentier-Capitalism-Owns-Economy-Pays/dp/1788739728">income that comes not from what you do but from what you own</a>. And government policy seems designed to prop up the rentier class at the expense of job creation and real investment. Until we come to grips with this two-track economy, we will never tame inequality.</p>



<p>The fact that in the second paragraph of his letter Jeff cites Amazon’s market cap as the value created for shareholders but uses the company’s net income when comparing gains by shareholders to those received by other stakeholders is a kind of sleight of hand. Because of course corporate profits—especially the prospect of growth of corporate profits—and market capitalization are related. If Amazon gets $79 of market cap for every dollar of profit (which is what that price-earnings ratio of 79 means), then if Amazon were to raise wages for employees or give a better deal to its third-party merchants (many of them small businesses), that would lower its profits, and presumably its market cap, by an enormous ratio.</p>



<p>Every dollar given up to these other groups isn’t just a dollar out of the pocket of shareholders. It is many times that. This of course <em>does</em> provide a very powerful incentive for public companies to squeeze these other parties for every last dollar of profit, encouraging lower wages, outsourcing to eliminate benefits, and many other ills that contribute to our two-tier economy. It may not be Amazon’s motivation—Jeff has always been a long-term thinker and was able to persuade financial markets to go along for the ride even when the company’s profits were small—but it is most certainly <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Makers-and-Takers-Rana-Foroohar-audiobook/dp/B01CUKFLII">the motivation for much of the extractive behavior by many companies today</a>. The pressure to increase earnings and keep stock prices high is enormous.</p>



<p>These issues are complex and difficult. Stock prices are <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/0ca06172-bfe9-11de-aed2-00144feab49a">reflexive</a>, as financier George Soros likes to observe. That is, they are based on what people believe about the future. Amazon’s current stock price is based on the collective belief that its profits will be even higher in future. Were people to believe instead that they would be meaningfully lower, the valuation might fall precipitously. To understand the role of expectations of future increases in earnings and cash flow, you have only to <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/AAPL/key-statistics?p=AAPL">compare Amazon with Apple</a>. Apple’s profits are three times Amazon’s and free cash flow four times, yet it is valued at only 36 times earnings and has a market capitalization less than 50% higher than Amazon. As expectations and reality converge, multiples tend to come down.</p>



<h3>How did Amazon’s third-party sellers fare?</h3>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>“[We] estimate that, in 2020, third-party seller profits from selling on Amazon were between $25 billion and $39 billion, and to be conservative here I’ll go with $25 billion.”</em></p></blockquote>



<p>That sounds pretty impressive, but how much of a profit margin is it really?</p>



<p>Amazon doesn’t explicitly disclose the gross merchandise volume of those third-party sellers, but there is enough information in the letter and in <a href="https://s2.q4cdn.com/299287126/files/doc_financials/2021/ar/Amazon-2020-Annual-Report.pdf">the company’s 2020 annual report</a> to make a back-of-the-napkin estimate. The letter says that Amazon’s third-party sales represent “close to 60%” of its online sales. If the 40% delivered by Amazon’s first-party sales come out to $197 billion, that would imply that sales in the third-party marketplace were almost $300 billion. $25 to $39 billion in profit on $300 billion works out to a profit margin between 8% and 13%.</p>



<p>But is Amazon calculating <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/o/operatingincome.asp">operating income</a>, <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/ebitda.asp">EBITDA</a>, or <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/n/netincome.asp">net income</a>? “Profit” could refer to any of the three, yet they have very different values.</p>



<p>Let’s generously assume that Amazon is calculating net income. In that case, small retailers and manufacturers selling on Amazon are doing quite well, since net income from US retailers’ and manufacturers’ overall operations are <a href="http://pages.stern.nyu.edu/~adamodar/New_Home_Page/datafile/margin.html">typically between 5 and 8%</a>. Without knowing which profit number Amazon’s team is estimating, though, and the methodology they use to arrive at it, it is difficult to be sure whether these numbers are better or worse than what these sellers achieve through other channels.</p>



<p>One question that’s also worth asking is whether selling on Amazon in 2020 was more or less profitable than it was in 2019. While Amazon didn’t report a profit number for its third-party sellers in 2019, it did report how much its sellers paid for the services Amazon provided to them. In 2019, that number was about $53.8 billion; in 2020, it was $80.5 billion, which represents a 50% growth rate. Net of these fees, income to Amazon but a cost to sellers, we estimate that seller revenue grew 44%. Since fees appear to be growing faster than revenues, that would suggest that in 2020, Amazon took a larger share of the pie and sellers got less. Of course, without clearer information from Amazon, it is difficult to tell for sure.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, Amazon took in another $21.5 billion in “other income,” which is primarily from advertising by sellers on Amazon’s platform. That grew by 52% from 2019’s $14 billion, again suggesting that Amazon’s share of the net is growing. And unlike some forms of advertising that bring in new customers, much of Amazon’s ad business represents a zero-sum competition between merchants bidding for top position, a position that in Amazon’s earlier years was granted on the basis of factors such as price, popularity, and user ratings.</p>



<h3>How about employees?</h3>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>“In 2020, employees earned $80 billion, plus another $11 billion to include benefits and various payroll taxes, for a total of $91 billion.”</em></p></blockquote>



<p>There’s no question that the $91 billion that Amazon paid out in wages and benefits in 2020 is meaningful. Some of those employees were very well compensated, others not so well, but all of them have jobs. Amazon is now one of the largest employers in the country. It is an exception to the tech industry in that it creates a large number of jobs, and not just high-end professional jobs, and that some of the jobs it creates are in locations where work is scarce.</p>



<p>That being said, Jeff’s description of the amount earned by employees is misleading. In every other case, he makes an effort to estimate the profit earned by a particular group. For employees, he treats the gross earnings of employees as if it were profit, writing, “If each group had an income statement representing their interactions with Amazon, the numbers above would be the ‘bottom lines’ from those income statements.”</p>



<p>No, Jeff, employee earnings are <em>their top line</em>. Just as a company has gross income before expenses, so do employees. The bottom line is what’s left over after all those expenses have been met. And for many of Amazon’s lower-paid employees—as is the case for lower-paid workers all over the modern economy—that true bottom line is negative, that is, less than they need to survive. Like workers at other giant profitable companies like Walmart and McDonald&#8217;s, <a href="https://thecounter.org/15-minimum-wage-amazon-top-employer-snap-recipients-walmart-mcdonalds/">a significant fraction of Amazon warehouse employees require government assistance</a>. So, in effect, taxpayers are subsidizing Amazon, because the share of the enterprise’s profits allocated to its lowest-paid employees was not enough for them to pay their bills.</p>



<p>That points to a major omission from the list of Amazon’s stakeholders: society at large. How does Amazon do when it comes to paying its fair share? According to a 2019 study, Amazon was the “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2019/dec/02/new-study-deems-amazon-worst-for-aggressive-tax-avoidance">worst offender</a>” among a rogues’ gallery of high-tech companies that use aggressive tax avoidance strategies. “Fair Tax Mark said this means Amazon’s effective tax rate was 12.7% over the decade when the headline tax rate in the US has been 35% for most of that period.” In 2020, Amazon made provision for taxes of $2.863 billion on pretax income of $24,178 billion, or about 11.8%. This may be legal, but it isn’t right.</p>



<p>Amazon is clearly moving in the right direction with employees. It introduced a $15 minimum wage in 2018, ahead of many of its peers. And given the genius of the company, the commitment to workplace safety and other initiatives to make Amazon a better employer that Jeff highlighted in his letter are likely to have a big payoff. When Amazon sets out to do something, it usually invents and learns a great deal along the way.</p>



<p>“We have always wanted to be Earth’s Most Customer-Centric Company,” Jeff wrote. “We won’t change that. It’s what got us here. But I am committing us to an addition. We are going to be Earth’s Best Employer and Earth’s Safest Place to Work. In my upcoming role as Executive Chair, I’m going to focus on new initiatives. I’m an inventor. It’s what I enjoy the most and what I do best. It’s where I create the most value&#8230;.We have never failed when we set our minds to something, and we’re not going to fail at this either.”</p>



<p>I find that an extremely heartening statement. At Amazon’s current stage of development, it has the opportunity, and is beginning to make a commitment, to put its remarkable capabilities to work on new challenges.</p>



<h2>Stakeholder value means solving multiple equations simultaneously</h2>



<p>I was very taken with Jeff’s statement that “if any shareowners are concerned that Earth’s Best Employer and Earth’s Safest Place to Work might dilute our focus on Earth’s Most Customer-Centric Company, let me set your mind at ease. Think of it this way. If we can operate two businesses as different as consumer ecommerce and AWS, and do both at the highest level, we can certainly do the same with these two vision statements. In fact, I’m confident they will reinforce each other.”</p>



<p>One of my criticisms of today’s financial-market-driven economy is that by focusing on a single objective, it misses the great opportunity of today’s technology, summed up by Paul Cohen, the former DARPA program manager for AI and now a professor at the University of Pittsburgh, when he said, “The opportunity of AI is to help humans model and manage complex interacting systems.” If any company has the skills to do that, I suspect it will be Amazon. And as Jeff wrote elsewhere in his letter, “When we lead, others follow.”</p>



<p>Amazon is also considering environmental impact. “Not long ago, most people believed that it would be good to address climate change, but they also thought it would cost a lot and would threaten jobs, competitiveness, and economic growth. We now know better,” Jeff wrote. “Smart action on climate change will not only stop bad things from happening, it will also make our economy more efficient, help drive technological change, and reduce risks. Combined, these can lead to more and better jobs, healthier and happier children, more productive workers, and a more prosperous future.” Amen to that!</p>



<p>In short, despite my questions and criticisms, there is a great deal to like about the directions Jeff set forth for Amazon in his final shareholder letter. In addition to the commitment to work more deeply on behalf of other stakeholders beyond customers and shareholders, I was taken with his concluding advice to the company: “The world will always try to make Amazon more typical—to bring us into equilibrium with our environment. It will take continuous effort, but we can and must be better than that.”</p>



<p>It is in the spirit of that aspiration that I offer the critiques found in this essay.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/checking-jeff-bezoss-math/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>9 additional books for the Next Economy</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/more-books-for-the-next-economy/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/more-books-for-the-next-economy/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 05:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=11466</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[We originally shared a selection of books relevant to the ongoing transformation of the economy, the world of work, the costs of capitalism, and how business gets done, but it was impossible to include all the titles we wanted to highlight. Thus, you get another compendium, this one perhaps a bit more eclectic than our [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We originally shared <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/books-for-the-next-economy/">a selection of books</a> relevant to the ongoing transformation of the economy, the world of work, the costs of capitalism, and how business gets done, but it was impossible to include all the titles we wanted to highlight. Thus, you get another compendium, this one perhaps a bit more eclectic than our first post (we hope) but just as elucidating and thought-provoking.</p>
<h2><em>Innovation + Equality</em></h2>
<p>University of Toronto economist Joshua Gans and Australian member of parliament Andrew Leigh, also an economist, question the market mechanisms that link technological progress to rising wealth inequality. They propose ideas to transform today’s winner-take-all economy into a more entrepreneurial <em>and</em> egalitarian society in their new book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/gz0V9QW0d00uMS0rF000gPB"><em>Innovation + Equality: How to Create a Future That Is More Star Trek Than Terminator</em></a><em>.</em> In a recent opinion piece for the <em>Hill</em>, the authors assert that we’re “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/wMVSQ9rFW0000Buh00d0A0P">running out of excuses for high inequality</a>.” You’ll find <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Q0PS0VM0FB0Wd0Qur00i9B0">an excerpt from the book, followed by an interview with the authors</a>, in the <em>Economist</em>.</p>
<h2><em>The Meritocracy Trap</em></h2>
<p>Yale Law School professor Daniel Markovits scrutinizes the great American faith that talent and hard work will result in success and upward mobility, and finds it entirely unjustified in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/XrW0BjM0Q000SP9Vd00uFC0"><em>The Meritocracy Trap: How America’s Foundational Myth Feeds Inequality, Dismantles the Middle Class, and Devours the Elite</em></a>. His sobering revelations include the role of higher education in deepening the class divide, as the concentration of wealthy kids in prestigious schools continues to grow and the middle class continues to shrink, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/dr0WBuDQPd0SV00M9k000F0">as is detailed in this </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/dr0WBuDQPd0SV00M9k000F0"><em>New York Times</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/dr0WBuDQPd0SV00M9k000F0"> review</a>. In this interview from the <em>Nation</em>, Markovits explains how “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/TlQFP0B0u000VME00W9drS0">the meritocracy is making us miserable</a>.” Listen in as <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/imPF0QMuBFW00r000Vd0S09">Markovits expands on his premise on </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/imPF0QMuBFW00r000Vd0S09"><em>The Ezra Klein Show</em></a>, or read <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/UdnB09S0WM0FrP00uQ000GV">this adapted excerpt in the </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/UdnB09S0WM0FrP00uQ000GV"><em>Atlantic</em></a>.</p>
<h2><em>The Code of Capital</em></h2>
<p>Columbia Law School professor Katharina Pistor explains the many ways our legal system perpetuates today’s extreme concentration of wealth in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/b0000rMWPFH0SBuo000dV9Q"><em>The Code of Capital: How the Law Creates Wealth and Inequality</em></a>. The <em>Boston Review</em> extolls Pistor’s tome along with two other alarming books that <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Ld90SM00u0IP0FpVB0W0r0Q">call out structural injustices and call for a thorough revision of economic imperatives</a>. Pistor occasionally writes for <em>Project Syndicate</em>; in her latest piece she declares, “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/NM00JFdr000uBPS0qQ90V0W">If wealth is justified, so is a wealth tax</a>.”</p>
<h2><em>Coders</em></h2>
<p>Technology journalist Clive Thompson, who writes for the <em>New York Times Magazine</em> and <em>Wired</em>, lays out how those who create the algorithms create the world and the ways we live in it in his book <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Bu00rF0SQ00090PM0VKWBdr"><em>Coders: The Making of a New Tribe and the Remaking of the World</em></a>. Thompson conveys the joy and artistry of programming along with the inevitable unintended consequences of innovation in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/b0000rMWPFL0SBus000dV9Q">this interview from </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/b0000rMWPFL0SBus000dV9Q"><em>The Verge</em></a>. The <em>New York Times</em> review of <em>Coders</em> describes the book as “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/o00MQ00tP00uBF09VSMrdW0">a journey—if you dare—into the minds of Silicon Valley programmers</a>.”</p>
<h2><em>Make, Think, Imagine</em></h2>
<p>In <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/o00NQ00uP00uBF09VSMrdW0"><em>Make, Think, Imagine: Engineering the Future of Civilization</em></a>, John Browne, an engineering apprentice who rose through the ranks to become CEO of BP from 1995 to 2007 and served as president of the UK’s Royal Academy of Engineering, asserts that technological progress can and must be harnessed to better civilization and spread prosperity&#8230;even today, as visions of a techno-dystopia can seem overwhelming. Browne discusses his faith in engineering, technology, and innovation in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/I0u0OFV0W9BvQr0d0P0MS00">this Book Talk hosted by Columbia University&#8217;s School of International and Public Affairs</a>. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/s0PP0Wu0VMQw0F0d9B00r0S">This </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/s0PP0Wu0VMQw0F0d9B00r0S"><em>Financial Times</em> review</a> emphasizes Browne’s faith in imagination, planning, and design to build a better society.</p>
<h2><em>Learning by Doing</em></h2>
<p>While it’s not a new book, we didn’t cover <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/I0u0QFV0W9BxQr0d0P0MS00"><em>Learning by Doing: The Real Connection Between Innovation, Wages, and Wealth</em></a> when it was published in 2015, and it deserves a place in our Next Economy reading list. Tim O’Reilly liked it so much that he devoted a chapter to it in his own 2017 book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/eQ0VRS00000MFP0d9uyWB0r"><em>WTF? What’s the Future and Why It’s Up to Us</em></a>. Entrepreneur and economist James Bessen, the executive director of the Technology &amp; Policy Research Initiative at Boston University School of Law, extolls learning on the job as the path to prosperity and advocates for policy changes that provide incentives for employers to put their workers on that path. Bessen was a speaker on the series <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/yuPFVdBQ0r0WSMS09z00000"><em>Talks at Google</em></a> in 2017 and a guest on <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/K00d9FM00WPT0ArVB0uQ0S0">Russ Roberts’s <em>EconTalk</em> podcast</a> in 2016. The <em>Atlantic</em> adapted an excerpt from his book: “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/R00W9VuMdr0000B0FUSPBQ0">Scarce Skills, Not Scarce Jobs</a>.”</p>
<h2><em>Hedge</em></h2>
<p>In his 2018 book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/kF0CW0Q00PB00MrdVu0V90S"><em>Hedge: A Greater Safety Net for the Entrepreneurial Age</em></a><em>,</em> Nicolas Colin, cofounder and director of the European investment firm <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/c0900dBF0WQM0urSD0VWP00">The Family</a> and a prolific writer, argues that as we progress from the industrial age into an evermore digital world of work—one of faster-growing companies, rampant entrepreneurship, and a growing population of independent workers and gig economy participants—it’s increasingly important for society to rethink and reinforce its safety net. In <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/R00W9VuMdr0000B0FXSPEQ0">this Medium post</a>, Colin raises the prospect that China—not the US—will be the architect of “the Great Safety Net 2.0.” He makes the case that Silicon Valley should throw out its playbook and start caring about the world in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/c0900dBF0WQM0urSF0VYP00">this essay</a> from <em>Forbes</em>. Colin made an appearance on <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/r90Z0S0P0MGWVQFuB00d0r0"><em>Talks at Google</em></a> this spring to discuss <em>Hedge</em> and share his ideas about technology, policy, and the need to upgrade our institutions.</p>
<h2><em>The Blockchain and the New Architecture of Trust</em></h2>
<p>Cryptocurrencies have been subject to scandal and subterfuge, but the decentralized, distributed ledger technology underpinning the rise of Bitcoin and its brethren (a.k.a. the blockchain) has evolved to be used in many industries for authentication of information. Kevin Werbach, professor of legal studies and business ethics at the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania, recounts this evolution and describes the potential of the blockchain as a type of legal technology that can create tremendous business and social value in his book <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/NM000Fdr000uBQS0IQ90V0W"><em>The Blockchain and the New Architecture of Trust</em></a>. Werbach weighed in on Facebook’s now back-burnered cryptocurrency, Libra, in the <em>New York Times</em>, positing it as “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/AQ0J09FM00QruBd00W010VS">the social network’s last, best hope to regain public trust</a>.” The <em>New York Times</em> covered Werbach’s book, along with another blockchain book, in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/hWBu29M00F000drQQ000SKV">this review</a>. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/ZMQ9B0uLr0000d0V300WSFQ">Here’s Werbach’s <em>Talks at Google</em> appearance</a> to discuss his book.</p>
<h2><em>Digital Minimalism</em></h2>
<p>Georgetown University computer science professor Cal Newport had an instant hit on his hands with <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/O0Q0B9dS0000QFW40M0ruVM"><em>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</em></a>; he became known as the Marie Kondo of mobile phones for his sensible advice for staying centered in a world filled with addictive devices by making intentional choices and using tech to support your goals rather than enabling it to use you. Word of this book spread far beyond the usual Next Economy media suspects. Newport took to the pages of <em>Outside</em> with tips for readers to maximize their free time: “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Ld90SM00u05Q0FNVB0W0r0Q">To Upgrade Your Leisure, Downgrade Your Phone</a>.” <em>GQ</em> interviewed Newport about <em>Digital Minimalism</em> and “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/quSF0r0VWO0Q9Q00M0B600d">why we’ll look back at our smartphones like cigarettes</a>.” <em>New Yorker</em> writer Jia Tolentino road-tested Newport’s advice to find out firsthand “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Bu00PF0SQ00090QM0V7WBdr">what it takes to put your phone away</a>.”</p>
<h2>New from O’Reilly: The cloud and beyond</h2>
<p>Our tireless editors don’t just sit around reading great books; they’re continually on the lookout for savvy experts who can translate their skills and knowledge into books, videos, online courses, and other learning experiences to give you the most effective tools to master what you need to know to thrive in the Next Economy. Here are a few new tools to sharpen your competitive edge.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/XrW0BQM0Q000SQ9Vd00uF80"><em>Cloud Native Transformation: Practical Patterns for Innovation</em></a>, book by Pini Reznik, Jamie Dobson, and Michelle Gienow</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Q0QS0VM0F90Wd0Qur00R9B0"><em>Understanding the Cloud</em></a>, expert playlist curated by David Linthicum</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/O0Q0B9dS0000QFWa0S0ruVM">Fundamentals of Learning: Learn Faster and Better Using Neuroscience</a>, interactive online training course led by Connie Missimer</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/lQMdT000WuVB0S0r90Q0b0F">Having Difficult Conversations</a>, interactive online training course led by Jeffrey Fredrick and Douglas Squirrel</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/gc0V9QW0d00uMS0rF000UQB"><em>Spotlight on Innovation: Using Creativity to Solve Your Trickiest Business Problems</em></a>, recording of a recent online training course with Rita J. King</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/more-books-for-the-next-economy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>10+ books for the Next Economy</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/books-for-the-next-economy/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/books-for-the-next-economy/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=11353</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[One of the most popular sections of the Next:Economy Newsletter is our periodic Deeper Reading feature, highlighting books of relevance to the ongoing transformation of the economy, the world of work, the costs of capitalism, and how business gets done. It’s nearly impossible to keep up with the recent spate of important, enlightening, and inspirational [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular sections of the <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/emails/newsletters/"><em>Next:Economy Newsletter</em></a> is our periodic Deeper Reading feature, highlighting books of relevance to the ongoing transformation of the economy, the world of work, the costs of capitalism, and how business gets done. It’s nearly impossible to keep up with the recent spate of important, enlightening, and inspirational publications&#8230;and even if we could, we wouldn’t have the space to do justice to every book that provides a fresh perspective on how we think about work, entrepreneurship, capitalism, digital transformation, the construct of money, climate change, and other pertinent topics. To that end, we&#8217;ve put together a selection of books that comprise an engrossing Next Economy reading list for the year ahead.</p>
<h2><em>The Making of a Democratic Economy</em></h2>
<p>Last year, a reader of Tim O’Reilly’s book—<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/O0w0000S0000QFWr0X0ru0M"><em>WTF? What’s the Future and Why It’s Up to Us</em></a>—pointed him to Marjorie Kelly’s 2001 book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Y0r0w0WQ00000000WMF0qSu"><em>The Divine Right of Capital</em></a>, which he found revelatory. Kelly, cofounder of the <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/WF0uYQM0W0s0Sr000000w00">Fifty by Fifty initiative</a> to help build a more inclusive economy through employee ownership, came out with a new book this summer, cowritten with Ted Howard, cofounder and president of the Democracy Collaborative. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/o00tQ00Zw00u0F000SMr0W0"><em>The Making of a Democratic Economy: How to Build Prosperity for the Many, Not the Few</em></a> addresses today’s systemic economic crisis of inequality and offers ideas for creating a more inclusive, democratic economy grounded in community, justice, and sustainability. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/SM0S0r00W000QF00u00w00u">Read it now on O’Reilly online learning</a>.</p>
<h2><em>The Great Reversal</em></h2>
<p>In his new book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/V0M1000rwu0S000FW000vQ0"><em>The Great Reversal: How America Gave Up on Free Markets</em></a>, economist Thomas Philippon, professor of finance at the NYU Stern School of Business, lays the blame for today’s US economic problems squarely at the feet of anticompetitive, monopolistic practices employed by the largest American corporations; he shows how these practices drive up prices for consumers while limiting choices and stifling investment, productivity, and wage growth, perpetuating a vicious cycle of inequality. Watch Philippon present the issues raised in his book, followed by a panel discussion, in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/P000Q0rFWM00w00w002Su00">this video from the Brookings Institution Global Economy and Development program</a>. In a recent interview from the public radio show <em>Marketplace</em>, Philippon explains how “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/yuwF000Q0r0WSMx00300000">market concentration and low competition has become the new normal in America</a>.” You can <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/DFy00040SM000w0uWQ000r0">read this adapted excerpt in the </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/DFy00040SM000w0uWQ000r0"><em>Atlantic</em></a>. (To understand the broader effects of the consolidation of corporations on politics and how it’s tearing society apart, check out Matt Stoller’s <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/V0M5000rwu0S000FW000zQ0"><em>Goliath: The 100-Year War Between Monopoly Power and Democracy</em></a>.)</p>
<h2><em>The Triumph of Injustice</em></h2>
<p>Renowned UC Berkeley economists Emmanuel Saez and Gabriel Zucman (who have helped US presidential candidate Elizabeth Warren devise her tax plan) detail the transformation that has turned the US tax code upside down (so that the working class pays more as the wealthiest Americans benefit from policies that lessen their load) and propose reforms that will rectify this shameful situation in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/uAQ0000M0W0r0600w00FSu0"><em>The Triumph of Injustice: How the Rich Dodge Taxes and How to Make Them Pay</em></a><em>.</em> We’ve already shared <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/yuwF000Q0r0WSMB00700000">this </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/yuwF000Q0r0WSMB00700000"><em>New York Times</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/yuwF000Q0r0WSMB00700000"> opinion piece by David Leonhardt</a>, which clearly depicts how the tax rate on the rich has plummeted from 1950 to the present. The book’s authors also wrote a <em>Times</em> opinion piece filled with more straightforward data visualizations depicting the inequity of the US tax system: “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/E0r0F008MC00Q00S0w00W0u">How to Tax Our Way Back to Justice</a>.”</p>
<h2><em>Good Economics for Hard Times</em></h2>
<p>Newly minted Nobel laureates Abhijit V. Banerjee and Esther Duflo—a husband-and-wife team of economics professors at MIT—expand on their award-winning research in their new book, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/CM00090DW0wF0Qr0000uS00"><em>Good Economics for Hard Times</em></a>. They pull apart conceptions perceived as common knowledge and dig into the facts about societal forces including inequality, migration, globalization, and taxation. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/x0F0000w0Eu0WQM0ar000S0">Here’s a glowing review from the </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/x0F0000w0Eu0WQM0ar000S0"><em>Guardian</em></a>. Yet another <em>New York Times</em> opinion piece—this one by Nicholas Kristof, asking, “<a href="http://link.oreilly.com/ZMQ000ubr0000000F00WSFw">Should we soak the rich? You bet</a>!”—draws on both this book and <em>The Triumph of Injustice</em> to make its argument. Harvard’s Joint Center for History and Economics hosted a launch conference for the book; <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/lwM0c000Wu000S0r00Q0G0F">watch the video here</a>. You’ll <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/j0dM0u0WF000000QSrH0w00">find an extensive excerpt of the book when you scroll down here</a>.</p>
<h2><em>The Future of Capitalism</em></h2>
<p>Oxford economist Paul Collier delves into global societal divisions—between urbanites and rural dwellers, educated elites and the unskilled working class, and developed and emerging economies—and offers pragmatic, ethical ways to bridge these social, economic, and cultural chasms within a more compassionate, inclusive form of capitalism in his book <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/p0000F0ueS000IQMrW000w0"><em>The Future of Capitalism: Facing the New Anxieties</em></a>. Bill Gates has given a great deal of thought to the book; <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/XrW00fM0Q000Sw00000uFJ0">in this review</a> he agrees with most of its premises while arguing that Collier should expand his framework for rectifying capitalism’s excesses beyond the levels of global, national, company, and family to include community. In <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/kF0gW0Q00w000Mr00u0K00S">this review from the </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/kF0gW0Q00w000Mr00u0K00S"><em>Financial Times</em></a>, Martin Wolf despairs that a renewed sense of social obligation can counter the powerful forces of selfishness and greed. Collier discusses his book in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/K0000FM00WwL0hr000uQ0S0">this video from Oxford’s Blavatnik School of Government</a>.</p>
<h2><em>The Enlightened Capitalists</em></h2>
<p>James O’Toole, professor emeritus at the USC Marshall School of Business, founding director of the Neely Center for Ethical Leadership and Decision Making, and author of 17 books, turns his eye to business leaders who try to balance profitability and social purpose in his latest work, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/V0Mi000rwu0S000FW000MQ0"><em>The Enlightened Capitalists: Cautionary Tales of Business Pioneers Who Tried to Do Well by Doing Good</em></a><em>.</em> As the subtitle forewarns, the impulse to build societal good into a corporation’s business practices has its perils; O’Toole offers case studies in the form of portraits of successful entrepreneurs who lost control of their enterprises to executives who did not share their belief that a company should do more than chase profits, including improving workers’ lives, advancing women in the workplace, and advocating for other social issues such as the environment. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Aw0j00FM00Qru0000W0N00S">This review in the </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Aw0j00FM00Qru0000W0N00S"><em>Financial Times</em></a> points out that more recent business structure innovations—such as B Corporations, employee-owned enterprises, and cooperatives—offer better opportunities for compatibility of capitalism and corporate benevolence. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/U0k000S0WM0Frw00uQ000O0">In this </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/U0k000S0WM0Frw00uQ000O0"><em>Recode Decode</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/U0k000S0WM0Frw00uQ000O0"> interview</a> by Kara Swisher, O’Toole tears into the Corporate Roundtable’s recent redefinition of the purpose of a corporation to care for more than short-term returns, expressing doubt that leaders of US corporations can “walk the walk.”</p>
<h2>Tales from two of today’s enlightened capitalists</h2>
<p><em>The Enlightened Capitalists</em> might be the perfect book to read as a prelude to recent autobiographies by two strikingly different business leaders who have stood up for social issues to the tune of millions of dollars. In <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/TlQFw000u0000MP00W00rS0"><em>It’s How We Play the Game: Build a Business. Take a Stand. Make a Difference.</em></a>, Ed Stack recounts how he built the DICK’S Sporting Goods empire from his father’s two Dick’s Bait and Tackle stores, always intending to be a force for good in the communities where the stores are located. Distressed by the rise in school shootings, Stack raised the age for in-store gun purchases to 21 and pulled semiautomatics from his shelves in the wake of the Parkland, Florida, attack, destroying $5 million in inventory and angering conservative lawmakers, the NRA, and a large part of his customer base while at the same time earning accolades for placing principles above profits. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/z0000rW0000MQQwuF0m0S00">The </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/z0000rW0000MQQwuF0m0S00"><em>Washington Post</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/z0000rW0000MQQwuF0m0S00"> describes Stack’s bold move and its ramifications here</a>, and Stack recounts his actions in the broader context of US gun control in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/n0F00Rn000QW0SM00u00rw0">this CBS News interview</a>.</p>
<p>Some people give discreetly and anonymously, but Salesforce founder, board chair, and co-CEO Marc Benioff is not that kind of guy. Benioff has famously put millions of dollars behind efforts to combat the homeless crisis in San Francisco, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/NM00TF0r000u0wS0pQ0000W">supporting legislation to raise taxes on large corporations to help the homeless</a> (and getting into Twitter wars with his tech CEO peers who disagreed with Prop C) and, more recently, donating $30 million to launch the <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/c000000F0WQM0urSq00Uw00">UCSF Benioff Homelessness and Housing Initiative</a>. In <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/kF0oW0Q00w000Mr00u0S00S"><em>Trailblazer: The Power of Business as the Greatest Platform for Change</em></a>—written with Salesforce EVP of global strategic affairs Monica Langley—Benioff presents his vision for the role of business in making the world a better place and discusses how his company’s core values of trust, customer success, innovation, and equality; a commitment to giving back to society; and a focus on corporate culture have created a powerful competitive advantage. Benioff recounts his efforts to close Salesforce’s gender pay gap in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/irwF0QMu0VW00r000000S00">this excerpt from </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/irwF0QMu0VW00r000000S00"><em>Trailblazer</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/irwF0QMu0VW00r000000S00"> in </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/irwF0QMu0VW00r000000S00"><em>Wired</em></a>.</p>
<h2><em>More from Less</em></h2>
<p>Andrew McAfee, cofounder and codirector of the MIT Initiative on the Digital Economy and a principal research scientist at the MIT Sloan School of Management, expresses a positive vision for the future propelled by the “four horsemen of the optimist”—effective capitalism, technological progress, public awareness of environmental issues, and responsive, effective government—in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/trS0000wF00Ws00QM0000uW"><em>More from Less: The Surprising Story of How We Finally Learned to Prosper Using Fewer Resources—and What Happens Next</em></a>. He asserts that free markets and tech innovation will enable people to prosper while government institutions and the free press will rein in rapacious greed and protect against social and environmental harm—beliefs that seem inconceivable at this point in US history, as citizens lose faith in crumbling institutions while a cynical administration fights to maintain power. Part of his optimism derives from the fact that the US standard of living has risen over the past two decades while American consumption of resources like water, metals, and building materials declines. McAfee’s concept of the decoupling of growth and environmental degradation—at least in prosperous, developed economies—comes into question in many reviews of his book; <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/V0Mt000rwu0S000FW000XQ0">this post from the MIT Initiative on the Digital Economy blog</a> addresses those qualms. <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Fu0MW00Yu0F000w0000SrQ0">Here’s an enlightening interview with McAfee</a> by Russ Roberts in his <em>EconTalk</em> podcast. (The transcript is also available.)</p>
<h2><em>The Case for the Green New Deal</em></h2>
<p>Political economist Ann Pettifor, cofounder and director of <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/lxM0x000Wu000S0r00Q000F">PRIME (Policy Research in Macroeconomics)</a> and author of several books on economics, argues that financial markets, the economy, politics, and the ecosystem are inextricably bound together in her latest, <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/a0000W0u0F0000vSZMQw00r"><em>The Case for the Green New Deal</em></a>. She explains how governments can finance a Green New Deal without raising taxes in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Fu0MW001y0F000x0000SrQ0">this </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Fu0MW001y0F000x0000SrQ0"><em>Guardian</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/Fu0MW001y0F000x0000SrQ0"> story</a>. Get a more detailed explanation of her rationale in <a href="http://link.oreilly.com/p0000F0uzS0002QMrW000x0">this interview from </a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/p0000F0uzS0002QMrW000x0"><em>New York</em></a><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/p0000F0uzS0002QMrW000x0"> magazine</a>.</p>
<h2>This just in: New releases from O’Reilly</h2>
<p>As we call attention to an array of Next Economy-related books, we’d be remiss not to tout a few of our own. Here’s a sampling of recent releases, available for you to access right now on O’Reilly online learning. (If you’re not yet a member, try it free for 10 days.)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/m000QA00000ruW00Mx30FS0"><em>The AI Organization: Learn from Real Companies and Microsoft’s Journey How to Redefine Your Organization with AI</em></a><em>,</em> by David Carmona</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/I0u04F00W00BQr000x0MS00"><em>Digital Transformation Game Plan: 34 Tenets for Merging Technology &amp; Business</em></a><em>,</em> by Gary O’Brien, Guo Xiao, and Mike Mason</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/m000QC00000ruW00Mx50FS0"><em>97 Things Every Engineering Manager Should Know: Collective Wisdom from the Experts</em></a>, edited by Camille Fournier</li>
<li><a href="http://link.oreilly.com/TDQFx000u0000M600W00rS0"><em>Unblocked: How Blockchains Will Change Your Business (and What to Do About It)</em></a> (audiobook), by Alison McCauley</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/books-for-the-next-economy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Antitrust regulators are using the wrong tools to break up Big Tech</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/antitrust-regulators-are-using-the-wrong-tools-to-break-up-big-tech/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/antitrust-regulators-are-using-the-wrong-tools-to-break-up-big-tech/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 16:22:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=9035</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[It’s a nerve-wracking time to be a Big Tech company. Yesterday, a US subcommittee on antitrust grilled representatives from Amazon, Google, Facebook, and Apple in Congress, and presidential candidates have gone so far as to suggest that these behemoths should be broken up. In the European Union, regulation is already happening: in March, the EU [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s a nerve-wracking time to be a Big Tech company. Yesterday, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/congress-puts-big-tech-in-crosshairs-11563311754">a US subcommittee on antitrust</a> grilled representatives from Amazon, Google, Facebook, and Apple in Congress, and presidential candidates have gone so far as to suggest that <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/03/08/politics/elizabeth-warren-amazon-google-facebook/index.html">these behemoths should be broken up</a>. In the European Union, regulation is already happening: in March, the EU levied its <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/20/business/google-fine-advertising.html">third multibillion-dollar fine against Google</a> for anti-competitive behavior.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://blog.aboutamazon.com/company-news/2018-letter-to-shareholders">his 2018 letter to shareholders</a>, published this past April, Jeff Bezos was already prepping for conversations with regulators. He doesn’t think Amazon is a monopoly. Instead, the company’s founder argues it is “just a small player in global retail.”</p>
<p>In Bezos’s defense, for many of the products Amazon sells, there are indeed many alternative sources, suggesting plenty of competition. Despite Amazon’s leadership in online retail, <a href="https://mgmresearch.com/amazon-vs-walmart-revenues-and-profits-comparison-1999-2018/">Walmart is more than double Amazon’s size </a>as a general retailer, with Costco not far behind Amazon. Specialty retailers like Walgreens and CVS in the pharmacy world and Kroger and Albertson’s in groceries also dwarf Amazon’s presence in their categories.</p>
<p>But Amazon does not just compete with Walmart, CVS, Kroger, and other retailers—it also competes with the merchants who sell products through its platform.</p>
<p>This competition isn’t just the obvious kind, such as the Amazon Basics-branded batteries that by 2016 represented <a href="https://www.1010data.com/company/blog/market-insights-series-amazon-s-advance-the-battle-of-batteries/">one third of all online battery sales</a>, as well as similar Amazon products in audio, home electronics, baby wipes, bed sheets, and kitchenware. Amazon also competes with its merchants for visibility on its platform, and charges them additional fees for favored placement. And because Amazon is now leading with featured products rather than those its customers think are the best, its merchants are incentivized to advertise on the platform. Amazon’s fast-growing advertising business is thus a kind of tax on its merchants.</p>
<p>Likewise, Google does not just compete with other search engines like Bing and DuckDuckGo, but with everyone who produces content on the world wide web. Apple’s iPhone and Google’s Android don’t just compete with each other as smartphone platforms, but also with the app vendors who rely on smartphones to sell their products.</p>
<p>This kind of competition is taken for granted by antitrust regulators, who are generally more concerned with the end cost for consumers. And as anyone who has shopped online will know, Amazon is nearly always the cheaper option. (In fact, surveys have suggested that between <a href="https://marketingland.com/online-shoppers-use-amazon-to-compare-products-259139">seven</a> and <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2016/09/27/amazon-is-the-first-place-most-online-shoppers-visit.html">nine</a> out of 10 Americans will check Amazon to compare the price of a purchase.) As long as the monopoly doesn’t lead to us forking out more money, then antitrust regulators traditionally leave it alone.</p>
<p>However, this view of antitrust leaves out some unique characteristics of digital platforms and marketplaces. These giants don’t just compete on the basis of product quality and price—they control the market through the algorithms and design features that decide which products users will see and be able to choose from. And these choices are not always in consumers’ best interests.</p>
<h2>A fresh approach to antitrust</h2>
<p>All of the internet giants—Amazon, Google, Facebook, and insofar as app stores are considered, Apple—provide the illusion of free markets, in which billions of consumers choose among millions of suppliers’ offerings, which compete on the basis of price, quality, and availability.</p>
<p>But if you recognize that what consumers really choose from is not the universe of all possible products, but those that are offered up to them either on the homepage or the search screen, the “shelf space” provided by these platforms is in fact far more limited than the tiniest of local markets—and what is placed on that shelf is uniquely under the control of the platform owner. And with mobile playing a larger and larger role, that digital shelf space is visibly shrinking rather than growing.</p>
<p>In short, the designers of marketplace-platform algorithms and screen layouts can arbitrarily allocate value to whom they choose. The marketplace is designed and controlled by its owners, and that design shapes “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Who-Gets-What-Why-Matchmaking/dp/0544705289">who gets what and why</a>” (to use the marvelous phrase from Alvin E. Roth, who received a Nobel prize in economics for his foundational work in the field of market design.)</p>
<p>When it comes to antitrust, the question of market power must be answered by analyzing the effect of these marketplace designs on both buyers and sellers, and how they change over time. How much of the value goes to the platform, how much to consumers, and how much to suppliers?</p>
<p>The platforms have the power to take advantage of either side of their marketplace. Any abuse of market power is likely to show up first on the supply side. A dominant platform can squeeze its suppliers while continuing to pass along part of the benefit to consumers—but keeping more and more of it for themselves.</p>
<p>Over time, though, consumers feel the bite. Power over sellers ultimately translates into power over customers as well. As the platform owner favors its own offerings over those of its suppliers, choice is reduced, though it is only in the endgame that consumer pricing—the typical measure of a monopoly—begins to be affected.</p>
<p>The control that the platforms have over placement and visibility puts them in a unique position to collect what economists call <em>rents</em>: that is, value extracted through the ownership of a limited resource. These rents may come in the form of additional advantage given to the marketplace’s own private-label products, but also through the fees that are paid by merchants who sell through that platform. These fees can take many forms, including the necessity for merchants to spend more on advertising in order to gain visibility; Amazon products don’t have to pay such a levy.</p>
<p>The term “rents” dates back to the very earliest days of modern economics, when agricultural land was still the primary source of wealth. That land was worked productively by tenant farmers, who produced value through their labor. But the bulk of the benefit was taken by the landed gentry, who lived lives of ease on the unearned income that accrued to them simply through the ownership of their vast estates. In today’s parlance, Amazon’s merchants are becoming sharecroppers. The cotton field has been replaced by a search field.</p>
<p>Not all rents are bad. Economist Joseph Schumpeter pointed out that technological innovation often can lead to temporary rents, as innovators initially have a corner on a new product or service. But he also pointed out that these so-called Schumpeterian rents can, over time, become traditional monopolistic rents.</p>
<p>This is what antitrust regulators should be looking at when evaluating internet platform monopolies. Has control over the algorithms and designs that allocate attention become the latest tool in the landlord’s toolbox?</p>
<p>In her book, <a href="https://marianamazzucato.com/publications/books/value-of-everything/"><em>The Value of Everything</em></a>, economist Mariana Mazzucato makes the case that if we are really to understand the sources of inequality in our economy, economists must turn their attention back to rents. One of the central questions of classical economics was what activities are actually creating value for society, and which are merely value extracting—in effect charging a kind of tax on value that has actually been created elsewhere.</p>
<p>In today’s neoclassical economics, rents are seen as a temporary aberration, the result of market defects that will disappear given sufficient competition. But whether we are asking fundamental questions about value creation, or merely insufficient competition, rent extraction gives us a new lens through which to consider antitrust policy.</p>
<h2>How internet platforms increase choice</h2>
<p>Before digital marketplaces curtailed our choices as consumers, they first expanded our options.</p>
<p>Amazon’s virtually unlimited virtual shelf space radically expanded opportunity for both suppliers and consumers. After all, <a href="https://www.scrapehero.com/number-of-products-on-amazon-april-2019/">Amazon carries 120 million unique products</a> in the US alone, compared to about 120,000 in a Walmart superstore or 35 million on walmart.com. What’s more, Amazon operates a marketplace with <a href="https://www.marketplacepulse.com/amazon/number-of-sellers">over 2.5 million third-party sellers</a>, whose products, collectively, <a href="https://blog.aboutamazon.com/company-news/2018-letter-to-shareholders">provide 58% of all Amazon retail revenue</a>, with only 42% coming from Amazon’s first-party retail operation.</p>
<p>In the first-party retail operation, Amazon buys products from its suppliers and then resells them to consumers. In the third-party operation, Amazon collects fees for providing marketplace services to sellers—including display on amazon.com, warehousing, shipping, and sometimes even financing—but never legally takes possession of the companies’ merchandise. This is what allows it to have so many more products to sell than its competitors: because Amazon never takes possession of inventory but instead charges suppliers for the services it provides, the risk of offering a slow-moving product is transferred from Amazon to its suppliers.</p>
<p>All of this appears to add up to the closest approximation ever seen in retail to what economists call “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perfect_competition">perfect competition</a>.” This term refers to market conditions in which a large number of sellers with offers to provide comparable products at a range of prices are met by a large number of buyers looking for those products. Those buyers are armed not only with the ability to compare the price at which products are offered, but also to compare the quality of those products via consumer ratings and reviews. In order to win the business of consumers, suppliers must not only offer the best products at the best prices, but must compete for customers to express their satisfaction with the products they have bought.</p>
<p>So far, at least according to the statistics Bezos shared in his annual letter, the success of the Amazon marketplace is a triumph for both suppliers and consumers, and antitrust regulators should look elsewhere. As he put it, “Third-party sellers are kicking our first-party butt.”</p>
<p>He may well be right, but there are warning signs from other internet marketplaces like Google search that suggest the situation may not be as rosy as it appears. As it turns out, regulators need to consider some additional factors in order to understand the market power of internet platforms.</p>
<h2>How internet platforms take away choice</h2>
<p>If Amazon has become “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Everything-Store-Jeff-Bezos-Amazon-ebook/dp/B00BWQW73E">the everything store</a>” for physical goods, Google is the everything store for information.</p>
<p>Even more than Amazon, Google appears to meet the conditions for perfect competition. It matches up consumers with a near-infinite source of supply. Ask any question, and you’ll be provided with answers from hundreds or even thousands of competing content suppliers.</p>
<p>To do this, Google <a href="https://www.google.com/search/howsearchworks/">searches hundreds of billions of web pages</a> created by hundreds of millions of information suppliers. Traditional price matching is absent, since much of the content is offered for free, but Google uses hundreds of other signals to determine what answers its customers are likely to find “best.” They measure such things as the reputation of the sites linking to any other site (page rank); the words those sites use to make those links (anchor text); the content of the document itself (via an AI engine referred to as “the Google Brain”); how likely people are to click on a given result in the list, based on millions of iterations, all recorded and measured; and even whether people clicked on a link and appear to have gone away satisfied (“a long click”) or came back and clicked on another (“a short click”).</p>
<p>The same goes for advertising on Google. Its <a href="https://www.wordstream.com/articles/what-is-google-adwords">“pay per click” ad auction model</a> was a breakthrough in the direction of perfect competition: advertisers pay only when customers click on their ads. Both Google and advertisers are thus incentivized to feature ads that users actually want to see.</p>
<p>Only about 6% of Google search results pages contain any advertising at all. Both content producers and consumers have the benefit of Google’s immense effort to index and search all web pages, not just those that are commercially valuable. Google is like a store where all of the goods are free to consumers, but some merchants pay, in the form of advertising, to have their goods placed front and center.</p>
<p>The company is well aware of the risk that advertising will lead Google to favor the needs of advertisers over those of searchers. In fact, “Advertising and mixed motives” is the title of the appendix to Google founders Larry Page and Sergey Brin’s <a href="http://infolab.stanford.edu/~backrub/google.html">original 1998 research paper on Google’s search algorithms</a>, written while they were still graduate students at Stanford.</p>
<p>“The goals of the advertising business model do not always correspond to providing quality search to users,” they thoughtfully observed. Google made enormous efforts to overcome those mixed motives by clearly separating their advertising results from their organic results, but the company has blurred those boundaries over time, perhaps without even recognizing the extent to which they have done so.</p>
<p>It is undeniable that the Google search results pages of today look nothing like they did when the company went public in 2004. The list of 10 “organic” results with three paid listings on the top and a sidebar of advertising results on the right that once characterized Google are long gone.</p>
<p>Dutch search engine consultant <a href="https://www.edwords.nl/2014/04/27/steeds-meer-ruimte-adwords-ten-koste-van-seo/">Eduard Blacquière documented the changes in size and placement of adwords</a> (link in Dutch), the pay-per-click advertisements that run alongside searches, between 2010 and 2014. Here’s a page he captured in June 2010, the result for a search for the word “autoverzekering” (“auto insurance” in Dutch).</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/09/figure1.jpg" alt="Changes in size and placement of AdWords"><figcaption>Changes in size and placement of AdWords. Screengrab: Eduard Blacquière.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Note that the adwords at the top of the page have a background tint, and those at the side have a narrower column width, setting both off clearly from the organic results. Take a quick glance at this page, and your eye can quickly jump to the organic results while ignoring the ads if that’s what you prefer.</p>
<p>Here is Blacquière’s dramatization of the change in size of that top block of adwords. As you can see, the ad block has both dramatically changed in size and lost its background color between 2010 and 2019, making it much harder to distinguish ads from organic results.</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/09/figure2.jpg" alt="harder to distinguish ads from organic results"><figcaption>Harder to distinguish ads from organic results. Screengrab: Eduard Blacquière.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Today, paid results can push organic results almost off the screen, so that the searcher has to scroll down to see them at all. On mobile pages with advertisements, this is almost always the case. Blacquière also documented the result of several studies done over a five-year period, which found the likelihood of a click on the first organic search result fell from over 40% in 2010 to less than 20% in 2014. This shows that through changes in homepage design alone, Google was able to shift significant attention from organic search results to ads.</p>
<p>Not only is paid advertising supplanting organic search results, but for more and more queries, Google itself has now collected enough information to provide what it considers to be the best answer directly to the consumer, eradicating the need to send us to a third-party website at all.</p>
<p>That’s the box that often appears above the search results when you ask a question, such as <em>What are the lyrics to “Don’t Stop Believing,”</em> or <em>What date did WWII end?; </em>the box to the right that pops up with restaurant reviews and opening hours; or a series of visual cards midway down the screen that show you the actors who appeared in a movie or different kinds of pastries common to a geographic region.</p>
<p>Where does this information come from? In 2010, with <a href="https://googleblog.blogspot.com/2010/07/deeper-understanding-with-metaweb.html">the acquisition of Metaweb</a>, Google committed to a project it called “the knowledge graph,” a collection of facts about well-known entities such as places, people, and events. This knowledge graph provides immediate answers for many of the most common queries.</p>
<p>The knowledge graph was initially culled from the web by ingesting information from sources such as Wikipedia, Wikidata, and the CIA Factbook, but since then, it has become far more encyclopedic and has ingested information from all over the web. In 2016, Google CEO Sundar Pichai claimed that the Google knowledge graph contained more than 70 billion facts.</p>
<p>As shown in the figure below, for a popular search that has commercial potential, like <em>visit Yellowstone</em>, not only is the search results page dominated by paid search results (ads) and content directly supplied by Google, but Google’s “answer boxes” are themselves filled with links to other Google pages rather than to third-party websites. (Note that Google personalizes results and also runs hundreds of thousands of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A/B_testing">A/B tests</a> a day on the effect of minor changes in position, so your own results for this identical search may have different results than are shown here.)</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/09/figure3.png" alt="google search results"><figcaption>Google search results. Screengrab: Tim O&#8217;Reilly.</figcaption></figure>
<p>As of March 2017, user clickstream data provided by web analytics firm Jumpshot suggests that <a href="https://moz.com/blog/state-of-searcher-behavior-revealed">up to 40% of all Google queries no longer result in a click through to an external website</a>. Think of all the questions you go to Google for that no longer require a second click: what’s the weather? What’s the current value of the euro against the dollar? What’s that song that’s playing in the background? What’s the best local restaurant? Biographies of eminent people, descriptions of cities, neighborhoods, businesses, historical events, quotes by famous authors, song lyrics, stock prices, and flight times all now appear as immediate answers from Google.</p>
<p>I am not necessarily suggesting anti-competitive intent. Google claims, with considerable justice, that all of these changes to search engine result pages are designed to improve user experience. And indeed, it is often helpful to get an immediate answer to a query rather than having to click through to another web site. Furthermore, much of this data is in fact licensed. But these deals seem like a step backward from the perfect competition represented by Google’s original reliance on multi-factor search algorithms to surface the very best information from independent web sites.</p>
<p>The net effect on Google’s financial performance is striking. In 2004, the year that Google went public, it had two principal advertising revenue engines: Adwords (those pay-per-click advertisements that run alongside searches on Google’s own site) and Adsense (pay-per-click advertisements that Google places on third-party websites on their behalf, either in search results on their site or directly alongside their content). In 2004, the two revenue sources were very close to equal. But by 2018, Google’s revenue from advertising on its own properties <a href="https://qz.com/1540608/the-problem-with-silicon-valleys-obsession-with-blitzscaling-growth/">had grown to 82% of its total advertising revenue, with only 18% coming from the advertising it provides on third–party sites</a>.</p>
<p>These examples illustrate the power of a platform to shape, both by placement on the screen and algorithmic priority, the pages users click on and the products they decide to buy—and therefore also the economic success for the supply side of its marketplace. Google maintains a rigorous separation between the search and advertising teams, but despite that fact, changes in the layout of Google’s pages and its algorithms have played an enormous role in shaping the attention of its users to favor those who advertise with Google.</p>
<p>When Google decides unilaterally on the size and position that its own products take on the screen, it also stops consumers from organically deciding what content to click on or what socks to buy. That’s what antitrust regulators should be considering: whether the algorithmic and design control exerted by sites like Google or Amazon reduces the choices we have as consumers.</p>
<h2>Maintaining the illusion of choice</h2>
<p>If Google has monopolized our access to information, Amazon’s fast-growing advertising business is now shaping what products consumers are actually given to choose from. Have they, too, taken a bite from the poisoned apple of advertising’s mixed motives?</p>
<p>Like Google, Amazon used to rely heavily on the collective intelligence of its users to recommend the best products from its suppliers. It did this by using information such as the supplier-provided description of the product, the number and quality of reviews, the number of inbound links, the sales rank of similar products, and so on, to determine the order in which search results would appear. These were all factored into Amazon’s default search ranking, which put products that were considered “Most Popular” first.</p>
<p>But as with Google, this eden of internet collective intelligence may be in danger of coming to an end.</p>
<p>In the example below, you can see that the default search for “best science fiction books” on Amazon now turns up only “Featured” (i.e., paid for) products. Are these the results you’d expect from this search? Where are the Hugo and Nebula award winners? Where are the books and authors with thousands of five-star reviews?</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/09/figure4.png" alt="Amazon science fiction books"><figcaption>Amazon science fiction books. Screengrab: Tim O&#8217;Reilly.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Contrast these results for those for the same search on Google, shown in the figure below. A knowledgeable science-fiction fan might quibble with some of these selections, but this is indeed a list of widely acknowledged classics in the field. In this case, Google presents no advertising, and so the results instead simply reflect the collective intelligence of what the web thinks is best.</p>
<p>While this might be taken as a reflection of the superiority of Google’s search algorithms over Amazon’s, the more important point is to note how differently a platform treats results when it has no particular commercial axe to grind.</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/09/figure5.png" alt="How differently a platform treats results when it has no particular commercial axe to grind"><figcaption>How differently a platform treats results when it has no particular commercial axe to grind. Screengrab: Tim O&#8217;Reilly.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Amazon has long claimed that the company is <a href="https://www.inc.com/greg-satell/the-secret-behind-amazons-uncanny-ability-to-out-innovate-just-about-every-other-company-on-planet.html">fanatically focused on the needs of its customers</a>. A search like the one shown above, which favors paid results, demonstrates how far the quest for advertising dollars takes them from that avowed goal.</p>
<h2>Advice for antitrust regulators</h2>
<p>So, how are we therefore best to decide if these Big Tech platforms need to be regulated?</p>
<p>In one famous exchange, Bill Gates, the founder and former CEO of Microsoft, <a href="https://stratechery.com/2018/the-bill-gates-line/">told Chamath Palihapitiya</a>, the one-time head of the Facebook platform:</p>
<blockquote><p>“This isn’t a platform. A platform is when the economic value of everybody that uses it exceeds the value of the company that creates it. Then it’s a platform.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Given this understanding of the role of a platform, regulators should be looking to measure whether companies like Amazon or Google are continuing to provide opportunity for their ecosystem of suppliers, or if they’re increasing their own returns at the expense of that ecosystem.</p>
<p>Rather than just asking whether consumers benefit in the short term from the companies’ actions, regulators should be looking at the long-term health of the marketplace of suppliers—they are the real source of that consumer benefit, not the platforms alone. Have Amazon, Apple, or Google <em>earned</em> their profits, or are they coming from monopolistic rents?</p>
<p>How might we know whether a company operating an algorithmically managed marketplace is extracting rents rather than simply taking a reasonable cut for the services it provides? The first sign may not be that it is raising prices for consumers, but that it is taking a larger percentage from its suppliers, or competing unfairly with them.</p>
<p>Before antitrust authorities look to remedies like breaking up these companies, a good first step would be to require disclosure of information about the growth and health of the supply side of their marketplaces. The statistics about the growth of its third-party marketplace that Bezos trumpeted in his shareholder letter tell only half the story. The questions to ask are who profits, by how much, and how that allocation of rewards is changing over time.</p>
<p>Regulators such as the SEC should require regular financial reporting on the allocation of value between the platform and its marketplace. I have done limited analysis for Google and Amazon based on information provided in their annual public filings, but much of the information required for a rigorous analysis is just not available.</p>
<p>Google provides an annual economic impact report analyzing value provided to its advertisers, but there is no comparable report for the value created for its content suppliers. Nor is there any visibility into the changing fortunes of app suppliers into the Play Store, Google’s Android app marketplace, or into the fortunes of content providers on YouTube.</p>
<p>Questions of who gets what and why must be asked of Amazon’s marketplace and its other operating units, <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/open-source-betrayed-industry-leaders-accuse-amazon-of-playing-a-rigged-game-with-aws-67177bc748b7">including its dominant cloud-computing division</a>, or Apple’s App Store. The role of Facebook’s algorithms in deciding what content appears in its readers’ newsfeeds has been widely scrutinized with regard to political bias and manipulation by hostile actors, but there’s been little rigorous economic analysis of <em>economic bias</em> in the algorithms of any of these companies.</p>
<p>Data is the currency of these companies. It should also be the currency of those looking to regulate them. You cannot regulate what you don’t understand. The algorithms that these companies use may be defended as trade secrets, but their outcomes should be open to inspection.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/antitrust-regulators-are-using-the-wrong-tools-to-break-up-big-tech/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Iterative competition is a catalyst for better problem solving</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/iterative-competition-is-a-catalyst-for-better-problem-solving/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/iterative-competition-is-a-catalyst-for-better-problem-solving/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 19:44:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anthony Goldbloom]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AI & ML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5392</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Most people think of machine learning competitions in connection with Kaggle, but there’s a lot more to the platform. In this presentation, Kaggle founder and CEO Anthony Goldbloom talks about how the company grew from a few platform members to more than two million, and how and why it expanded beyond competitions. Highlights from Goldbloom’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most people think of machine learning competitions in connection with Kaggle, but there’s a lot more to the platform. In this presentation, Kaggle founder and CEO Anthony Goldbloom talks about how the company grew from a few platform members to more than two million, and how and why it expanded beyond competitions.</p>
<p>Highlights from Goldbloom’s presentation include:</p>
<p>Kaggle competitions show that iterative competition is a catalyst for better problem solving. Goldbloom notes that the live public leaderboard has a significant direct impact on performance, with competitors continually trying to one-up one another. “It&#8217;s a very efficient way to not draw a false conclusion on a problem,” Golbloom says. “And you know once you&#8217;ve run a competition, you&#8217;re at the limit of what&#8217;s possible.” (<a href="#t=285">4:45</a>)</p>
<p>The public rankings of competitors in the Kaggle competitions aren’t just good for bragging rights &#8212; the rankings are becoming a widely recognized machine learning credential. Goldbloom shares an example of Kaggle competitor “Giba,” who was ranked number 2 and in constant battle for first place: “ Giba, whose real name is Gilberto, is from Brazil. He was an electrical engineer at Petrobras. As a result of his performances on Kaggle, he got poached by Airbnb. And that is the case for a lot of the people in the top couple hundred on Kaggle.” (<a href="#t=457">7:37</a>)</p>
<p>The Kaggle team noticed that users were trying to share code and tutorials in their forum environments, which weren’t ideal (static code, missing libraries, and language version issues were just a few of the issues). So, Goldbloom explains, they launched Kaggle Kernels to facilitate sharing code, and then expanded to allow users to share full data sets, analysis related to &#8212; or even unrelated to &#8212; competitions, and to offer short tutorial courses. (<a href="#t=646">10:46</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/iterative-competition-is-a-catalyst-for-better-problem-solving/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Use technology to do what you do better</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-technology-to-do-what-you-do-better/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-technology-to-do-what-you-do-better/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 18:18:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Lessin and Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation & Disruption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5382</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In this presentation, Tim O’Reilly sits down with Jessica Lessin, founder and editor-in-chief of the technology website The Information. They discuss the impact of technology on industry, issues around venture capital, and how companies should approach new technology. Highlights from Lessin’s and O’Reilly’s discussion include: We’re headed toward a period of innovation decentralization from the [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this presentation, Tim O’Reilly sits down with Jessica Lessin, founder and editor-in-chief of the technology website The Information. They discuss the impact of technology on industry, issues around venture capital, and how companies should approach new technology.</p>
<p>Highlights from Lessin’s and O’Reilly’s discussion include:</p>
<p>We’re headed toward a period of innovation decentralization from the big tech companies, Lessin predicts, as many of these companies are facing increased PR/public perception and/or regulatory issues&#8211;issues that might give startup entrepreneurs reason to pause before teaming up. “And the funding is still flush for startups that want to take big swings,” Lessin notes. (<a href="#t=153">2:33</a>)</p>
<p>The democratization of value is going to be the next big wave. There’s a lot of hype&#8211;as well as skepticism&#8211;around blockchain and cryptocurrency technologies, but Lessin thinks we’re in the early days of something very big that we haven’t quite identified yet. “We&#8217;ve lived through what technology has done to information, and just how the internet has busted that open. I think it will do the same for money, for value, and I think that&#8217;s a really, really big idea that goes beyond blockchain applications or particular cryptocurrencies.” (<a href="#t=232">3:52</a>)</p>
<p>In the mid-2000s, the news industry panicked as it saw the rise of Google and Facebook, and did an ill-fated 180 with its business model, shifting the focus to online advertising and measuring clicks. “If the media business instead said, ‘OK, this technology, this new distribution is very powerful&#8211;how do we use it to become better at what we&#8217;re good at,’ which is original reporting, we&#8217;d be in a different place. … As an industry, instead of talking about Facebook and first click free and Google for a decade, we had instead been talking about how to use technology to literally do our jobs better, just imagine the reporting that would have happened.” (<a href="#t=610">10:10</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-technology-to-do-what-you-do-better/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>We need more than innovation to build a world that’s prosperous for all</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/we-need-more-than-innovation-to-build-a-world-thats-prosperous-for-all/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/we-need-more-than-innovation-to-build-a-world-thats-prosperous-for-all/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 19:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5422</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In this talk, Tim O’Reilly, Founder and CEO of O&#8217;Reilly Media, uses the principle of “gradual, then suddenly” as a means to explain how we can reconcile technological advancements with the evolution of human society, and to understand that those two things drive each other forward, feeding off the momentum of one another. Highlights from [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this talk, Tim O’Reilly, Founder and CEO of O&#8217;Reilly Media, uses the principle of “gradual, then suddenly” as a means to explain how we can reconcile technological advancements with the evolution of human society, and to understand that those two things drive each other forward, feeding off the momentum of one another.</p>
<p>Highlights from O’Reilly’s presentation include:</p>
<p>Technological change happens gradually, then suddenly. Understanding this “gradual, then suddenly” principle is key to understanding why innovation isn’t enough when the world and technology need to get on the same page; “sometimes the world has to catch up to an idea,” O’Reilly notes. (<a href="#t=17">00:17</a>)</p>
<p>Algorithmically designed marketplaces are the future of the economy &#8212; we need to figure out how to make a good one. “There&#8217;s a lot for us to learn about the economy from the way that technology platforms are forced to weigh the value they allocate to different participants,” O’Reilly argues. “If you realize that that&#8217;s what we&#8217;re doing in the choices we make, you make better choices. (<a href="#t=931">15:31</a>)</p>
<p>AI technology won’t replace human work. Quoting Nick Hanauer, O’Reilly argues that humans won’t run out of work until we run out of problems. O’Reilly explains: “And then, gradually then suddenly, guess what: there are a lot of problems we&#8217;re starting to wake up to. The climate is changing. We need to find new ways to generate energy. We have to re-think transportation. We have to find new ways to feed the world. Hundreds of millions of people will need to be relocated. We need to fix the mess we&#8217;ve created.” (<a href="#t=1260">21:00</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/we-need-more-than-innovation-to-build-a-world-thats-prosperous-for-all/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to get things done in a large organization</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:19:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Cutts]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5396</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The nature of work and how business gets done is rapidly changing in the digital age. In this presentation, Matt Cutts, acting director for the United States Digital Service and former software engineer at Google, reminds people it is possible to cut through the red tape at large organizations to get stuff done for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The nature of work and how business gets done is rapidly changing in the digital age. In this presentation, Matt Cutts, acting director for the United States Digital Service and former software engineer at Google, reminds people it is possible to cut through the red tape at large organizations to get stuff done for the betterment of customers and end-users.</p>
<p>Highlights from Cutts’ presentation include:</p>
<p>It’s crucial for large organizations to choose a North Star &#8212; a vision and reason for why they uniquely exist. This North Star informs the company’s strategies and goals. For example, at Google it was to organize the world’s information and make it accessible. Every project and effort by the people employed at Google was in service of this vision. Without this, employees are just reactive and working in a vacuum. (<a href="#t=57">00:57</a>)</p>
<p>Emotion plays a large role in the collective ability to get things done. Emotions, such as fear, can create obstacles and prevent an organization from accomplishing its goals. Strong negative emotions can make organizations risk averse, or create incentives for people to not want the responsibility of failure. The fear of risk ends up being worse than the actual risk. Trust and empathy, on the other hand, can lead to powerful results. (<a href="#t=144">02:24</a>)</p>
<p>Talking to your users is the most powerful hack you can deploy in the fight to get things done within large organizations. Veterans’ Affairs (VA) discovered there was a gap between its mission to deliver an exceptional customer experience and what veterans had to say about actually navigating the bureaucracy. But, by finally talking to veterans, it allowed the VA to take action in the service of its mission. (<a href="#t=413">06:53</a>)</p>
<p>You can see Cutts’ complete presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Balance your ecosystem to succeed at business</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 21:10:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Baldwin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5410</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In this talk, O’Reilly President Laura Baldwin describes how O’Reilly’s mission-driven approach works, and she outlines why companies should apply a balanced strategy for running their organizations. Highlights from Baldwin’s presentation include: Many companies think about their businesses as a set of three things: customers, employees, and shareholders. These are important, but if you&#8217;re only [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this talk, O’Reilly President Laura Baldwin describes how O’Reilly’s mission-driven approach works, and she outlines why companies should apply a balanced strategy for running their organizations.</p>
<p>Highlights from Baldwin’s presentation include:</p>
<p>Many companies think about their businesses as a set of three things: customers, employees, and shareholders. These are important, but if you&#8217;re only thinking about these things in isolation, you&#8217;re not considering your entire ecosystem. (<a href="#t=217">3:37</a>)</p>
<p>An ecosystem approach means the communities O’Reilly serves need to be part of the thought process. This includes customers, contributors, business partners, vendors, and competitors. O’Reilly aims to keep all of these constituents in balance. (<a href="#t=515">8:35</a>)</p>
<p>O’Reilly’s online learning platform has an ecosystem of talent because the company thinks about what the talent needs, not just what O’Reilly needs. This focus ultimately benefits customers. (<a href="#t=968">16:08</a>)</p>
<p>Baldwin is an an avid reader of business books, but she says many of them over-complicate things. Paying attention to your whole ecosystem and keeping it in balance is the way you succeed. (<a href="#t=1184">19:44</a>)</p>
<p>Watch Baldwin’s full presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Making Facebook a scapegoat is a mistake</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/making-facebook-a-scapegoat-is-a-mistake/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/making-facebook-a-scapegoat-is-a-mistake/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Radar Analysis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/making-facebook-a-scapegoat-is-a-mistake/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Chris Hughes, a co-founder of Facebook, recently wrote an opinion piece for the New York Times presenting an argument for breaking up Facebook. I was trying to stay out of this discussion, and Nick Clegg&#8217;s response pretty much summed up my opinions. But I got one too many emails from friends that simply assumed I&#8217;d [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Chris Hughes, a co-founder of Facebook, recently wrote an opinion piece for the <em>New York Times</em> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html">presenting an argument for breaking up Facebook</a>. I was trying to stay out of this discussion, and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/11/opinion/facebook-nick-clegg-chris-hughes.html">Nick Clegg&#8217;s response</a> pretty much summed up my opinions. But I got one too many emails from friends that simply assumed I&#8217;d be in agreement with Chris, especially given <a href="https://qz.com/1540608/the-problem-with-silicon-valleys-obsession-with-blitzscaling-growth/">my critique of blitzscaling</a> and Silicon Valley&#8217;s obsession with &#8220;world domination.&#8221;</p>
<p>If Facebook should be broken up, it should be on grounds of anticompetitive behavior, and Chris barely even touches on that topic. Dragging in the history of all Facebook&#8217;s various corporate missteps <em>for which a breakup would provide no remedy</em> just muddies the water and lets everyone think that punishment has been done. It&#8217;s actually a way of NOT solving the actual problems. Breaking up Facebook won&#8217;t solve the disinformation problem. It won&#8217;t solve the privacy problem. It might well make it harder for Facebook to work on those problems.</p>
<p>In addition, if harm to our society is sufficient reason for a breakup, there are a lot of companies ahead of Facebook in the queue. Big banks. The pharma companies that brought us the opioid crisis. The energy cartel that&#8217;s still fighting against responding to climate change 70 years after the warning bells were sounded.</p>
<p>Even if you restrict yourself to surveillance capitalism, picking out one high-profile malefactor, issuing draconian punishment, and then going back to business as usual everywhere else is a lose-lose, not a win. Facebook is not at the root of this problem, nor even the worst offender. To solve this problem, we need to look not only beyond Facebook, but also beyond the entire tech industry. Banks and telcos are often worse privacy offenders than Google or Facebook. And if you restrict yourself to harm from disinformation, polarization, and radicalization, Twitter and YouTube are just as culpable and, out of the spotlight, appear to be doing less than Facebook to police their problems. Reddit is far worse, and traditional media outlets, especially the Fox News empire, almost as bad. (See Yochai Benkler&#8217;s excellent book on <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Network-Propaganda-Manipulation-Disinformation-Radicalization/dp/0190923636">Network Disinformation</a>.)</p>
<p>Yes, Facebook has scale, but even there, I thought Chris&#8217; arguments were weak. In particular, I found the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html"><em>New York Times</em> infographic</a> to be quite disingenuous:</p>
<figure class="center" id="id-6nGie"><img alt="facebook breaking up infographic" src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/06/Tim_screenshot-cc98c69fd11a6f979f41a3aebcbf5715.png"><figcaption><span class="label">Figure 1. </span>Screenshot of the infographic on <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html">Chris Hughes&#8217; opinion piece in the <em>New York Times</em></a>.</figcaption></figure>
<p>What&#8217;s wrong with this infographic? It lists all of Facebook&#8217;s properties, including those that are primarily messaging, while limiting the competition purely to social media, and failing to include other messaging products. Take out WhatsApp and Messenger, and Facebook suddenly doesn&#8217;t look so big. Or add in other messaging products from companies like Apple, Google, Microsoft, and plain old SMS, and again, suddenly Facebook doesn&#8217;t look so dominant. Add in Google&#8217;s other properties besides YouTube, especially those like search and the new newsfeed on Android phones that influence what people see and understand about the world. Restrict it to the individual national markets where the competition actually happens, and it would look different again. This isn&#8217;t analysis. This is polemics.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not saying there aren&#8217;t grounds for investigation of anticompetitive behavior in the tech industry, or by Facebook specifically, but if someone&#8217;s going to talk breakup, I&#8217;d love to see reporting and opinion pieces that make a true antitrust case, if there is one.</p>
<p>If the world really wants to tackle the problems that networked media creates or amplifies, making Facebook a scapegoat and letting everyone else off the hook is a massive mistake.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/making-facebook-a-scapegoat-is-a-mistake/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>The fundamental problem with Silicon Valley’s favorite growth strategy</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-fundamental-problem-with-silicon-valleys-favorite-growth-strategy/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-fundamental-problem-with-silicon-valleys-favorite-growth-strategy/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Radar Analysis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-fundamental-problem-with-silicon-valleys-favorite-growth-strategy/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The pursuit of monopoly has led Silicon Valley astray. Look no further than the race between Lyft and Uber to dominate the online ride-hailing market. Both companies are gearing up for their IPOs in the next few months. Street talk has Lyft shooting for a valuation between $15 and $30 billion dollars, and Uber valued [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The pursuit of monopoly has led Silicon Valley astray.</p>
<p>Look no further than the race between Lyft and Uber to dominate the online ride-hailing market. Both companies are gearing up for their IPOs in the next few months. Street talk has <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bizcarson/2018/12/06/lyft-confidentially-files-for-ipo-to-try-to-beat-uber-to-the-public-market/#5314223415a2">Lyft shooting for a valuation between $15 and $30 billion dollars</a>, and <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-uber-ipo/uber-ipo-proposals-value-company-at-120-billion-wsj-idUSKCN1MQ1N8">Uber valued at an astonishing $120 billion dollars</a>. Neither company is profitable; their enormous valuations are based on the premise that if a company grows big enough and fast enough, profits will eventually follow.</p>
<p>Most monopolies or duopolies develop over time, and have been considered <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Curse-Bigness-Antitrust-New-Gilded/dp/0999745468">dangerous to competitive markets</a>; now they are sought after from the start and are the holy grail for investors. If LinkedIn co-founder Reid Hoffman and entrepreneur Chris Yeh’s new book <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Blitzscaling-Lightning-Fast-Building-Massively-Companies/dp/1524761419">Blitzscaling</a></em> is to be believed, the Uber-style race to the top (or the bottom, depending on your point of view) is <em>the</em> secret of success for today’s technology businesses.</p>
<p><em>Blitzscaling</em> promises to teach techniques that are “the lightning-fast path to building massively valuable companies.” Hoffman and Yeh argue that in today’s world, it’s essential to “achieve massive scale at incredible speed” in order to seize the ground before competitors do. By their definition, blitzscaling (derived from the blitzkrieg or “lightning war” strategy of Nazi general Heinz Guderian) “prioritizes speed over efficiency,” and risks “potentially disastrous defeat in order to maximize speed and surprise.”</p>
<p>Many of these businesses depend on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_effect">network effects</a>, which means the company that gets to scale first is likely to stay on top. So, for startups, this strategy typically involves raising a lot of capital and moving quickly to dominate a new market, even when the company’s leaders may not know how they are going to make money in the long term.</p>
<p>This premise has become doctrine in Silicon Valley. But is it correct? And is it good for society? I have my doubts.</p>
<p>Imagine, for a moment, a world in which Uber and Lyft hadn’t been able to raise billions of dollars in a winner-takes-all race to dominate the online ride-hailing market. How might that market have developed differently?</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>Blitzscaling isn’t really a recipe for success but rather survivorship bias masquerading as a strategy.</p></blockquote>
<p>Uber and Lyft have developed powerful services that delight their users and are transforming urban transportation. But if they hadn’t been given virtually unlimited capital to offer rides at subsidized prices taxicabs couldn’t match in order to grow their user base at blitzscaling speed, would they be offering their service for less than it actually costs to deliver? Would each company be <a href="https://medium.com/@AsherOfLA/ubers-balance-sheet-says-we-re-not-a-tech-company-e3b6a9561d14">spending 55% of net revenue</a> on driver incentives, passenger discounts, sales, and marketing to acquire passengers and drivers faster than the other? Would these companies now be profitable instead of <a href="https://news.crunchbase.com/news/understanding-uber-loses-money/">hemorrhaging billions of dollars a year</a>? Would incumbent transportation companies have had more time to catch up, leading to a more competitive market? Might drivers have gotten a bigger share of the pie? Would a market that grew more organically—like the web, e-commerce, smartphones, or mobile mapping services—have created more value over the long term?</p>
<p>We’ll never know, because investors, awash in cheap capital, anointed the winners rather than letting the market decide who should succeed and who should fail. This created a de-facto duopoly long before either company had proven that it has a sustainable business model. And because these two giants are now locked in a capital-fueled deathmatch, the market is largely closed off to new ideas except from within the existing, well-funded companies.</p>
<h2>The case for blitzscaling</h2>
<p>There are plenty of reasons to believe that blitzscaling makes sense. The internet is awash in billionaires who made their fortunes by following a strategy summed up in Mark Zuckerberg’s advice to <a href="https://www.inc.com/zoe-henry/mark-zuckerberg-move-fast-and-break-things.html">“move fast and break things.”</a> Hoffman and Yeh invoke the storied successes of Apple, Microsoft, Amazon, Google, and Facebook, all of whom have dominated their respective markets and made their founders rich in the process, and suggest that it is blitzscaling that got them there. And the book tells compelling tales of current entrepreneurs who have outmaneuvered competitors by pouring on the gas and moving more quickly. Hoffman recalls his own success with the blitzscaling philosophy during the early days of Paypal. Back in 2000, the company was growing 5% per day, letting people settle their charges using credit cards while using the service for free. This left the company to absorb, ruinously, the 3% credit card charge on each transaction. He writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>I remember telling my old college friend and Paypal co-founder/CEO Peter Thiel, &#8216;Peter, if you and I were standing on the roof of our office and throwing stacks of hundred-dollar bills off the edge as fast as our arms could go, we still wouldn’t be losing money as quickly as we are right now.&#8217;</p></blockquote>
<p>But it worked out. Paypal built an enormous user base quickly, giving the company enough market power to charge businesses to accept Paypal payments. They also persuaded most customers to make those payments via direct bank transfers, which have much lower fees than credit cards. If they’d waited to figure out the business model, someone else might have beat them to the customer that made them a success: eBay, which <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/ebay-picks-up-paypal-for-1-5-billion/">went on to buy Paypal for $1.5 billion</a> (which everyone thought was a lot of money in those days), launching Thiel and Hoffman on their storied careers as serial entrepreneurs and investors.</p>
<p>Of course, for every company like Paypal that pulled off that feat of hypergrowth without knowing where the money would come from, there is a dotcom graveyard of hundreds or thousands of companies that never figured it out. That’s the “risks potentially disastrous defeat” part of the strategy that Hoffman and Yeh talk about. A strong case can be made that blitzscaling isn’t really a recipe for success but rather <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias">survivorship bias</a> masquerading as a strategy.</p>
<p>However, Hoffman and Yeh do a good job of explaining the conditions in which blitzscaling makes sense: The market has to be really big; there has to be a sustainable competitive advantage (e.g., network effects) from getting bigger faster than the competition; you have to have efficient means to bootstrap distribution; and you have to have high gross margins so the business will generate positive cash flow and profits when it does get to scale. This is good management advice for established companies as well as startups, and the book is chock full of it.</p>
<p>Hoffman and Yeh also make the point that what most often drives the need for blitzscaling is competition; an entrepreneur with a good idea can be too close to the center of the bullseye, inevitably drawing imitators. The book opens with an excellent tale of how Airbnb used blitzscaling to respond to the threat of a European copycat company by raising money to open and aggressively expand its own European operations years before the company would otherwise have chosen to do so.</p>
<p>But sometimes it isn’t just the threat of competition that drives the need to turbocharge growth: it’s the size and importance of the opportunity, and the need to get big fast enough to effect change. For example, you can make the case that if Uber and Lyft and Airbnb hadn’t blitzscaled, they would have been tied up in bureaucratic red tape, and the future they are trying to build wouldn’t just have happened more slowly; it would never have happened.</p>
<p>The strategic use of blitzscaling isn’t limited to startups. It can also apply to large companies, governments, and even nonprofits. For example, we’re facing a blitzscaling opportunity right now at <a href="https://www.codeforamerica.org/">Code for America</a>, the non-profit founded and run by my wife Jennifer Pahlka, and on whose board I serve.</p>
<p>Our mission is to use the principles and practices of the digital age to improve how government serves the American public, and how the public improves government. Since Code for America is a non-profit, we aren’t trying to “take the market.” There’s no financial imperative to seize an opportunity before someone else does. Our goal is to show what’s possible, to build a constituency and a consensus for a change in the way government does things, and to encourage the development of an ecosystem of new vendors who can work with government the same way we do. By demonstrating that the work of government can be done quickly and cheaply at massive scale using open source software, machine learning, and other 21st-century technology, we look to shape the expectations of the market.</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>Emulating the tortoise, not the hare, has been our goal. We’ve always preferred opportunities where time is an ally, not an enemy.</p></blockquote>
<p>So why is blitzscaling relevant to us? It’s not about making millions and snuffing out the competition—as in many of the most compelling cases for blitzscaling—it’s about building enough momentum to break through the stone walls of an old established order. In our case, we are attempting to save taxpayers money and radically alter the lives of millions of Americans.</p>
<p>Here’s a concrete example: one of the areas we’ve gotten deeply involved in is criminal justice reform. Specifically, we’re helping governments implement new laws and initiatives to redress 30 years of over-aggressive policy that has left <a href="https://www.politifact.com/new-york/statements/2017/aug/18/andrew-cuomo/yes-one-three-us-adults-have-criminal-record/">almost 70 million Americans with some kind of criminal record</a> and <a href="http://www.ncsl.org/research/civil-and-criminal-justice/federal-criminal-justice-reform-in-2018.aspx">2.2 million behind bars</a>. (That’s <a href="https://www.sentencingproject.org/criminal-justice-facts/">the highest percentage in the world</a>.) A broad consensus is emerging on both left and right that it’s time to rethink our criminal justice system.</p>
<p>Too often, though, those passing new laws have given insufficient thought to their implementation, leaving existing bureaucratic processes in place. For example, to clear a criminal record under 2014’s <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/California_Proposition_47,_Reduced_Penalties_for_Some_Crimes_Initiative_(2014)">California Proposition 47</a>, which reduced the penalty for many crimes by reclassifying them as misdemeanors rather than felonies, a person must go to the District Attorney’s office in each jurisdiction where he or she has a record, ask the DA to download their rap sheet, determine eligibility by assessing the obscure codes on the rap sheet, and, if eligible, petition the court for clearance. Facing such a cumbersome, expensive process, only a few thousands of those eligible were able to clear their records.</p>
<p>After the passage in 2016 of <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/California_Proposition_64,_Marijuana_Legalization_(2016)">California Proposition 64</a>, which decriminalized marijuana and added millions to the rolls of those who had criminal records eligible to be expunged, San Francisco District Attorney George Gascon announced a program for automatic expungement. The DA’s office would not wait for petitioners to appear, but would preemptively download and evaluate all eligible records. Unfortunately, lacking technology expertise, Gascon’s office set out to do it with manual labor, hiring paralegals to download and evaluate the rap sheets and file the necessary paperwork with the courts.</p>
<p>When we demonstrated that we could download the records in bulk and automate the evaluation of rap sheets, working through thousands of records in minutes and automatically generating the paperwork for clearance, they were all in. True automatic expungement looks like a real possibility. Now we aim to scale up our team to support the entire state in this ambitious program.</p>
<p>So what’s the rush? The first reason for urgency is the human toll we can alleviate by getting the work done more quickly. When people can clear their records, it gives them better access to jobs, subsidized housing, and many other benefits.</p>
<p>The second reason is that many other states are also reducing sentences and pushing for record clearance. While we’ve already got our <a href="https://www.clearmyrecord.org/">Clear My Record</a> project well underway in California, other states are turning to legacy vendors working through legacy procurement processes. If existing vendors exploit this opportunity and persuade states to sign traditional contracts before we show how cheaply and effectively the job can be done, millions of dollars in public money may be wasted doing it the old way, and years of delay in implementation are at stake. (These contracts typically cost hundreds of millions of dollars and take years to deliver on.)</p>
<p>So we’re asking ourselves, is it enough to show what’s possible and hope that others do the right thing? Or might we get to our desired outcome more effectively if we scale up our own capability to address the problem? The key question we are wrestling with is “how can we move faster?”—which is exactly the question that Hoffman and Yeh’s book seeks to answer.</p>
<p>In short, there are compelling reasons to blitzscale, and the book provides a great deal of wisdom for those facing a strategic inflection point where success depends on moving much faster. But I worry that the book oversells the idea, and that too many entrepreneurs will believe this is the only way to succeed.</p>
<h2>Why I’m skeptical of blitzscaling</h2>
<p>To understand why I’m skeptical about blitzscaling, you have to understand a bit about my own entrepreneurial history. I started my company, <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/online-learning/try-now.html">O’Reilly Media</a>, 40 years ago with a $500 initial investment. We took in no venture capital, but despite that have built a business that generates hundreds of millions of dollars of profitable annual revenue. We got there through steady, organic growth, funded by customers who love our products and pay us for them.</p>
<p>Emulating the tortoise, not the hare, has been our goal. We’ve always preferred opportunities where time is an ally, not an enemy. That’s not to say that we haven’t had our share of blitzscaling opportunities, but in each of them, we kickstarted a new market and then let others take the baton.</p>
<p>In 1993, my company launched GNN, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_Network_Navigator">Global Network Navigator</a>, which was the first advertising-supported site on the World Wide Web, and the first web portal. We were so early that we had to persuade the world that advertising was the natural business model for this new medium. We plowed every penny we were making from our business writing and publishing computer-programming manuals into GNN—our own version of throwing hundred dollar bills off the rooftop. And for two years, from 1993 until we sold GNN to AOL in mid-1995, we were <em>the</em> place where people went to go to find new websites.</p>
<p>As the commercial web took off, however, it became clear that we couldn’t play by the same rules as we had in the publishing market, where a deep understanding of what customers were looking for, superior products, innovative marketing, and fair prices gave us all the competitive advantages we needed. Here, the market was exploding, and unless we could grow as fast or faster than the market, we’d soon be left behind. And we could see the only way to do that would be to take in massive amounts of capital, with the price of chasing the new opportunity being the loss of control over the company.</p>
<p>Wanting to build a company that I would own and control for the long term, I decided instead to spin out GNN and sell it to AOL. Jerry Yang and David Filo made a different decision at Yahoo!, founded a year after GNN. They <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Yahoo!">took venture capital, blitzscaled their company, and beat AOL to the top of the internet heap</a>—before being dethroned in their turn by Google.</p>
<p>It happened again in 1996 when O’Reilly launched a product called <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19961017231650/http:/website.ora.com:80/">Website</a>, the first commercial Windows-based web server. We’d been drawn to the promise of a web in which everyone was a publisher; instead, websites were being built on big centralized servers, and all most people could do was consume web content via ubiquitous free browsers. So we set out to democratize the web, with the premise that everyone who had a browser should also be able to have a server. Website took off, and became a multimillion-dollar product line for us. But our product was soon eclipsed by Netscape, which had raised tens of millions of dollars of venture capital, and eventually <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netscape">had a multibillion-dollar IPO</a>—before being <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Browser_wars">crushed in turn by Microsoft</a>.</p>
<p>In the case of both GNN and Website, you can see the blitzscaling imperative: a new market is accelerating, and there is a clear choice between keeping up and being left behind. In those two examples, I made a conscious choice against blitzscaling because I had a different vision for my company. But far too many entrepreneurs don’t understand the choice, and are simply overtaken by better-funded competitors who seize the opportunity more boldly. And in too many markets, in the absence of antitrust enforcement, there is always the risk that no matter how much money you raise and how fast you go, the entrenched giants will be able to leverage their existing business to take over the new market you’ve created. That’s what Microsoft did to Netscape, and what <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/copycat-how-facebook-tried-to-squash-snapchat/">Facebook did to Snapchat</a>.</p>
<p>Had we followed Hoffman and Yeh’s advice, we would have taken on a contest we were very unlikely to win, no matter how much money we raised or how fast we moved. And even though we abandoned these two opportunities when the blitzscalers arrived, O’Reilly Media has had enormous financial success, becoming a leader in each of our chosen markets.</p>
<h2>Winning at all costs</h2>
<p>There’s another point that Hoffman and Yeh fail to address. It matters what stories we tell ourselves about what success looks like. Blitzscaling can be used by any company, but it can encourage a particular kind of entrepreneur: hard-charging, willing to crash through barriers, and often ruthless.</p>
<p>We see the consequences of this selection bias in the history of the on-demand ride-hailing market. Why did Uber emerge the winner in the ride-hailing wars? Sunil Paul, the founder of Sidecar, was the visionary who came up with the idea of a peer-to-peer taxi service provided by people using their own cars. Logan Green, the co-founder of Lyft, was the visionary who had set out to reinvent urban transportation by filling all the empty cars on the road. But Travis Kalanick, the co-founder and CEO of Uber, was the hyper-aggressive entrepreneur who raised money faster, broke the rules more aggressively, and cut the most corners in the race to the top.</p>
<p>In 2000, a full eight years before Uber was founded, <a href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect2=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;p=1&amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;d=PALL&amp;RefSrch=yes&amp;Query=PN/6356838">Sunil Paul filed a patent</a> that described many of the possibilities that the newly commercialized GPS capabilities would provide for on-demand car sharing. <a href="https://medium.com/@SunilPaul/the-untold-story-of-ridesharing-3bf812a7cb03">He explored founding a company at that time</a>, but realized that GPS-enabled phones weren’t common enough. It was just too early for his ideas to take hold.</p>
<p>The market Paul had envisioned began, in fits and starts, around 2007. That year, Logan Green and John Zimmer, the founders of Lyft, started a company called Zimride that was inspired by the bottom-up urban jitneys Green had fallen in love with during a trip to Zimbabwe. They began with a web app to match up college students making long-distance trips with others going in the same direction. In 2008, Garrett Camp and Travis Kalanick founded Uber as a high-end service using SMS to summon black-car drivers.</p>
<p>Neither Zimride nor Uber had yet realized the full idea we now think of as smartphone-enabled ride hailing, and each was working toward it from a different end—peer-to-peer, and mobile on-demand respectively. The two ideas were about to meet in an explosive combination, fueled by the wide adoption of GPS-enabled smartphones and app marketplaces. Following the 2007 introduction of the iPhone and, at least as importantly, the 2008 introduction of the iPhone App Store, the iPhone became a platform for mobile applications.</p>
<p>Once again, it was Paul who first saw the future. Inspired by Airbnb’s success in getting ordinary people to rent out their homes, he realized people might also be willing to rent out their cars. He worked on several versions of this idea. <a href="https://medium.com/@SunilPaul/the-untold-tale-of-ridesharing-part-ii-how-the-sharing-got-into-ridesharing-7f69a606eb17">In 2009, while working with the founders of what became Getaround in a class he was teaching at Singularity University</a>, Paul explored peer-to-peer fractional car rental. Then, in 2012, he launched a new company, Sidecar, to provide the equivalent of peer-to-peer taxi service, with ordinary people providing the service using their own cars. He set out to get permission from regulatory agencies for this new approach.</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>There are few small wins for the entrepreneur; only the big bets pay off. And, as in Las Vegas, only the house always wins.</p></blockquote>
<p>Green and Zimmer <a href="https://medium.com/@SunilPaul/the-untold-story-of-ridesharing-part-iii-the-birth-of-sidecar-and-ridesharing-9f6e6c706d8d">heard about Paul’s work on Sidecar</a> and realized immediately that this model could help them realize their original vision for Zimride. They pivoted quickly from their original vision, launching Lyft as a project within Zimride about three months after Sidecar. When Lyft took off, they sold the original Zimride product and went all-in on the new offering. (That’s blitzscaling for you. Seize the ground first.)</p>
<p>Uber was an even more aggressive blitzscaler. Hearing about Lyft’s plans, Uber announced UberX, its down-market version of Uber using ordinary people driving their own cars instead of chauffeurs with limousines, the day before Lyft launched, even though all that it had developed in the way of a peer-to-peer driver platform was a press release. In fact, Kalanick, the co-founder and CEO, had been skeptical about the legality of the peer-to-peer driver model, <a href="https://soundcloud.com/twistartups/travis-kalanick-of-uber-on-2">telling Jason Calacanis</a>, the host of the podcast This Week in Startups, “It would be illegal.”</p>
<p>And the race was on. Despite his earlier reservations about the legality of the model, Uber out-executed its smaller rivals, in part by ignoring regulation while they attempted to change the rules, and became the market leader. Uber also followed the blitzscaling playbook more closely, raising far more money than its rivals, and growing far faster. Lyft managed to become a strong number two. But by 2015, Sidecar was a footnote in history, going out of business after having raised only $35.5 million to Uber’s $7.3 billion and Lyft’s $2 billion. To date, <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/uber/funding_rounds/funding_rounds_list#section-funding-rounds">Uber has raised a total of $24.3 billion</a>, and <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/lyft/funding_rounds/funding_rounds_list#section-funding-rounds">Lyft $4.9 billion</a>.</p>
<p>Hoffman and Yeh embrace this dark pattern as a call to action. Early in their book, Blake, the cynical sales manager played by Alec Baldwin in the movie <em>Glengarry Glen Ross</em>, appears as an oracle dispensing wise advice:</p>
<blockquote><p>As you all know, first prize is a Cadillac Eldorado. Anyone wanna see second prize? Second prize is a set of steak knives. Third prize is you’re fired. Get the picture?</p></blockquote>
<p>In the real world, though, while Sunil Paul’s company went out of business, it was Travis Kalanick of Uber who got fired. Stung by <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/uber-company-scandals-and-controversies-2017-11">scandal after scandal</a> as Uber deceived regulators, spied on passengers, and tolerated a culture of sexual harassment, <a href="https://www.mercurynews.com/2019/01/29/heres-the-uber-investor-letter-that-forced-travis-kalanick-out/">the board eventually asked for Kalanick’s resignation</a>. Not only that, Uber’s worldwide blitzscaling attempts—competing in ride-hailing not only with Lyft in the U.S. but with Didi in China and with Grab and Ola in Southeast Asia, and with Google on self-driving cars—eventually spread the company too thin, just as Guderian’s blitzkrieg techniques, which had worked so well against France and Poland, failed during the invasion of Russia.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the forced bloom of Uber’s market share lead became a liability even in the U.S. Even though Uber had far more money, the price war between the two companies cost Uber far more in markets where its share was large and Lyft’s was small. Lyft focused on the U.S. market and began to chip away at Uber’s early lead. It also made significant gains on Uber as passengers and drivers, stung by the sense that Uber was an amoral company, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/dr-gridlock/wp/2017/05/16/deleteuber-will-have-lasting-fallout-for-ride-hailing-app-study-says/">began to abandon the service</a>. Uber is still the larger and more valuable company, and Dara Khosrowshahi, the new CEO, has made enormous progress in stabilizing its business and restoring its reputation. But Lyft’s gains appear to be sustainable.</p>
<h2>Blitzscaling—or sustainable scaling?</h2>
<p>While Hoffman and Yeh’s book claims that companies like Google, Facebook, Microsoft, Apple, and Amazon are icons of the blitzscaling approach, this idea is plausible only with quite a bit of revisionist history. Each of these companies achieved profitability (or in Amazon’s case, positive cash flow) long before its IPO, and growth wasn’t driven by a blitzkrieg of spending to acquire customers below cost but by breakthrough products and services, and by strategic business model innovations that were rooted in a future the competition didn’t yet understand. These companies didn’t blitzscale; they scaled sustainably.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/google#section-funding-rounds">Google raised only $36 million before its IPO</a>—an amount that earned Sidecar’s Sunil Paul the dismal third prize of going out of business. For that same level of investment, Google was already hugely profitable.</p>
<p>Facebook’s rise to dominance was far more capital-intensive than Google’s. <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/facebook/funding_rounds/funding_rounds_list#section-funding-rounds">The company raised $2.3 billion before its IPO</a>, but it too was already profitable long before it went public; according to insiders, it ran close to breakeven from fairly early in its life. The money raised was strategic, a way of hedging against risk, and of stepping up the valuation of the company while delaying the scrutiny of a public offering. As Hoffman and Yeh note in their book, in today’s market, “Even if the money doesn’t prove to be necessary, a major financing round can have positive signaling effects—it helps convince the rest of the world that your company is likely to emerge as the market leader.”</p>
<p>Even Amazon, which lost billions before achieving profitability, raised only <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/amazon#section-funding-rounds">$108 million in venture capital before its IPO</a>. How was this possible? Bezos realized his business generated enormous positive cash flow that he could borrow against. It was his boldness in taking the risk of borrowing billions (preserving a larger ownership stake for himself and his team than if he had raised billions in equity), not just Amazon’s commitment to growth over profits, that helped make him the world’s richest man today.</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>Winners-take-all is an investment philosophy perfectly suited for our age of inequality and economic fragility.</p></blockquote>
<p>In short, none of these companies (except arguably Amazon) followed the path that Hoffman and Yeh lay out as a recipe for today’s venture-backed companies. Venture-backed blitzscaling was far less important to their success than product and business-model innovation, brilliant execution, and relentless strategic focus. Hypergrowth was the <em>result</em> rather than the <em>cause</em> of these companies’ success.</p>
<p>Ironically, Hoffman and Yeh’s book is full of superb practical advice about innovation, execution, and strategic focus, but it’s wrapped in the flawed promise that startups can achieve similar market dominance as these storied companies by force-feeding inefficient growth.</p>
<p>For a company like Airbnb, a company with both strong network effects and a solid path to profitability, blitzscaling is a good strategy. But blitzscaling also enables too many companies like <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/investing/stock/snap/financials">Snap</a>, which managed to go public while still losing enormous amounts of money, <a href="http://fortune.com/2018/02/23/snapchat-evan-spiegel-ipo/">making its founders and investors rich</a> while <a href="http://thein.fo/6a7abbe36ed12701">passing on to public market investors the risk</a> that the company will never actually become a profitable business. Like Amazon and Airbnb, some of these companies may become sustainable, profitable businesses and grow into their valuation over time, but as of now, they are still bleeding red ink.</p>
<p>Sustainability may not actually matter, though, according to the gospel of blitzscaling. After all, the book’s marketing copy does not promise the secret of building massively profitable or enduring companies, but merely “massively valuable” ones.</p>
<p>What is meant by value? To too many investors and entrepreneurs, it means building companies that achieve massive financial exits, either by being sold or going public. And as long as the company can keep getting financing, either from private or public investors, the growth can go on.</p>
<p>But is a business really a business if it can’t pay its own way?</p>
<h2>Is it a business or a financial instrument?</h2>
<p>Benjamin Graham, the father of value investing, <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=OsDXyPQXBmMC&amp;pg=PT87&amp;dq=benjamin+graham+voting+machine+weighing+machine&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiJ8rWJ4_DfAhVO7lQKHab7DGMQ6AEIMDAB#v=onepage&amp;q=benjamin%20graham%20voting%20machine%20weighing%20machine&amp;f=false">is widely reported to have said</a>: “In the short run, the market is a voting machine. In the long run, it’s a weighing machine.” That is, in the short term, investors vote (or more accurately, place bets) on the present value of the future earnings of a company. Over the long term, the market discovers whether they were right in their bets. (That’s the weighing machine.)</p>
<p>But what is happening today is that the market has almost entirely turned into a betting machine. Not only that, it’s a machine for betting on a horse race in which it’s possible to cash your winning ticket long before the race has actually finished. In the past, entrepreneurs got rich when their companies succeeded and were able to sell shares to the public markets. Increasingly, though, <a href="https://medium.com/@rizstanford/secondary-sales-in-vc-backed-startups-a-quick-primer-for-entrepreneurs-bdc25ea7f39a">investors are allowing insiders to sell their stock much earlier than that</a>. And even when companies do reach the point of a public offering, these days, many of them still have no profits.</p>
<p>According to University of Florida finance professor Jay Ritter, <a href="https://site.warrington.ufl.edu/ritter/files/2018/01/IPOs2017Statistics_January17_2018.pdf">76% of all IPOs in 2017 were for companies with no profits</a>. <a href="https://banyanhill.com/dot-com-bubble-2-ipo-fail/">By October 2018, the percentage was 83%</a>, exceeding even the 81% seen right before the dotcom bust in 2000.</p>
<figure id="id-4xi2w"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/06/US_IPOs-512e9d5588115b6e44840a29fbf0b0e8.jpg"></figure>
<p>Would profitless companies with huge scale be valued so highly in the absence of today’s overheated financial markets?</p>
<p>Too many of the companies likely to follow Hoffman and Yeh’s advice are actually financial instruments instead of businesses, designed by and for speculators. The monetization of the company is sought not via the traditional means of accumulated earnings and the value of a continuing business projecting those earnings into the future, but via the exit, that holy grail of today’s Silicon Valley. The hope is that either the company will be snapped up by another company that does have a viable business model but lacks the spark and sizzle of internet-fueled growth, or will pull off a profitless IPO, like Snap or Box.</p>
<p>The horse-race investment mentality has a terrible side effect: companies that are not contenders to win, place, or show are starved of investment. Funding dries up, and companies that could have built a sustainable niche if they’d grown organically go out of business instead. “Go big or go home” results in many companies that once would have been members of a thriving business ecosystem indeed going home. As Hoffman and Yeh put it:</p>
<blockquote><p>Here is one of the ruthless practices that has helped make Silicon Valley so successful: investors will look at a company that is on an upward trajectory but doesn’t display the proverbial hockey stick of exponential growth and conclude that they need to either sell the business or take on additional risk that might increase the chances of achieving exponential growth&#8230; Silicon Valley venture capitalists want entrepreneurs to pursue exponential growth even if doing so costs more money and increases the chances that the business will fail.</p></blockquote>
<p>Because this blitzscaling model requires raising ever more money in pursuit of the hockey stick venture capitalists are looking for, the entrepreneur’s ownership is relentlessly diluted. Even if the company is eventually sold, unless the company is a breakout hit, most of the proceeds go to investors whose preferred shares must be repaid before the common shares owned by the founders and employees get anything. There are few small wins for the entrepreneur; only the big bets pay off. And, as in Las Vegas, the house always wins.</p>
<p>Bryce Roberts, my partner at <a href="http://oatv.com/">O’Reilly AlphaTech Ventures</a> (OATV), recently wrote about the probability of winning big in business:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">Timely reminder that the VCs aren’t even in the home run business.</p>
<p>They’re in the grand slam business.</p>
<p>Interestingly, odds of hitting a grand slam (.07%) are uncannily similar to odds of backing a unicorn (.07% of VC backed startups) <a href="https://t.co/O0VgCeuAe3">https://t.co/O0VgCeuAe3</a></p>
<p>—indievc (@indievc) <a href="https://twitter.com/indievc/status/1075795023961088002?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 20, 2018</a></p></blockquote>
<p>This philosophy has turned venture capitalists into movie studios, financing hundreds of companies in pursuit of the mega-hit that will make their fund, and at its worst turns entrepreneurs into the equivalent of Hollywood actors, moving from one disposable movie to another. (“The Uber of Parking” is sure to be a hit! And how about “the Uber of Dry Cleaning”?)</p>
<p>The losses from the blitzscaling mentality are felt not just by entrepreneurs but by society more broadly. When the traditional venture-capital wisdom is to shutter companies that aren’t achieving hypergrowth, businesses that would once have made meaningful contributions to our economy are not funded, or are starved of further investment once it is clear that they no longer have a hope of becoming a home run.</p>
<p>Winners-take-all is an investment philosophy perfectly suited for our age of inequality and economic fragility, where a few get enormously rich, and the rest get nothing. In a balanced economy, there are opportunities for success at all scales, from the very small, through successful mid-size companies, to the great platforms.</p>
<p>Is <em>Glengarry Glen Ross</em>’s sales competition really the economy we aspire to?</p>
<h2>There is another way</h2>
<p>There are business models, even in the technology sector, where cash flow from operations can fund the company, not venture capitalists gripping horse-race tickets.</p>
<p>Consider these companies: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mailchimp">Mailchimp</a>, funded by $490 million in annual revenue from its 12 million customers, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/06/technology/mailchimp-and-the-un-silicon-valley-way-to-make-it-as-a-start-up.html">profitable from day one without a penny of venture capital</a>; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlassian">Atlassian</a>, bootstrapped for eight years before raising capital in 2010 after it had reached nearly $75 million in self-funded annual revenue; and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shutterstock">Shutterstock</a>, which took in venture capital only after it had already bootstrapped its way to becoming the largest subscription-based stock photo agency in the world. (In the case of both Atlassian and Shutterstock, outside financing was a step toward liquidity through a public offering, rather than strictly necessary to fund company growth.) All of these companies made their millions through consumer-focused products and patience, not blitzscaling.</p>
<p>Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson, the founders of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basecamp_(company)">Basecamp</a>, a 20-year-old, privately held, profitable Chicago company whose core product is used by millions of software developers, have gone even further: they entirely abandoned the growth imperative, shedding even successful products to keep their company under 50 people. Their book about their approach, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Doesnt-Have-Be-Crazy-Work/dp/0062874780">It Doesn’t Have to Be Crazy At Work</a></em>, should be read as an essential counterpoint to <em>Blitzscaling</em>.</p>
<p>Another story of self-funded growth I particularly like is far from tech. <a href="https://www.rxbar.com/">RxBar</a>, a Chicago-based nutrition bar company with $130 million of self-funded annual revenue, was <a href="https://www.inc.com/magazine/201804/danielle-sacks/rxbar-peter-rahal-exit-interview.html">acquired last year by Kellogg for $600 million</a>. Peter Rahal, one of the two founders, recalls that he and co-founder Jared Smith were in his parents’ kitchen, discussing how they would go about raising capital to start their business. His immigrant father said something like, “<a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/308136">You guys need to shut the fuck up and just sell a thousand bars</a>.”</p>
<p>And that’s exactly what they did, putting in $5,000 each, and hustling to sell their bars via Crossfit gyms. It was that hustle and bias toward customers, rather than outside funding, that got them their win. Their next breakthrough was in their distinctive “No BS” packaging, which made the ingredients, rather than extravagant claims about them, the centerpiece of the message.</p>
<p>The exit for RxBar, when it came, was not the objective, but a strategy for growing a business that was already working. “Jared and I never designed the business to sell it; we designed it to solve a problem for customers,” <a href="https://www.inc.com/magazine/201804/danielle-sacks/rxbar-peter-rahal-exit-interview.html">Rahal recalled</a>. “In January 2017, Jared and I were sitting around and asked what do we want to do with this business? Do we want to continue and make it a family business? Or do we want to roll it up into a greater company, really scale this thing and take it to the next level? We wanted to go put fire on this thing.”</p>
<p>They could have raised growth capital at that point, like Mike Cannon-Brooks of Atlassian or Jon Oringer of Shutterstock did, but acquisition provided a better path to sustainable impact. Kellogg brought them not just an exit, but additional capabilities to grow their business. Rahal continues to lead the brand at Kellogg, still focusing on customers.</p>
<h2>Raise less, own more</h2>
<p>The fact that the Silicon Valley blitzscaling model is not suited for many otherwise promising companies has led a number of venture capitalists, including my partner Bryce Roberts at OATV, to develop an approach for finding, inspiring, and financing cash-flow positive companies.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.indie.vc/">Indie.vc</a>, a project at OATV, has developed <a href="https://github.com/indievc/terms/blob/master/term_sheet_v3.md">a new kind of venture financing instrument</a>. It’s a convertible loan designed to be repaid out of operating cash flow rather than via an exit, but that can convert to equity if the company, having established there is a traditional venture business opportunity, decides to go that route. This optionality effectively takes away the pressure for companies to raise ever more money in pursuit of the hypergrowth that, as Hoffman and Yeh note, traditional venture capitalists are looking for. The program also includes a year of mentorship and networking, providing access to experienced entrepreneurs and experts in various aspects of growing a business.</p>
<p>In the <a href="http://www.indie.vc/faq/">Indie.vc FAQ</a>, Bryce wrote:</p>
<blockquote><p>We believe deeply that there are hundreds, even thousands, of businesses that could be thriving, at scale, if they focused on revenue growth over raising another round of funding. On average, the companies we’ve backed have increased revenues over 100% in the first 12 months of the program and around 300% after 24 months post-investment. We aim to be the last investment our founders NEED to take. We call this <a href="https://medium.com/strong-words/permissionless-entrepreneurship-df80dd8fb6c5">Permissionless Entrepreneurship</a>.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is a bit like the baseball scouting revolution that Michael Lewis chronicled in <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moneyball_(film)">Moneyball</a></em>. While all the other teams were looking for home-run hitters, Oakland A’s manager Billy Beane realized that on-base percentage was a far more important statistic for actually winning. He took that insight all the way from the league basement to the playoffs, winning against far richer teams despite the A’s own low-salary budget.</p>
<p>One result of an investment model looking for the equivalent of on-base percentage—that is, the ability to deliver a sustainable business for as little money as possible—is that many entrepreneurs can do far better than they can in the VC blitzscale model. They can build a business that they love, like I did, and continue to operate it for many years. If they do decide to exit, they will own far more of the proceeds.</p>
<p>Even successful swing-for-the fences VCs like Bill Gurley of <a href="http://www.benchmark.com/">Benchmark Capital</a> agree. As Gurley, an early Uber investor and board member, <a href="https://twitter.com/bgurley/status/1083756889089798145">tweeted recently</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en">
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">100% agree with this article, &amp; have voiced this opinion my whole career. The vast majority of entrepreneurs should NOT take venture capital. Why? Article nails it: it is a binary &#8220;swing for the fences&#8221; exercise. Bootstrapping more likely to lead to individual financial success. <a href="https://t.co/s1mAOKwz6m">https://t.co/s1mAOKwz6m</a></p>
<p>— Bill Gurley (@bgurley) <a href="https://twitter.com/bgurley/status/1083756889089798145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 11, 2019</a></p></blockquote>
<p>Indie.vc’s search for profit-seeking rather than exit-seeking companies has also led to a far more diverse venture portfolio, with more than half of the companies led by women and 20% by people of color. (This is in stark contrast to traditional venture capital, where <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/315992">98% of venture dollars go to men</a>.) Many are from outside the Bay Area or other traditional venture hotbeds. The 2019 Indie.vc tour, in which Roberts looks for startups to join the program, hosts stops in Kansas City, Boise, Detroit, Denver, and Salt Lake City, as well as the obligatory San Francisco, Seattle, New York, and Boston.</p>
<p>Where conventional startup wisdom would suggest that aiming for profits, not rounds of funding, will lead to plodding growth, many of our Indie.vc companies are growing just as fast as those from the early-stage portfolios in our previous OATV funds.</p>
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@ThompsonAder/indie-and-me-86b2e0abeb5c">Nice Healthcare</a> is a good example. Its founder, Thompson Aderinkomi, had been down the traditional blitzscaling path with his prior venture and wanted to take a decidedly different approach to funding and scaling his new business. Seven months post-investment by Indie.vc, Nice was able to achieve 400% revenue growth, over $1 million in annual recurring revenue, and is now profitable. All while being run by a black founder in Minneapolis. Now that’s a real unicorn! Some of the other fast-growing companies in the Indie.VC portfolio include <a href="http://theshaderoom.com/">The Shade Room</a>, <a href="https://www.fohr.co/">Fohr</a>, <a href="https://storq.com/">Storq</a>, <a href="https://re3d.org/">re:3d</a>, and <a href="https://chopshop.co/">Chopshop</a>.</p>
<p>OATV has invested in its share of companies that have gone on to raise massive amounts of capital—<a href="https://foursquare.com/">Foursquare</a>, <a href="https://www.planet.com/">Planet</a>, <a href="https://www.fastly.com/">Fastly</a>, <a href="https://www.acquia.com/">Acquia</a>, <a href="https://www.signalsciences.com/">Signal Sciences</a>, <a href="https://www.figma.com/">Figma</a>, and <a href="https://www.devoted.com/">Devoted Health</a> for example—but we’ve also funded companies that were geared toward steady growth, profitability, and positive cash flow from operations, like <a href="https://www.instructables.com/">Instructables</a>, <a href="https://seeclickfix.com/">SeeClickFix</a>, <a href="https://peerj.com/">PeerJ</a>, and <a href="https://opensignal.com/">OpenSignal</a>. In our earlier funds, though, we were trying to shoehorn these companies into a traditional venture model when what we really needed was a new approach to financing. So many VCs throw companies like these away when they discover they aren’t going to hit the hockey stick. But Roberts kept working on the problem, and now his approach to venture capital is turning into a movement.</p>
<p>A recent <em>New York Times</em> article, “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/11/technology/start-ups-rejecting-venture-capital.html">More Startups Have an Unfamiliar Message for Venture Capitalists: Get Lost</a>,” describes a new crop of venture funds with a philosophy similar to Indie.vc. Some entrepreneurs who were funded using the old model are even buying out their investors using debt, like video-hosting company <a href="https://wistia.com/">Wistia</a>, or their own profits, like social media management company <a href="https://buffer.com/">Buffer</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.sweetlabs.com/">Sweet Labs</a>, one of OATV’s early portfolio companies, has done the same. With revenues in the high tens of millions, the founders asked themselves why they should pursue risky hypergrowth when they already had a great business they loved and that already had enough profit to make them rich. They offered to buy out their investors at a reasonable multiple of their investment, and the investors agreed, giving back control over the company to its founders and employees. What Indie.vc has done is to build in this optionality from the beginning, reminding founders that an all-or-nothing venture blitzscale is not their only option.</p>
<h2>The responsibility of the winners</h2>
<p>I’ve talked so far mainly about the investment distortions that blitzscaling introduces. But there is another point I wish Hoffman and Yeh had made in their book.</p>
<p>Assume for a moment that blitzscaling is indeed a recipe for companies to achieve the kind of market dominance that has been achieved by Apple, Amazon, Facebook, Microsoft, and Google. Assume that technology is often a winner-takes-all market, and that blitzscaling is indeed a powerful tool in the arsenal of those in pursuit of the win.</p>
<p>What is the responsibility of the winners? And what happens to those who don’t win?</p>
<p>We live in a global, hyperconnected world. There is incredible value to companies that operate at massive scale. But those companies have responsibilities that go with that scale, and one of those responsibilities is to provide an environment in which other, smaller companies and individuals can thrive. Whether they got there by blitzscaling or other means, many of the internet giants are platforms, something for others to build on top of. <a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fstratechery.com%2F2018%2Fthe-bill-gates-line%2F">Bill Gates put it well in a conversation with Chamath Palihapitiya</a> when Palihapitiya was the head of platform at Facebook: “A platform is when the economic value of everybody that uses it exceeds the value of the company that creates it.”</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>For every company that pulled off that feat of hypergrowth, there is a dotcom graveyard of hundreds of companies that never figured it out.</p></blockquote>
<p>The problem with the blitzscaling mentality is that a corporate DNA of perpetual, rivalrous, winner-takes-all growth is fundamentally incompatible with the responsibilities of a platform. Too often, once its hyper-growth period slows, the platform begins to compete with its suppliers and its customers. Gates himself <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=MX4ZjwPrM5YC&amp;lpg=PT95&amp;ots=0B8TCEAE0l&amp;dq=choke%20off%20netscape%27s%20air%20supply&amp;pg=PT95#v=onepage&amp;q=choke%20off%20netscape's%20air%20supply&amp;f=false">faced (and failed) this moral crisis when Microsoft became the dominant platform of the personal computer era</a>. Google is now facing this same moral crisis, and also failing.</p>
<p>Windows, the web, and smartphones such as the iPhone succeeded as platforms because a critical mass of third-party application developers added value far beyond what a single company, however large, could provide by itself. Nokia and Microsoft were also-rans in the smartphone platform race not just because they couldn’t get customers to buy their phones, but because they couldn’t get enough developers to build applications for them. Likewise, Uber and Lyft need enough drivers to pick people up within a few minutes, wherever they are and whenever they want a ride, and enough passengers to keep all their drivers busy. Google search and Amazon commerce succeed because of all that they help us find or buy from others. Platforms are two-sided marketplaces that have to achieve critical mass on <em>both</em> the buyer and the seller sides.</p>
<p>Yet despite the wisdom Gates expressed in his comments to Palihapitiya about the limitations of Facebook as a platform, he clearly didn’t go far enough in understanding the obligations of a platform owner back when he was Microsoft’s CEO.</p>
<p>Microsoft was founded in 1975, and its operating systems —first MS-DOS, and then Windows—became the platform for a burgeoning personal computer industry, supporting hundreds of PC hardware companies and thousands of software companies. Yet one by one, the most lucrative application categories—word processing, spreadsheets, databases, presentation software—came to be dominated by Microsoft itself.</p>
<p>One by one, the once-promising companies of the PC era—Micropro, Ashton-Tate, Lotus, Borland—went bankrupt or were acquired at bargain-basement prices. Developers, no longer able to see opportunity in the personal computer, shifted their attention to the internet and to open source projects like Linux, Apache, and Mozilla. Having destroyed all its commercial competition, Microsoft sowed the dragon’s teeth, raising up a new generation of developers who gave away their work for free, and who enabled the creation of new kinds of business models outside Microsoft’s closed domain.</p>
<p>The government also took notice. When Microsoft moved to crush Netscape, the darling of the new internet industry, by shipping a free browser as part of its operating system, it had gone too far. In 1994, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Microsoft_Corp.">Microsoft was sued by the U.S. Department of Justice</a>, signed a consent decree that didn’t hold, and was sued again in 1998 for engaging in anti-competitive practices. A final settlement in 2001 gave enough breathing room to the giants of the next era, most notably Google and Amazon, to find their footing outside Microsoft’s shadow.</p>
<p>That story is now repeating itself. I recently did an analysis of Google’s public filings since its 2004 IPO. One of the things those filings report is the share of the ad business that comes from ads on Google’s own properties (<a href="https://ads.google.com/home/">Google Ads</a>) versus from ads it places on its partner sites (<a href="https://www.google.com/adsense/start/#/?modal_active=none">AdSense</a>). While Google has continued to grow the business for its partners, the company has grown its own share of the market far, far faster. As shown on the chart below, when Google went public in 2004, 51% of ad revenue came from Google’s own search engine while 49% came from ads on third-party websites served up by Google. But by 2017, revenue from Google properties was up to 82%, with only 18% coming from ads on third-party websites.</p>
<figure id="id-aBiNq"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/06/Google_growth-e6d38f5d537a17f48b8288d25f3c4b55.jpg"></figure>
<p>Where once advertising was relegated to a second-class position on Google search pages, it now occupies the best real estate. Ads are bigger, they now appear above organic results rather than off to the side, and there are more of them included with each search. Even worse, organic clicks are actually disappearing. In category after category—local search, weather, flights, sports, hotels, notable people, brands and companies, dictionary and thesaurus, movies and TV, concerts, jobs, the best products, stock prices, and more—Google no longer sends people to other sites: it provides the information they are looking for directly in Google. This is very convenient for Google’s users, and very lucrative for Google, but very bad for the long-term economic health of the web.</p>
<p>In a recent talk, SEO expert Rand Fishkin gave <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/randfish/seo-on-the-serps-brighton-seo-closing-talk?ref=https://sparktoro.com/blog/on-serp-seo-the-infuriating-reality-of-searchs-future/">vivid examples of the replacement of organic search traffic with “no click” searches</a>&nbsp;(especially on mobile) as Google has shifted from providing links to websites to providing complete answers on the search page itself. <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/randfish/seo-on-the-serps-brighton-seo-closing-talk/18-The_Scary_PartOrganic_Paid_No">Fishkin’s statistical view is even more alarming than his anecdotal evidence</a>. He claims that in February 2016, 58% of Google searches on mobile resulted in organic clicks, and 41% had no clicks. (Some of these may have been abandoned searches, but most are likely satisfied directly in the Google search results.) By February 2018, the number of organic clicks had dropped to 39%, and the number of no click searches had risen to 61%. It isn’t clear what proportion of Google searches his data represents, but it suggests the cannibalization is accelerating.</p>
<blockquote class="pullquote"><p>Growth for growth’s sake seems to have replaced the mission that made Google great.</p></blockquote>
<p>Google might defend itself by saying that providing information directly in its search results is better for users, especially on mobile devices with much more limited screen real estate. But search is a two-sided marketplace, and Google, now effectively the marketplace owner, needs to look after both sides of the market, not just its users and itself. If Google is not sending traffic to its information suppliers, should it be paying them for their content?</p>
<p>The health of its supplier ecosystem should be of paramount concern for Google. Not only has the company now drawn the same kind of <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-eu-google-antitrust/europe-hits-google-with-record-5-billion-antitrust-fine-appeal-ahead-idUSKBN1K80U8">antitrust scrutiny</a> that once dogged Microsoft, it has weakened its own business with a self-inflicted wound that will fester over the long term. As content providers on the web get less traffic and less revenue, they will have fewer resources to produce the content that Google now abstracts into its rich snippets. This will lead to a death spiral in the content ecosystem on which Google depends, much as Microsoft’s extractive dominion over PC software left few companies to develop innovative new applications for the platform.</p>
<p>In his book <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hit-Refresh-Rediscover-Microsofts-Everyone/dp/0062652508/">Hit Refresh</a></em>, Satya Nadella, Microsoft’s current CEO, reflected on the wrong turn his company had taken:</p>
<blockquote><p>When I became CEO, I sensed we had forgotten how our talent for partnerships was a key to what made us great. Success caused people to unlearn the habits that made them successful in the first place.</p></blockquote>
<p>I asked Nadella to expand on this thought in <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/conversation-satya-nadella-his-new-book-hit-refresh-tim-o-reilly/">an interview I did with him in April 2017</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The creation myth of Microsoft is what should inspire us. One of the first things the company did, when Bill and Paul got together, is that they built the BASIC interpreter for the ALTAIR. What does that tell us today, in 2017? It tells us that we should build technology so that <em>others</em> can build technology. And in a world which is going to be shaped by technology, in every part of the world, in every sector of the economy, that’s a great mission to have. And, so, I like that, that sense of purpose, that we create technology so that others could create more technology.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now that they’ve gone back to enabling others, <a href="http://fortune.com/2019/01/15/data-sheet-microsoft-satya-nadella/">Microsoft is on a tear</a>.</p>
<p>We might ask a similar question: what was the creation myth of Google? In 1998, Larry Page and Sergey Brin set out to <a href="https://www.google.com/about/">“organize the world’s information and make it universally accessible and useful.”</a> Paraphrasing Nadella, what does that tell us today, in 2019? It tells us that Google should build services that help <em>others</em> to create the information that Google can then organize, make accessible, and make more useful. That’s a mission worth blitzscaling for.</p>
<p>Google is now 20 years old. One reason for its extractive behavior is that it is being told (<a href="https://www.mercurynews.com/2018/10/26/google-parent-alphabets-results-disappoint-investors/">now by Wall Street</a> rather than venture investors) that it is imperative to keep growing. But the greenfield opportunity has gone, and the easiest source of continued growth is cannibalization of the ecosystem of content suppliers that Google was originally created to give users better access to. Growth for growth’s sake seems to have replaced the mission that made Google great.</p>
<h2>The true path to prosperity</h2>
<p>Let’s circle back to Uber and Lyft as they <a href="https://www.recode.net/2018/12/6/18128937/lyft-ipo-uber-strategy">approach their IPOs</a>. Travis Kalanick and Garrett Camp, the founders of Uber, are serial entrepreneurs who set out to get rich. Logan Green and John Zimmer, the founders of Lyft, are idealists whose vision was to reinvent public transportation. But having raised billions using the blitzscaling model, both companies are subject to the same inexorable logic: they must maximize the return to investors.</p>
<p>This they can do only by convincing the market that their money-losing businesses will be far better in the future than they are today. Their race to monopoly has ended up instead with a money-losing duopoly, where low prices to entice ever more consumers are subsidized by ever more capital. This creates enormous pressure to eliminate costs, including the cost of drivers, by <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/ubers-losses-mount-at-self-driving-car-unit">investing <em>even more money</em> in technologies like autonomous vehicles</a>, once again “prioritizing speed over efficiency,” and “risking potentially disastrous defeat” while blitzscaling their way into an unknown future.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the defeat being risked is not just theirs, but ours. Microsoft and Google began to cannibalize their suppliers only after 20 years of creating value for them. Uber and Lyft are being encouraged to eliminate their driver partners from the get-go. If it were just these two companies, it would be bad enough. But it isn’t. Our entire economy seems to have forgotten that workers are also consumers, and suppliers are also customers. When companies use automation to put people out of work, they can no longer afford to be consumers; when platforms extract all the value and leave none for their suppliers, they are undermining their own long-term prospects. It’s two-sided markets all the way down.</p>
<p>The goal for Lyft and Uber (and for all the entrepreneurs being urged to blitzscale) should be to make their companies more sustainable, not just more explosive—more equitable, not more extractive.</p>
<p>As an industry and as a society, we still have many lessons to learn, and, apologies to Hoffman and Yeh, I fear that how to get better at runaway growth is far from the most important one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-fundamental-problem-with-silicon-valleys-favorite-growth-strategy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is O&#8217;Reilly Radar?</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/what-is-oreilly-radar/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/what-is-oreilly-radar/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Loukides and Roger Magoulas]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AI & ML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation & Disruption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Architecture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/what-is-oreilly-radar/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[O’Reilly Radar is a process that assimilates signals and data to track, map, and name technology trends that impact many aspects of modern business and living. Almost as old as O’Reilly itself, Radar has a history of playing a key role in the development and amplification of influential themes, including open source, Web 2.0, big [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>O’Reilly Radar is a process that assimilates signals and data to track, map, and name technology trends that impact many aspects of modern business and living. Almost as old as O’Reilly itself, Radar has a history of playing a key role in the development and amplification of influential themes, including <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/tim/opensource/">open source</a>, <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/pub/a/web2/archive/what-is-web-20.html">Web 2.0</a>, <a href="http://assets.en.oreilly.com/1/event/54/mdw_online_bigdata_radar_pdf.pdf">big data</a>, <a href="https://learning.oreilly.com/library/view/what-is-devops/9781449340346">DevOps</a>, <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/the-wtf-economy">Next Economy</a>, and others.</p>
<p>O&#8217;Reilly applies the Radar approach to spot what&#8217;s coming next and show how technology is changing our world. Using reports, conferences, and conversations, the Radar group provides decision-makers with the tools and connections they need to thrive during these dynamic times.</p>
<p>Our insights come from many sources: our own reading of the industry tea leaves, our many contacts in the industry, our <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/3-emerging-trends-tech-leaders-should-watch">analysis of usage on the O’Reilly online learning platform</a>, and data we assemble on technology trends. After we track and identify emergent trends, we map them into themes that address their broader impact on employees, organizations, and society at large.</p>
<p>The process is not easy or simplistic. It requires follow-up analysis, much internal debate, and a healthy dose of realism in response to industry hype. Our goal is to provide insights and confidence to folks making decisions about technology, strategy, purpose, and mission.</p>
<p>We take a few fundamental approaches to exploring technology adoption, each building on the other:</p>
<ul>
<li>We convene communities of interest through our <a href="http://oreilly.com/conferences/">conferences</a>, summits, and our Foo Camps (short for “Friends of O’Reilly,” these are invite-only, unconference-style events).</li>
<li>We conduct qualitative research, taking advantage of our ability to convene communities, using surveys, interviews, and salons to gain intimate access to thought leaders, business leaders, and those in the trenches who are wrestling with technology and change.</li>
<li>We conduct quantitative analysis to track technology adoption, from the esoteric and emergent to the everyday world of developers, designers, administrators, managers, and architects. The <a href="https://learning.oreilly.com/">O’Reilly online learning platform</a> is one of the quantitative tools we use; it serves as a massive sensor that we analyze for insights into users’ engagement with technology.</li>
</ul>
<p>Through this process, we’ve identified the following five themes business and technology leaders should consider. These themes are not discrete; we see much bleed between topics and how they interact—a characteristic of the current technology environment that affects, well, nearly everything organizations touch.</p>
<h2>Next Economy</h2>
<p>Next Economy defines how business leaders, policymakers, and technologists can chart a course from the economy we experience today to a better future for all, acknowledging the wonders and challenges that we have collectively wrought.</p>
<p>This research area focuses on big picture economic trends that nearly all organizations face, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>How is technology changing the shape of the corporation and the nature of work?</li>
<li>What skills become more valuable as more types of work are subject to automation?</li>
<li>What economic incentives encourage businesses to treat people as costs to be eliminated rather than as assets to invest in? How do we change those incentives?</li>
<li>How do algorithmic systems drive value, manifest bias, and affect fairness—particularly in closed platforms with their own economics?</li>
<li>What is the impact of behavioral economics?</li>
<li>How does diversity improve all aspects of decision-making?</li>
<li>Do we need a new model and way of assessing antitrust in the age of internet-scale platforms?</li>
<li>What does technology let us do now that was formerly impossible?</li>
</ul>
<p>This Radar theme offers a new and empowering perspective on creating value and success, leveraging innovation, and embracing disruption and change.</p>
<p>Radar has been looking at the Next Economy for the last five years, including running Next:Economy conferences in <a href="https://conferences.oreilly.com/nextcon/economy-us-2015">2015</a> and <a href="https://conferences.oreilly.com/nextcon/economy-us">2016</a>. Tim O’Reilly’s book <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/tim/wtf-book.html"><em>WTF?: What’s the Future and Why It’s Up to Us</em></a> provides a deeper dive into Next Economy topics. Lately, we have sharpened our attention on Next Economy topics into a focus on the Future of the Firm, as covered in the next section and in our “<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/future-of-the-firm">Future of the Firm</a>” report.</p>
<h2>Future of the Firm</h2>
<p>As jobs become more automated and work is increasingly done on a contingent and contract basis, you have to ask: what does a firm really do?</p>
<p>Yes, successful businesses are increasingly digital and technologically astute. But how do they attract, retain, incent, and manage people in a world where by choice or by circumstance two billion people work part-time? How do they develop their workforce when automation is advancing at light speed? And how do they attract customers and full-time employees when competition is high and trust is at an all-time low?</p>
<p>Modern businesses are being reshaped by a number of factors, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Increasing demand for trust, responsibility, credibility, honesty, and transparency in organizations.</li>
<li>Employees’ search for meaning.</li>
<li>New leadership models with networks replacing hierarchies—the recognition that the top-down approach is too slow, catalyzing a move toward decentralization and teams.</li>
<li>The impact of generational change on employee and customer expectations.</li>
<li>Big systemic thinking—the need to understand and consider organizations as operating in complex, interconnected environments.</li>
<li>Automation creating new kinds of partnerships between people and machines.</li>
<li>Free agency, personal brands, and the evolving employer/employee relationship.</li>
<li>Compensation beyond pay.</li>
<li>Diversity, inclusion, and fairness at work.</li>
<li>Governance and the case for cognitive and experiential diversity.</li>
</ul>
<p>We explore each of these trends in our report “<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/future-of-the-firm">Future of the Firm</a>.”</p>
<h2>Machine Learning / Artificial Intelligence</h2>
<p>Few technologies have the potential to change the nature of work, of the firm, and how we live as machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI). The impact of ML/AI on the future of our economy is both uncertain and undeniable. With new tools and computing power, ML/AI has become more effective at predictions, recommendations, certain types of pattern matching, and optimizing processes. And while the space has matured quickly, organizations continue to grapple with how to best apply ML/AI models—we are still in early days with much to learn.</p>
<p>We see a lot of the effort around ML/AI aimed at improving or reframing the customer experience—i.e., making processes simpler, faster, more convenient, more intuitive, and anticipating requests or actions. However, results don’t always meet expectations due to a number of factors:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need for large quantities of well-organized, accurate data.</li>
<li>The time and resources required to train machine learning models.</li>
<li>Algorithms that are difficult or too complex to understand.</li>
<li>Bias and fairness issues.</li>
<li>The need for constant monitoring.</li>
<li>Unreliable accuracy.</li>
</ul>
<p>The result: ML/AI work requires a different approach and different perspective from how we develop software. Managing risk and measuring success means more unpredictable schedules and more tolerance for failure—think of ML/AI projects as a portfolio of experiments to monitor and evaluate.</p>
<p>Learn more about how organizations are evaluating and implementing ML/AI in our report “<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/data/free/ai-adoption-in-the-enterprise.csp">AI Adoption in the Enterprise</a>.”</p>
<h2>Next Architecture</h2>
<p>Analysis of the <a href="https://learning.oreilly.com/">O’Reilly online learning platform</a> shows growing engagement with cloud, orchestration, and microservices topics. When coupled with continued interest in containers, this engagement paints a picture of increased use of a new kind of software architecture for building an organization’s digital presence. This architecture, which we call the Next Architecture, is cloud based, with functionality decomposed into microservices that are modularized into containers and managed and monitored by dynamic orchestration. Conversations with thought leaders across many industries confirm that the combination of cloud, containers, orchestration, and decomposition does indeed represent the path many organizations are taking for their next architecture.</p>
<p>Why the change? Organizations see the need to support agility, flexibility, scaling, resiliency, and productivity in building their digital properties as intrinsic to their value propositions and their ability to compete. The Next Architecture is not a cure-all or magic bullet. It’s a way of thinking about and designing systems that promises to be more flexible and adaptable than traditional monolith approaches.</p>
<p>Moving to the Next Architecture is not to be taken lightly, requiring new skills and the ability to manage complexity, including the particularly difficult task of turning complex functionality into modular, stand-alone services that can be easily upgraded or replaced. For most organizations, these challenges are worth confronting as a more flexible, agile, scalable architecture becomes essential for their digital properties.</p>
<p>See our report &#8220;<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/what-is-next-architecture/">What is Next Architecture?</a>&#8221; for more detail.</p>
<h2>Responding to Innovation &amp; Disruption</h2>
<p>How do you run a business when everything is always changing, and innovation and disruption have become the new norms? Once you acknowledge that change is inevitable, how do you embrace it? Moonshots? Incremental change? Innovation centers? Skunkworks? Key hires? Some mix? It’s confusing, and each approach has its benefits and risks.</p>
<p>At a fundamental level, the best way to thrive in a world of constant innovation and disruption is to constantly reinvent yourself—to pay attention to technology, to your customers, to thought leaders, and adapt. Leaders and staff at all levels need to embrace continuous learning to avoid surprising and existential threats. History is littered with organizations that failed to adapt: look at Digital Equipment Corporation. Look at Kodak. Look at Sears.</p>
<p>But we also see companies making profound turnarounds. Five years ago, Microsoft looked stagnant and irrelevant. Nobody would say that now. Microsoft adapted to a future that looks different from the past, embracing change, embracing open source, and embracing the cloud.</p>
<p>Taking a note from Microsoft, what are the adaptations <em>your</em> organization needs to make? What technologies and shifts do you see on the horizon that will need to be addressed through innovation and disruption?</p>
<p>For example, blockchain, the distributed trust data structure, offers the potential for great disruption. And, our analysis shows organizations using our online learning platform paying increasing and considerable attention to blockchain as a topic.</p>
<p>While banks and other financial institutions are trialing blockchain applications, we see a wealth of possibilities beyond finance to apply blockchain’s encrypted and distributed data structure: supply chain / asset tracking, customer loyalty, identity management, government records, educational credentials, and distributed energy generation. Blockchain brings incredible disruptive potential to the future—or, it may not. It’s too early to tell. Nonetheless, if you’re not paying attention to blockchain, you can be sure someone you compete with is.</p>
<p>Get an introduction to blockchain’s components and uses in “<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/what-is-a-blockchain">What is a blockchain?</a>”</p>
<h2>More to come from O’Reilly Radar</h2>
<p>Our first report of 2019, “Future of the Firm,” is now <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/future-of-the-firm">available</a>.</p>
<p>Over the coming months we’ll explore each of these themes through reports and analytic studies, event tracks, interviews with leaders and experts, and through other content and activities. We hope you’ll join us.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/what-is-oreilly-radar/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gradually, then suddenly</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/gradually-then-suddenly/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/gradually-then-suddenly/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Look Ahead]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Radar Analysis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/gradually-then-suddenly/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[There’s a passage in Ernest Hemingway’s novel The Sun Also Rises in which a character named Mike is asked how he went bankrupt. “Two ways,” he answers. “Gradually, then suddenly.” Technological change happens much the same way. Small changes accumulate, and suddenly the world is a different place. Throughout my career at O’Reilly Media, we’ve [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s a passage in Ernest Hemingway’s novel <em>The Sun Also Rises</em> in which a character named Mike is asked how he went bankrupt. “Two ways,” he answers. “Gradually, then suddenly.”</p>
<p>Technological change happens much the same way. Small changes accumulate, and suddenly the world is a different place. Throughout my career at O’Reilly Media, we’ve tracked and fostered a lot of “gradually, then suddenly” movements: the World Wide Web, open source software, big data, cloud computing, sensors and ubiquitous computing, and now the pervasive effects of AI and algorithmic systems on society and the economy.</p>
<p>What are some of the things that are in the middle of their “gradually, then suddenly” transition right now? The list is long; here are a few of the areas that are on my mind.</p>
<h2>AI and algorithms are everywhere</h2>
<p>The most important trend for readers to focus on is the development of new kinds of partnership between human and machine. We take for granted that algorithmic systems do much of the work at online sites like Google, Facebook, Amazon, and Twitter, but we haven’t fully grasped the implications. These systems are hybrids of human and machine. Uber, Lyft, and Amazon Robotics brought this pattern to the physical world, reframing the corporation as a vast, buzzing network of humans both guiding and guided by machines. In these systems, the algorithms decide who gets what and why; they’re changing the fundamentals of market coordination in ways that gradually, then suddenly, will become apparent.</p>
<h2>The rest of the world is leapfrogging the US</h2>
<p>The volume of mobile payments in China is <a href="https://mobilepaymentconference.com/why-china-leads-the-world-in-mobile-payments/">$13 trillion versus the US’ $50 billion</a>, while credit cards never took hold. Already <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/wired25-anne-wojcicki-keller-rinaudo-zipline-medical-drones/">Zipline’s on-demand drones are delivering 20% of all blood supplies in Rwanda</a> and will be coming soon to other countries (including the US). In each case, the lack of existing infrastructure turned out to be an advantage in adopting a radically new model. Expect to see this pattern recur, as incumbents and old thinking hold back the adoption of new models.</p>
<h2>China and the transformation of Africa</h2>
<p>Speaking of Africa, if it isn’t on your radar, it should be. Gradually, then suddenly, it&#8217;s becoming <em>“</em>the next factory of the world.” That’s the title of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Next-Factory-World-Investment-Reshaping-ebook/dp/B01MUGYCME">a 2017 book by McKinsey’s Irene Sun</a>. There’s also a detailed McKinsey report, <em><a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/middle-east-and-africa/the-closest-look-yet-at-chinese-economic-engagement-in-africa">Dance of the Lions and Dragons</a></em>, based on a study of more than 1,000 Chinese-owned factories in Africa. As the US has withdrawn into a kind of neo-isolationism, China is stepping up. There&#8217;s a lot of <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2018/09/three-myths-about-chinas-investment-in-africa-and-why-they-need-to-be-dispelled/">misinformation, rooted in denial, about its “One Belt, One Road” initiative</a>. Expect to wake up one day and realize that China has done to the US what the US did to the UK in the 20th century, becoming the new leader of the world economy, for good or ill. Up until now, China has spent a lot more time copying us than we spend copying them; that’s suddenly going to go into reverse. For a detailed look at the competition between the two “AI superpowers,” read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/AI-Superpowers-China-Silicon-Valley/dp/132854639X">Kai-Fu Lee’s book</a> of that name. See trend 1.</p>
<h2>The next agricultural revolution</h2>
<p>Last year, when I spoke at the <a href="https://foodtechconnect.com/events/">Food+Tech Connect Conference</a> in Amsterdam, I got an eyeful of the agricultural revolution that is happening in the Netherlands. Did you know that this tiny country, 1/270th the size of the US, is <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/2017/09/holland-agriculture-sustainable-farming/">the world’s second-largest food exporter</a>? That’s a testament to the way that precision farming and other new technologies are transforming agriculture. Silicon Valley is waking up to the opportunity, and so are consumers. I stopped in at an Oakland sports bar recently, and what did I see on the menu but an <a href="https://impossiblefoods.com/food/">Impossible Burger</a>. This new meatless meat is no longer just a treat for tech elites. Expect meaningful change in the makeup of our food supply, what we consume, and how it gets to us. If you’re skeptical, remember that 25 years ago, the internet was just becoming mainstream, and even the smartphone revolution is only 10 years old. Gradually, then suddenly, both have transformed the world.</p>
<h2>Climate change</h2>
<p>You have to have huge ideological blinders on not to see that the effects of climate change are less and less “gradual” and that we are rushing headlong toward a “suddenly” moment. One of the most interesting discoveries for me in the past year has been the work of groups like <a href="https://sohp.fas.harvard.edu/">the Initiative for the Science of the Human Past at Harvard</a>, which have been looking at the connection between climate change events and the fall of ancient civilizations. My friend <a href="http://www.malcolmwiener.net/">Malcolm Wiener</a> pointed out to me that climate events trigger mass migrations, which often bring with them new plagues, and whether a civilization survives (<a href="https://press.princeton.edu/titles/11079.html">as the Roman Empire did, albeit on a reduced scale</a>) or falls depends on the quality of its ruling elites. I leave you to consider the implications of the current political moment.</p>
<h2>Genetic engineering</h2>
<p>Genetic engineering is an important driver of food innovation, but it’s also a huge part of the possible response to climate change. <a href="https://reviverestore.org/projects/woolly-mammoth/">Bring the wooly mammoth back to life</a>? <a href="https://med.stanford.edu/news/all-news/2018/04/crispr-used-to-genetically-edit-coral.html">Save coral reefs</a>? But climate adaptation is just the tip of the iceberg. Could we <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90257662/these-gorgeous-colors-come-from-dye-made-by-bacteria-not-chemicals">replace chemical dyes with bacterial by-products</a>? And don’t get me started on the application of genomics to healthcare. Back in 2010, George Church pointed out the equivalent of <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/s/417628/a-moores-law-for-genetics/">Moore’s law for gene sequencing</a>. As a result of that acceleration, we’re now approaching the “suddenly” moment for precision medicine. And of course, AI is in the middle of all that, helping with drug discovery, synthesis of new materials, and biological pathways. But I suspect that there&#8217;s also a hidden intersection with &#8230;</p>
<h2>Neural interfaces</h2>
<p>One of my biggest “Wow!” moments of 2018 took place in the offices of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5Z5aZK2C3ew">neural interface company CTRL-labs</a>. Their demo involves someone playing the old <em>Asteroids</em> computer game without touching a keyboard, using machine learning to interpret the nerve signals that are sent to the hands. But it isn’t quite what you think. Moving things in the digital realm without moving your hands seems startling enough (though it’s worth remembering that it was once considered remarkable to be able to read silently without moving your lips). But that’s just the first stage. Essentially, users of this technology “grow” another virtual hand, which they can move independently of their physical hands. One of the researchers bowled me over when he said he was “working on controlling nine cursors at once.” Gradually, then suddenly, our children will interface with machines in deeper and deeper ways. Humanity is already going cyborg (see trend 1); expect it to accelerate. Don’t fall into the trap of thinking that AI will replace humans when it can be used even more powerfully to augment them.</p>
<h2>Online learning</h2>
<p>Online learning isn’t just about online schools like Udacity and Coursera or <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/online-learning/index.html">O’Reilly’s own learning platform</a>. What’s too often overlooked is how education and cognitive augmentation go hand in hand. The reason Uber and Lyft have a seemingly unlimited supply of drivers is because no training is required; the app itself does the heavy lifting of telling the driver where to pick up the passenger and how to get to the destination. At O’Reilly, we call this “<a href="https://trainingindustry.com/articles/content-development/the-next-big-shift-in-enterprise-learning-performance-adjacent-learning">performance-adjacent learning</a>.” Josh Bersin calls it “<a href="https://joshbersin.com/2018/06/a-new-paradigm-for-corporate-training-learning-in-the-flow-of-work/">learning in the flow of work</a>.” So many of the attempts to create online education seem to be reproducing 20th century models online; instead, we’ve hitched our platform squarely to the “gradually, then suddenly” trend of knowledge on demand, understanding that the supporting role of coursework is to get you to the point where you can take in and use on-demand knowledge. (We call this “structural literacy.”) See trend 1.</p>
<h2>The crisis of faith in government</h2>
<p>Ever since Jennifer Pahlka and I began working on the Gov 2.0 Summit back in 2008, we’ve been concerned that if we can’t get government up to speed on 21st century technology, a critical pillar of the good society will crumble. When we started that effort, we were focused primarily on government innovation; over time, through Jen’s work at <a href="https://www.codeforamerica.org/">Code for America</a> and the <a href="https://www.usds.gov/">United States Digital Service</a>, that shifted to a focus on making sure that government services actually work for those who need them most. Michael Lewis&#8217; latest book, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fifth-Risk-Michael-Lewis/dp/1324002646">The Fifth Risk</a></em>, highlights just how bad things might get if we continue to neglect and undermine the machinery of government. It’s not just the political fracturing of our country that should concern us; it’s the fact that government plays a critical role in infrastructure, in innovation, and in the safety net. That role has gradually been eroded, and the cracks that are appearing in the foundation of our society are coming at the worst possible time.</p>
<h2>Deeper reading</h2>
<p>Economics is my learning frontier right now as I explore the connections between the business ecosystems of the great tech platforms and trends in what I’ve been calling the Next Economy. Some of the books that I’ve taken the most from this year include <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Doughnut-Economics-Seven-21st-Century-Economist/dp/1603586741">Doughnut Economics</a></em>, by Kate Raworth; <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Value-Everything-Making-Taking-Economy/dp/161039674X">The Value of Everything</a></em>, by Mariana Mazzucato; <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Asia-Works-Joe-Studwell/dp/0802121322">How Asia Works</a></em>, by Joe Studwell; <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Assumptions-Economists-Make-Jonathan-Schlefer/dp/0674052269">The Assumptions Economists Make</a></em>, by Jonathan Schlefer; <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Prediction-Machines-Economics-Artificial-Intelligence/dp/1633695670">Prediction Machines</a></em>, by Ajay Agrawal, Joshua Gans, and Avi Goldfarb; and <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Adam-Smith-Change-Your-Life/dp/1591847958">How Adam Smith Can Change Your Life</a></em>, by Russ Roberts. That final book is not at all what most people will expect from the title. It&#8217;s not about the “invisible hand” or <em>The Wealth of Nations</em> but about Adam Smith’s other great book, <em>The Theory of Moral Sentiments</em>, which explores the role of social norms as a check on self-interest. We must rediscover and reinvent those norms, or gradually, then suddenly, we&#8217;ll continue the descent into economic and political barbarism.</p>
<p>Rather than ending this newsletter on a down note, let me remind you that the future is not inevitable. As I wrote in <a href="https://oreil.ly/2Hgrnoo">my book</a> last year, it&#8217;s up to us:</p>
<blockquote><p>This is my faith in humanity: that we can rise to great challenges. Moral choice, not intelligence or creativity, is our greatest asset. Things may get much worse before they get better. But we can choose instead to lift each other up, to build an economy where people matter, not just profit. We can dream big dreams and solve big problems. Instead of using technology to replace people, we can use it to augment them so they can do things that were previously impossible.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/gradually-then-suddenly/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>The future of work goes beyond the predictions of the World Economic Forum</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-future-of-work-goes-beyond-the-predictions-of-the-world-economic-forum/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-future-of-work-goes-beyond-the-predictions-of-the-world-economic-forum/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andy Oram]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-future-of-work-goes-beyond-the-predictions-of-the-world-economic-forum/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The World Economic Forum (WEF) has released a 147-page report on the future of jobs. With this document, one of the leading think tanks has weighed in on the great debate of our time: Will machines take over our work? And more broadly, how can society make sure that automation benefits more than a handful [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The World Economic Forum (WEF) has released <a href="https://www.weforum.org/reports/the-future-of-jobs-report-2018">a 147-page report on the future of jobs</a>. With this document, one of the leading think tanks has weighed in on the great debate of our time: Will machines take over our work? And more broadly, how can society make sure that automation benefits more than a handful of managers and tech experts?</p>
<p>In this article, while summarizing the WEF&#8217;s key recommendation, I&#8217;ll point out its limitations, springing from the constraints that the authors place on themselves. This will lead to a list of topics worth further investigation: the prospects for the emergence of new industries, the importance of the non-profit sector, and impacts on the informal economy. I&#8217;ll also touch on geographic impacts and the willingness of companies to tolerate the innovative employees who supposedly will drive change.</p>
<h2>Message to employers: Train your staff</h2>
<p>The WEF firmly endorses the optimistic side of the current debate: they predict that the massive job loss caused by automation and big data will be offset by even more jobs created in new, creative, intellectually demanding fields. This is encouraging (although I was disappointed at first, hoping to live off a monthly bank deposit and devote myself to the piano and poetry), but WEF also highlights the resulting &#8220;reskilling imperative&#8221;: the importance of retraining workers and training young people to be agile. <a href="http://reports.weforum.org/future-of-jobs-2018/workforce-trends-and-strategies-for-the-fourth-industrial-revolution/">Table 3 on page 9</a> of the report divides roles into those that are stable, new, and redundant (&#8220;pick up your check on the way out&#8221;). Most people today can find their occupations in the redundant column.</p>
<p>Are corporations up to the task? The WEF points out that they currently offer training opportunities to their best-trained and most privileged staff (page 14), and asks the corporations to offer training to the people who need it most. I worry that managers won&#8217;t do this. We can already see the mad scramble for scarce staff in fields as different as statistics and nursing. Everyone loses in such a situation&#8211;even the highly sought employees experience the stress of overwork.</p>
<p>The report doesn&#8217;t address society&#8217;s role in education. Many countries have excellent educational systems, and some (especially in Scandinavia) are <a href="https://www.usnews.com/news/best-countries/articles/2018-02-06/what-sweden-can-teach-the-world-about-worker-retraining">noted for retraining adults</a>. The kinds of jobs being created in the automated economy call for lots of training—how long does it take to become a data scientist or robotics engineer?—but companies expect only 10% of their employees to require more than one year of reskilling (page 13). Apparently, society will have to pick up the task. I will return to the question of education later in this article.</p>
<h2>Where the WEF stopped short</h2>
<p>It&#8217;s important to see the constraints that WEF placed on themselves when producing this report. They just asked the executives of current companies in 12 categories—mostly big companies—to talk about the jobs they expect to hire or train for. This is why the report failed to address public education. The direction chosen also made it impossible to consider new companies that will arise. Finally, the WEF didn&#8217;t try to inquire about new job opportunities that might arise totally outside the current corporate structure: nonprofits and the notorious &#8220;informal sector.&#8221; I think this is where people without corporate prospects will gravitate, and society needs to support that.</p>
<p>Thus, the number of new jobs required in an automation economy could be far greater than even the optimistic numbers predicted by the WEF. The following sections of the article look at each area.</p>
<p>We must remember that the economy can be disrupted by unexpected events such as war, along with the completely expected blows of climate change. As I write this, Moody&#8217;s Analytics predicts <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/09/17/moodys-hurricane-florence-damage-estimated-at-17-to-22-billion.html">at least $17 billion of damage</a> from our current disaster, Hurricane Florence, and costs may rise <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/economy/hurricane-florence-caused-up-to-50-billion-in-damage-report">as high as $50 billion</a>. With current catastrophes ranging from <a href="https://www.climate.gov/news-features/event-tracker/hot-dry-summer-has-led-drought-europe-2018">drought in Europe</a> to <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/typhoon-hit-philippines-rescuers-use-bare-hands-look-survivors-massive-n910111">mudslides in the Philippines</a>, we have to worry that our economy is in for serious trouble, along with all humans and other forms of life. But in this article I will do what most economists do, and just project current trends forward.</p>
<h3>New companies</h3>
<p>Areas that barely existed a decade ago, such as analytics for health care and 3D printing, are now teeming with promising new ventures. Some are quickly absorbed by large, established companies, while others survive by offering services to those companies. But job growth will happen in this area. Start-ups exacerbate the skills gap, though, because they lack the resources that large companies have to retrain people. Furthermore, established companies will buy or contract with the new companies to avoid spending money on reskilling their own employees. This way of sidestepping their responsibilities could reinforce the dreaded layoffs and exits from the workforce we all want to avoid.</p>
<h3>Nonprofits and quality-of-life jobs</h3>
<p>If automation truly relieves humans of repetitive and unpleasant work, we can expect a growth in &#8220;quality of life&#8221; occupations: wellness centers, adult education, travel, the arts, and so on. Some of these occupations are revenue-generating and can support themselves, but a lot of them—particularly education, health care, and the arts—require subsidization. Governments and companies may invest directly, as they do with primary and secondary education and with health care, or the investment may come through complex channels like donations to universities and arts centers. But however investment happens, the non-profit sector requires it. This is not addressed by the WEF.</p>
<p>Two factors make these issues particularly relevant to the future of work. First, the automated economy requires education and mental health services: education for the technical skills workers will need, and mental health to prepare them for delicate interactions with other people. Workers will also need to learn how to interact with robots (this is <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/patricklin/2016/02/01/relationships-with-robots-good-or-bad-for-humans/#39e8b9a7adc2">not a joke</a>).</p>
<p>And these necessities raise serious problems because elites today fail to appreciate the importance of funding the non-profit sector. This skepticism is partly rational, because one can point to plenty of poorly conceived projects and job padding. But I believe that the private sector contains lots of waste as well. We must not punish the non-profit sector in general for its lapses.</p>
<p>Travel and the arts, which may be for-profit or non-profit, are important for a different reason. They represent an income transfer from the affluent to the less affluent, and many areas of the world depend on that income. A healthy economy has to take them into account, even though they are non-productive.</p>
<p>The WEF looked at prospects for jobs in different countries and regions of the world, but did not break down geography further. One of the pressing trends throughout the world is the concentration of jobs in a few entrepreneurial cities, with other areas emptying out or suffering &#8220;epidemics of despair.&#8221; The WEF didn&#8217;t offer remedies for the well-known drain of talent from rural and inner regions to coastal cities with attractive living conditions. Automation will exacerbate these effects unless society&#8217;s leaders explicitly counteract them. We&#8217;ll see more of this issue in the following section.</p>
<h3>The informal sector</h3>
<p>The term &#8220;informal&#8221; covers a huge range of employment, such as many of the house cleaners and handymen employed by readers of this article. The informal economy is already estimated to cover <a href="http://www.wiego.org/informal-economy/statistical-picture">some 30% to 80% of all employment</a>. There can be many ways to view the informal sector from both an ethical and a regulatory standpoint, as <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2015/06/why-we-need-to-rethink-the-informal-economy/">recognized by the WEF itself</a>.</p>
<p>Aside from blatantly illegal forms of employment, such as drug dealing and the manufacture of knock-off fashion products, much of the informal economy consists of enterprises that create value and help under-served populations through innovative activities that the formal sector doesn&#8217;t think of doing. But informal companies tend to be in geographic and economic areas that can&#8217;t take advantage of the advanced analytics and robotics diffusing through the formal sector. If the formal sector becomes radically more efficient, it may put the informal sector out of business, and the urgency of reskilling will be even greater.</p>
<h2>Can companies make the shift?</h2>
<p>I&#8217;ve talked a lot about the barriers to reskilling, whose importance lay at the center of the WEF report. In their <a href="http://reports.weforum.org/future-of-jobs-2018/automotive-aerospace-supply-chain-transport/">industry profiles</a><a href="http://reports.weforum.org/future-of-jobs-2018/automotive-aerospace-supply-chain-transport/"> section</a> they note a great deal of worry about finding skilled personnel. But there&#8217;s another looming problem: an enormous number of industries have trouble making the digital shift because they admit they don&#8217;t understand the opportunities.</p>
<p>I also wonder whether corporations will recognize the need for the new, creative roles—and even more important, whether their need for control and old-fashioned hierarchy will allow them to nurture and make positive use of people in such roles. <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/leadership/changing-change-management">Seventy percent of change programs fail to achieve their goals</a>, largely due to employee resistance and lack of management support. Naturally, the topic is highly popular in the business literature. As an <a href="https://hbr.org/1969/01/how-to-deal-with-resistance-to-change">article in the Harvard Business Review</a> points out, people don&#8217;t tend to resist technical changes, but do resist changes in social relationships. I take this to indicate that creating empowered and independent-minded staff is extremely threatening to management, who are likely to resist the changes needed for innovation.</p>
<p>So I see the future of work as uncertain. We all know where we&#8217;d like to go: a world of self-realized individuals contributing to a better life for all. The WEF report has seriously underestimated the hurdles that lie in our path. The WEF recognizes that corporations see reskilling as a burden, but the difficulty goes much farther—many managers will see it as a threat. Other forces in society may also be suspicious of empowered individuals.</p>
<p>Can society reap the benefits of automation? It will require more than an appeal to management to do a modest amount of reskilling. Advocates must reach out and present automation as a vision that’s more appealing to the general public than hanging on to old jobs and ways of relating. Touting the technical benefits of automation will not be enough to overcome fears, nor will it produce the kind of automation that goes beyond replacing workers. A change of such historic social impact must be presented as a social movement—and a non-partisan one. When ordinary people demand a new relation to technology, education, and the workplace, they may be able to redeem from the cocktail of analytics, devices, and big data a life of meaning and productive contributions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/the-future-of-work-goes-beyond-the-predictions-of-the-world-economic-forum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shaping the stories that rule our economy</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/shaping-the-stories-that-rule-our-economy/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/shaping-the-stories-that-rule-our-economy/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim O’Reilly]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/shaping-the-stories-that-rule-our-economy/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Mariana Mazzucato opens her new book, The Value of Everything, with an ironic reminder from Plato’s Republic: “Our first business is to supervise the production of stories and choose those we think suitable and reject the rest.” She is acknowledging the way that much of our society is, as George Soros reminds us, reflexive, shaped [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mariana Mazzucato opens her new book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Value-Everything-Making-Taking-Economy/dp/161039674X"><em>The Value of Everything</em></a>, with an ironic reminder from Plato’s <em>Republic</em>: “Our first business is to supervise the production of stories and choose those we think suitable and reject the rest.” She is acknowledging the way that much of our society is, as George Soros reminds us, reflexive, shaped by ideas that become true or false as we are persuaded to believe them, and also pointing out that as a result, controlling the stories we are told is a prime instrument of power.</p>
<p>One of those mind-shaping stories is about the source of value in the economy—where it comes from, who produces it, and who should get the benefits. It’s easy, Mazzucato argues, to believe the stories we have been told are simply true, and to no longer question them. And question them we must, because the stories that rule our economy today are often wrong and, at best, incomplete.</p>
<p>So, we must ask why we have been led to believe by our modern economic accounting that the owners of capital are the primary value creators in our society, deserving of the greatest part of the fruits of increased productivity; that government by definition is outside “the production boundary” (that is, does not create any value but simply redistributes it or consumes it); and that unpaid household labor, too, creates no economic value. Are these stories correct, or merely self-serving?</p>
<p>Mazzucato spends much of the first part of her book giving a master class on the historical struggle to define value and its curious absence from the discussion in modern economics.</p>
<p>“Until the mid-19th century,” Mazzucato writes, “almost all economists assumed that in order to understand the prices of goods and services, it was first necessary to have an objective theory of value, a theory tied to the conditions in which those goods and services were produced, including the time needed to produce them and the quality of the labor employed; and the determinants of &#8216;value&#8217; actually shaped the price of goods and services. Then, this thinking began to go in reverse. Many economists came to believe that the value of things was determined by the &#8216;market&#8217;—or in other words, what the buyer was prepared to pay. All of a sudden, value was in the eye of the beholder. Any goods and services being sold at an agreed market price were by definition value-creating.”</p>
<p>That this economic framework leaves out much of what makes human life worth living is obvious to most of us. But that’s not the primary focus of Mazzucato’s critique. She takes aim instead at the legitimization of financial rent extraction by this model. Part and parcel of this modern theory of value is the idea that value creators are entitled to whatever they can extract from the rest of society. The wizards of Wall Street who brought us the 2008 financial crisis were, by this new definition, creating value even when knowingly selling defective mortgage securities, as long as they were able to find willing buyers for their goods. In 2009, with the world economy in tatters, Goldman Sachs CEO Lloyd Blankfein was able to say with a straight face that his employees were the most productive in the world.</p>
<p>The inclusion of finance as a productive activity is a remarkably recent addition to the economic playbook. It was only in 1993 that the System of National Accounts, which controls how countries calculate their GDP, began to count financial activity as value added, rather than simply as a cost to businesses. Mazzucato notes, “This turned what had previously been viewed as a deadweight cost into a source of value added overnight.”</p>
<p>And with that change to the idea of value came changes to the regulations that managed the activities of finance, eliminating the clear dividing lines that had previously separated finance as an enabler of industrial investment from its speculative activities, which were previously tolerated but frowned on. (One of the things that jumped out at me in this history is the way that government measurement of value and consequent regulation resembles, albeit in slow motion, the algorithmic regulation carried out by internet platforms such as Google and Facebook, Amazon and Apple. Government is the platform for our economy as surely as Apple is the platform for the App Store; its regulations shape what is allowed, who gets what and why.)</p>
<p>Pharma pricing, too, comes in for a drubbing in Mazzucato’s book. If price determines value, it is perfectly legitimate for a drug company to charge whatever the market will bear. After all, proponents argue, the cost of a drug should not be based on what it took to produce it, but on what it is worth to someone suffering from the condition it alleviates.</p>
<p>Mazzucato does not find this argument persuasive. Picking up on themes from her earlier book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Entrepreneurial-State-Debunking-Public-Private/dp/1610396138/"><em>The Entrepreneurial State</em></a>, she points out that far more of the costs of the research on which new drugs are based have been borne by the public in the form of government-funded R&amp;D. The so-called investors have come in only when government has taken most of the risks. Yet, because of our distorted theory of value, government gets no credit, and companies that have brought relatively little to the table reap outsized returns.</p>
<p>Mazzucato deeply questions the idea, widespread in modern Western societies and embedded in the very definition of GDP, that government does not in itself produce value. She makes the case that mission-driven government investment has created many of the marvels of the modern world, and it is only the oddity of our beliefs about value that keeps government from reaping the benefit on behalf of the public that footed the bill.</p>
<p>In a recent email conversation with me on the need to rethink the deal between private and public investors, Mazzucato wrote, “If the public sector is a co-creator of wealth and not just a redistributor or enabler, then why does it not get a return for its risk-taking? That return could come in different forms, from conditions on reinvestment (to prevent hoarding and financialization) to conditions on the structure of intellectual property rights (less strong and wide) to equity in downstream investments.” She pointed out that Tesla and Solyndra got virtually the same amount in government-guaranteed loans, but while the taxpayer picked up the loss for Solyndra, they did not get any upside from Tesla. The price per share went from $9 when Tesla took out the loan in 2009 to $90 when it was paid back in 2013—yet the deal the government struck only allowed them to get three million shares if the loan was not paid back (that is, because the company was failing.) No private investor would take such a bad deal! While there are those who argue the government gets its return via future tax receipts and downstream economic spillovers, I agree with Mazzucato that any story in which losses belong to the government, but any gains belong to the private sector “value creators” is one of those self-serving stories Plato advised those in power to tell.</p>
<p>Mazzucato&#8217;s point, though, is not to “try to argue for one correct theory of value,” but “to bring back value theory as a hotly debated area.” She notes that “value is not a given thing, unmistakably inside or outside the production boundary.” The definition of productivity, going back to Ricardo, is that of an excess of production over that which must be consumed, leaving the balance available for reinvestment in further production. But if instead the surplus is hoarded or frittered away by those who did not actually produce it (the classical definition of “economic rents”), the economy becomes less productive. In the new economics, though, she points out, “incomes must by definition reflect productivity. There is no space for rents, in the sense of people getting something for nothing.”</p>
<p>From Mazzucato’s perspective, equating price and value has real-world consequences for lower economic productivity. The modern economy is rife with economic rents, particularly those imposed by the financial industry, but also various forms of government-granted monopolies, the hereditary accumulation of control over scarce resources, or outright use of force. The modern idea that rents are simply an “imperfection”, a barrier that can be competed away, has replaced the classical economic idea of rent as unearned income—that is, income received from unproductive activities is treated as equivalent to that derived from the production of real value.</p>
<p>In the spirit of adding to the debate, I would make the case that rethinking the relative role of industries such as finance or pharma versus government as value creators is only the beginning. While Mazzucato gives a nod to the absence of household labor and what we now call the caring economy from our economic accounting, the book would benefit from a clarion call for putting these squarely inside the production boundary.</p>
<p>In each of the past debates about value, more and more human activity came to be understood as value creating not just because economists persuaded us of the new idea, but because of changes in society itself. The ideas of the 18th-century physiocrats made sense in a world where people rarely moved far from their homes, and land and agriculture <em>were</em> the principal sources of value. As the economy became less local, it was much easier to see that without the productive benefit of trade and all the services that make it possible, agricultural produce might rot in the field for lack of distribution, or never be grown in the first place. As the industrial revolution provided more and better goods, how could we not recognize industry as a kind of productivity? And as finance and debt allowed for the acceleration not just of production but of consumption, thereby enabling faster circulation within the economy, how could we fail to recognize some productive role for finance?</p>
<p>So, too, it seems to me, that as machines make the production of the necessities of life less expensive, humanity has the opportunity for greater leisure. Though Mazzucato largely omits this from her history, at some point we allowed entertainment within the production boundary. How did we get from the point where Adam Smith specifically called out opera singers and dancers as examples of unproductive members of society to one in which we think of our creative industries as major contributors to the economy, yet <em>still</em> fail to recognize our mothers, our teachers, our caregivers, those family members who clean our homes or put dinner on the table, as productive?</p>
<p>As we progress further into the age of intelligent machines, able to do more and more of even the routine cognitive labor that makes up much of the modern economy, we will clearly need to confront this curious gap in our economic accounting.</p>
<p>In his fascinating new book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/AI-Superpowers-China-Silicon-Valley/dp/132854639X/"><em>AI Superpowers</em></a>, Kai Fu Lee, China&#8217;s leading AI investor, looks at the future of work question and makes the case that we need to look not to solutions like universal basic income, but instead at a &#8220;Social Investment Stipend&#8221; that pays people to invest time in other people, in their community, and in the environment. To use Mazzucato’s language, this would be to put the caring economy inside the production boundary.</p>
<p>Yet another area Mazzucato points out as needing further elucidation is how we deal with “activities that appear to add value to the economy but whose output is not priced.” How might we measure the value exchange between platforms like Google, Facebook, and YouTube and their users? How might we measure the value of free and open source software? While economists have developed workarounds to include these kinds of services in the national accounts, it seems to me that these are the equivalent of the epicycles of Ptolemaic astronomy, increasingly contorted attempts to work around the failings of the underlying theory.</p>
<p>I am intrigued by signs that we are entering a new kind of economy that runs in parallel with the money economy measured by economists. For example, in economic theory, price signaling is the primary coordinator of the market&#8217;s &#8220;invisible hand, yet Google search is a massive information market in which price plays no role. The matching market of information producers and consumers is coordinated by hundreds of other algorithmically collated information signals. There is a parallel priced market (for advertising) that runs as a kind of sidecar on the search market itself, and that provides Google’s enormous profits. But how are we to measure the value exchange in the primary search market? In some cases, content is produced precisely to drive advertising. In other cases, the content is produced to drive transactions. But vast amounts of it are produced and consumed merely for the joy of producing and consuming, an economy of abundance that reminds us that what is bought and sold is not all that humans exchange.</p>
<p>There is also more to be said on the questions Mazzucato raises about the extent to which finance is actually productive, versus extractive. “The celebration of finance by political leaders and expert bankers is, however, not universally shared among economists,” she writes. “It clashes with the common experience of business investors and households, for whom financial institutions’ control of the flow of money seems to guarantee the institutions’ own prosperity far more readily than that of their customers.”</p>
<p>In this critique, she follows in the footsteps of earlier economists, who see economic rents as the primary enemies of equitable value distribution. In an on-stage conversation at Bloomberg last week, she remarked to me: “Most of the people who like to cite Adam Smith have obviously never read him. For him, the ‘free market’ did not mean ‘free of government regulation.’ It meant ‘free of rents’, and he recognized that one of the jobs of government is to keep the market that way.” Of course, as she notes in the book, government is currently doing a poor job of maintaining a market free of rents, precisely because our current definition of “value” allows rent-seekers free rein.</p>
<figure id="id-RDmiA" class="center"><img src="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2019/06/photo-68a29332dbf1a3bbdf26698d00076030-4.jpg" alt="Mariana Mazzucato and Tim O'Reilly"><figcaption><span class="label">Figure 2. </span>Mariana Mazzucato and Tim O&#8217;Reilly at Bloomberg. Image: O&#8217;Reilly Media.</figcaption></figure>
<p>“The &#8216;banking problem&#8217; arose,” she writes, “because as the 20th century progressed, banks’ role in fueling economic development steadily diminished in theory and practice—while their success in generating revenue and profit, through operations paid for by households, firms, and governments, steadily increased.” As Mazzucato notes, very little business investment today is provided by banks; far from being an enabler of economic activity, they have become net value extractors. Said more pungently, venture capitalist and economist Bill Janeway once explained to me that at some point banks stopped serving their customers and started trading against them.</p>
<p>Mazzucato makes the case that we need policies that recognize the difference when the financial industry is simply trading existing financial assets, rather than funding additional production in the real economy. These policies might include tax reforms such as financial transaction taxes that would penalize short-term trades, or setting up new institutions like public banks that provide patient long-term committed finance. (Here is a recent <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/bartlett/public-purpose/publications/2018/jun/patient-finance-innovation-driven-growth">policy brief</a> she wrote on patient long term capital.)</p>
<p>I would have also liked to see further discussion of the way that finance is different from what I call the traditional “Adam Smith market” of goods and services traded among people and firms, and has become something profoundly different—a betting market.</p>
<p>Janeway’s fascinating book <em><a href="https://www.billjaneway.com/inside-the-book-1/">Doing Capitalism in the Innovation Economy</a></em> tackles this problem by describing the economy as a “three-player game” between government, “the market” (that is, the Adam Smith-style market that I describe above), and financial capitalism, which is a futures betting market on the other two. The debate over which parts of banking belong in the traditional economy and which are part of an entirely new virtualized betting economy independent of traditional market fundamentals needs much further thought.</p>
<p>The recognition that we use the term “the market” for two very different things would be a useful addition to the discussion. In both popular and scholarly discussions (including occasionally in Mazzucato’s book), we see this confusion between stock market value and the size and profitability of a business in the real economy.</p>
<p>We constantly see references to the &#8220;size&#8221; of companies as their market capitalization, not their revenues, their profits, their number of employees, or other real-world factors. For example, when people refer to Uber as a “$60 billion dollar company,” they are referring to the betting odds, expressed in dollars, as to its market “worth.” Meanwhile, Uber currently has approximately $10 billion in revenue, on which it earns zero—or to be more exact, loses billions of dollars. So the financial market bet is completely at variance with the current reality in the market of actual goods and services. In the best case, this betting market brings previously unimaginable new futures into being. In the worst case, though, it is a bet on future value extraction via the establishment of economic rents, not on true value creation!</p>
<p>In my own book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/WTF-Whats-Future-Why-Its/dp/0062565710/"><em>WTF? What’s the Future and Why It’s Up to Us</em></a>, I call this special betting economy currency “supermoney.” In Silicon Valley, too often a company must be understood not as a producer of goods and services, but as a financial instrument, designed to get funding, perhaps to win attention and popularity and get acquired or go public based on hope and enthusiasm, but perhaps never be a working business.</p>
<p>This special currency allows highly valued companies to pay their employees more, acquire other companies cheaply, and often create enormous wealth for their investors and the early-stage employees, who are now increasingly able to cash in on the company long before it has attained any real profits. They may have disrupted and destroyed existing businesses that make money the old fashioned way, inflated the value of local real estate, and created other economic damage. Financing entrepreneurial risk-taking is a socially productive use of finance; financing entrepreneurial theater for the benefit of gullible investors while allowing insiders to take profits off the table before the economic outcome is clear is another version of the financial market game of socializing losses and privatizing gains.</p>
<p>The value of a company’s stock is, in theory, the net present value of a stream of its future profits–what would it be worth to own that company over time? Because the future is not certain, the price of a stock is essentially a bet on the company’s future growth and earnings. Benjamin Graham, the father of value investing, that now rare practice of which Warren Buffett is the leading practitioner, explained this concept by saying that in the short run, the market is like a voting machine, but in the long run, the market is like a weighing machine. But what happens when companies are valued on growth alone, and never expected to produce actual profits (i.e., a productive surplus)? This is akin to a horse race where bets are settled before the race has finished being run. The financial betting economy and the real economy of goods and services become radically disconnected.</p>
<p>But more importantly, I describe our financial markets as the first rogue AI, hostile to humanity, much like the rogue paperclip maximizer in Nick Bostrom’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Superintelligence-Dangers-Strategies-Nick-Bostrom/dp/0198739834/"><em>Superintelligence</em>.</a> When we optimize for the financial betting markets, humans are a cost to be eliminated, because increased corporate profits drive huge multiples in the betting markets where wealth is being extracted. The economy we want to build must recognize increasing the value to and for humans as the goal. To build that economy, we need a strenuous engagement with the questions Mariana Mazzucato asks in this book, an engagement deeply informed by the history of economic thought and how we got where we are today.</p>
<p>I found this book enormously stimulating. You will, too. Highly recommended.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/shaping-the-stories-that-rule-our-economy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
