<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	>

<channel>
	<title>Future of the Firm &#8211; Radar</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/topics/future-of-the-firm/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar</link>
	<description>Now, next, and beyond: Tracking need-to-know trends at the intersection of business and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 15:09:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.3.13</generator>
	<item>
		<title>3 ways to confront modern business challenges</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/3-ways-to-confront-modern-business-challenges/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/3-ways-to-confront-modern-business-challenges/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rita J. King]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Big Systemic Thinking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=12425</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[I interviewed four business leaders in late 2019 to get their perspectives on the biggest obstacles and opportunities organizations are facing. Craig Lemasters was the president and CEO of Assurant Solutions. Under his leadership, Assurant Solutions doubled in size to $4B, underwent a digital transformation to expand an offering of risk management solutions in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I interviewed four business leaders in late 2019 to get their perspectives on the biggest obstacles and opportunities organizations are facing.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/strong-leaders-forge-an-intersection-of-knowledge-and-experience">Craig Lemasters</a> was the president and CEO of Assurant Solutions. Under his leadership, Assurant Solutions doubled in size to $4B, underwent a digital transformation to expand an offering of risk management solutions in the connected living space, and became established in 25 new markets around the world. After Lemasters left Assurant, he bought a company called GXG where, as the chief executive officer, he focuses on accelerating the growth of companies through rapid-cycle learning. (Disclosure: GXG is a partner of Science House, a consultancy I co-direct.)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/leaders-need-to-mobilize-change-ready-workforces">Jen Bruno</a> is the SVP of culture and human capital at LPL Financial, a firm founded to help entrepreneurial financial advisors offer independent financial guidance. Early in her career, Bruno was a florist who dreamed of working at the Walt Disney company. The dream became reality. (Disclosure: LPL is a client of my consultancy.)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/an-enterprise-vision-is-your-companys-north-star">Dana Codispoti</a> is the head of HR transformation at AIG. Previously, she worked at BNY Mellon and Morgan Stanley, and in multiple industries spanning consumer products, pharmaceuticals, and hospitality. With an engineering background and a mind for data and analytics, Codispoti is adept at leading change in processes that have scaled across large companies, with an eye for both humanity and technology.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/great-leaders-inspire-innovation-and-creativity-from-within-their-workforces">James Jorasch</a> is the founding CEO of Science House, a New York-based consultancy that I co-direct. For 14 years prior to founding Science House, Jorasch was the head of inventing at Walker Digital. He’s a named inventor on more than 750 patents, including the patents at the core of Priceline, and his innovation work spans many industries, including retail, health care, and gaming.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Below, you’ll find notable themes that emerged during the discussions. You can see the full interviews <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/tag/big-systemic-thinking/">here</a>.</p>
<h2>Continuous learning and continuous improvement</h2>
<p>When people ask Craig Lemasters how long he ran Assurant Solutions, he says 44 quarters rather than 11 years.</p>
<p>“That’s how we think,” he said. “How do you free up time to think beyond a quarter or two or a year or two? We can do that. We can get to that place.”</p>
<p>But when Assurant’s distribution model—big box retailers—started collapsing, Lemasters wondered how he would shape the company’s future while focusing on the short term.</p>
<p>He knew it started with him as a CEO, but he didn’t know that other “lonely CEOs” were stuck in the same place. He engaged GXG (a company he later purchased) to help him over the hurdle by exposing him to the wisdom of others who navigated the same path. Continuous learning, especially from others who have developed wisdom from being in the same position, helps leaders get unstuck and become more agile.</p>
<p>Continuous learning is also required to understand the relationship between humanity and technology.</p>
<p>“Technology is driving and enabling at the same time,” Dana Codispoti said. “It’s a matter of how we use it. We need the human mind.”</p>
<p>From an HR perspective, Codispoti said, we need to go faster to get our minds ready. Companies should understand, among other things, the power of robotics and AI, along with the art of the possible, “while they are fixing the foundation,” Codispoti said. Too often, companies try to grasp at the next big thing without laying the foundation for learning first.</p>
<p>“There’s a whole world of things to learn,” Codispoti said. “I look at it as an enabler.”</p>
<p>Jen Bruno agreed. “Every business professional should consider themselves a continuous learner,” Bruno said. She noted that people need to be “change ready,”and get better at applying what they know in different areas for the greater good. Every company should get employees excited and engaged to learn because change keeps happening “faster than we can imagine.”</p>
<p>What makes a company a world-class learning organization?</p>
<p>“When people truly are in a mindset of continuous improvement,” Bruno said. “We can learn something from every person we meet. That’s good for business. Share talent and knowledge, and foster collaboration for greater outcomes.”</p>
<h2>Business lessons from technology processes</h2>
<p>Companies need a clear vision in a complex world, Codispoti said. “Create a north star that people can align to, that gets people excited about solving a problem,” she said. “Without it, they spin and spin and spin. If people don’t know how their work is value-add, you lose engagement. It ties to the enterprise vision.”</p>
<p>As more companies shift to Agile software development and, more importantly, an Agile mindset, the culture of companies has begun to mimic the iterative nature of technology. Smaller, granular pieces need to communicate with each other in the most effective way. This is true for microservices architecture, for example, and for people across teams.</p>
<p>Codispoti said that creating a process requires an end-to-end vision, but silos often lead to fragments being created piecemeal. “Once [a broken process] is enabled through technology and you want to make changes, it’s hard and people blame the technology,” Codispoti said.</p>
<p>Huge problems, James Jorasch said, need to be “distilled down to something that a client can understand and take action on.” Science House works with large enterprise clients, often on transformational software projects that can span years. The parallel between technology and people applies here, too.&nbsp; Making complex projects and transformations more modular creates a parallel impact on people and organizational structures, changing the nature of their responsibilities and spans of control. Bringing modular pieces together, whether the modules are temporal or functional, changes the role of traditional hierarchical organizational structures as they adapt to increased complexity.</p>
<p>“The nature of management is changing, and not just because of Agile,” Jorasch said. “It’s a different way of thinking. Managers have gone from managing people to managing processes, mindsets, skills, and problems.”</p>
<p>They also need to manage information flow into and from these groups.</p>
<p>“There are lessons learned from tech that will be applicable to people,” Jorasch said. “Where are the bottlenecks? What are the styles of thinking you need? Focus on what’s essential. How do you get the right information to the right person at the right time?”</p>
<h2>Humility is an asset</h2>
<p>One of the themes that came throughout the interviews was the need for humility. Without it, companies tend to stay inward looking and siloed.</p>
<p>“Companies struggle with cross-collaboration,” Codispoti said. “People tend to work in silos. They need to partner with experts in other areas. They don’t need to do it on their own, and they’re missing opportunities.”</p>
<p>Bruno and Lemasters both cited humility as a critical trait for leaders. Humility gives people the energy to cross over into an unfamiliar area, Bruno said, and creates the capacity for empathy.</p>
<p>“I look for the humility quotient,” Lemasters said. “A willingness for leaders to embrace outside thinking and ideas. Some would call it criticism, but it isn’t. Have the humility to accept people who have wisdom in their swim lanes. We learn quickly. There’s goodness in humanity, and people want to help.”</p>
<p>Jorasch often cites the need for not taking ourselves too seriously during innovation sessions, for example, because one person’s silly or half-formed comment gives another person a great idea. Humility helps prevent people from having to project authority or expertise every time they speak. With humility comes better listening; more honest, authentic input; less defensiveness; and more collaboration based on respect for one’s peers’ opinions.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/radar/tag/big-systemic-thinking/">Be sure to check out the full interviews for additional insights</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/3-ways-to-confront-modern-business-challenges/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>An enterprise vision is your company&#8217;s North Star</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/an-enterprise-vision-is-your-companys-north-star/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/an-enterprise-vision-is-your-companys-north-star/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 09:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Webb]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Big Systemic Thinking]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=12395</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Dana Codispoti, head of HR Transformation at AIG, about how to address the human factor in business [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Dana Codispoti, head of HR Transformation at AIG, about how to address the human factor in business transformations to keep employees engaged and connected to the overall business mission. They also discuss the future of the human-technology relationship and why technology should be viewed as an enabler rather than a replacement for human contributions.</p>
<p>Here are some highlights from their conversation:</p>
<p>With technology iterating and improving at ever-increasing speeds, companies are challenged with how best to utilize data and analytics to inform new technology decisions. Codispoti stresses that it&#8217;s imperative to start with the foundation, the &#8220;building blocks,&#8221; and not jump straight to the innovation or &#8220;shiny object.&#8221; The key, Codispoti notes, to successfully navigating new technologies and processes lies with the people and their engagement with the company&#8217;s overall vision. &#8220;One of the most important things you need to do in technology initiatives,&#8221; she says, &#8220;is to create a vision to help people understand what they are driving toward. I see a lot of work being done in the trenches where people don&#8217;t see the bigger picture—everybody&#8217;s working on an individual project or set of projects, but they can&#8217;t understand how it fits into a broader picture. If there isn&#8217;t a vision for the company, create one, or create a North Star that people can align to. That gets people excited about a problem; it gets people excited about participating in the solution. &#8230; If people don&#8217;t know why their work is value add and how it ties to a broader picture, you lose engagement.&#8221; (<a href="#t=118">01:58</a>)</p>
<p>Mitigating risk is a hurdle for any company facing changing technology and business processes. Codispoti says the solution lies in breaking out of silos and comfort zones to leverage the expertise of colleagues across an organization. &#8220;I find companies struggle with cross collaboration,&#8221; She explains. &#8220;If someone&#8217;s, for example, working in a business, they need to leverage their partners. In my case, it would be HR, finance, the risk organization, the audit, and legal folks. I think people tend to work in silos, and they need to lift up their heads, look around and say, these people are experts in those areas. Talk through and partner with them to understand the problems they&#8217;re solving for so that they can help point out the risk. People think they need to do all that on their own, and they&#8217;re missing opportunities to mitigate risk. &#8230; It&#8217;s about breaking through silos and pointing out how collaboration is additive—when you work in teams, you get more. People also have a mindset that &#8216;I need to fix this for my area,&#8217; and it&#8217;s not an enterprise mentality. As you go through these transformations, it&#8217;s about trying to influence the culture to say you wear two hats: one is for whatever you&#8217;re working on and one is for the enterprise, and lead with that enterprise mindset.&#8221; (<a href="#t=328">05:28</a>)</p>
<p>Looking toward the future and humanity&#8217;s evolving relationship with technology, Codispoti stresses that machines will always need people and humans should not fear being replaced. &#8220;There&#8217;s a large level of awareness around technology driving the future in a lot of ways, but I think there&#8217;s also fear that technology is going to take over humanity—we know that&#8217;s not the case,&#8221; She says. &#8220;You need both. &#8230; At the end of the day, the work is in the work, in the process, in the culture, in the people, and then technology becomes an enabler. So, it&#8217;s driving and enabling at the same time, but I think everybody needs to co-exist. Nobody&#8217;s going to be wiped out by technology; it&#8217;s a matter of how we use it and we recognize that it can do things faster than we can, but in some ways we need the human mind to enhance whatever technology is doing.&#8221;(<a href="#t=880">14:40</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/an-enterprise-vision-is-your-companys-north-star/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Leaders need to mobilize change-ready workforces</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/leaders-need-to-mobilize-change-ready-workforces/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/leaders-need-to-mobilize-change-ready-workforces/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 09:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Webb]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Big Systemic Thinking]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=12408</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Jen Bruno, SVP of culture and human capital at LPL Financial, about mobilizing a change-ready workforce, leadership [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Jen Bruno, SVP of culture and human capital at LPL Financial, about mobilizing a change-ready workforce, leadership rotation programs, and fostering continuous learning.</p>
<p>Here are some highlights from their conversation:</p>
<p>The reality, Bruno argues, is that businesses are in a state of change. And while humans tend to have a hard time with change, the time is ripe for people to take advantage of the coming changes to grow and develop. &#8220;Companies have a hard time mobilizing a workforce that is change-ready because people inherently want to do what they know; we build our careers on the skills that have allowed us to move to the next level. We&#8217;re at a time right now where people can look beyond that and use those skills in another department or a new area; crossing over can enable the imagination, the creativity, and the innovation that companies so desperately want in order to grow and best serve their customers. It&#8217;s an exciting opportunity for people to think of themselves as change agents and be willing to crossover and work in different areas, leveraging what they know and learning what they don&#8217;t know. (<a href="#t=383">06:23</a>)</p>
<p>Bridging culture gaps—and communication gaps— between departments is essential, Bruno says, to enable teams to work together efficiently and effectively to reap better outcomes. Creating these working relationship bridges, she argues, starts at the top. &#8220;I&#8217;m a big fan of having leaders rotate through the different jobs within an organization. The true way to learn empathy is to do the work yourself and understand what the people in specific roles go through on a day-to-day business. You&#8217;ll have a better understanding of the business operation as a whole. I think it makes you a better business leader because it does help develop that empathy, and it allows you to build your network of people internally, and that&#8217;s really important too.&#8221; (<a href="#t=656">10:56</a>)</p>
<p>The key to weathering the transition to what work will become in the future, Bruno argues, is continuous learning. &#8220;Every business professional should consider themselves a continuous learner. There is so much to learn from other organizations that have similar situations, from business people we have things in common with, and it&#8217;s important to be change-ready and willing to leverage what you know in different areas for the greater good. We should all be preparing ourselves as much as we can so we can bring value to the companies we work for, whatever that might look like.&#8221; To that end, it&#8217;s important for learning and development approaches to evolve, she says, to be more effective in the face of the changes coming our way. &#8220;I hope I never see a PowerPoint presentation being held up in a room for an hour while somebody talks to an audience, because that&#8217;s not really fostering learning in a way that gets people excited and engaged.&#8221; (<a href="#t=839">13:59</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/leaders-need-to-mobilize-change-ready-workforces/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Great leaders inspire innovation and creativity from within their workforces</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/great-leaders-inspire-innovation-and-creativity-from-within-their-workforces/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/great-leaders-inspire-innovation-and-creativity-from-within-their-workforces/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 09:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Webb]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Big Systemic Thinking]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=12403</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with James Jorasch, founding CEO of Science House, about the importance of innovation and how to inspire and [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with James Jorasch, founding CEO of Science House, about the importance of innovation and how to inspire and harness the creative talent in your workforce.</p>
<p>Here are some highlights from their conversation:</p>
<p>It&#8217;s important, Jorasch says, to appropriate the techniques of innovation that bring together ideas from disparate sources and apply those to people in your company. &#8220;We need people also to collide; people with different perspectives, different concepts, different ideas need to come together over and over again.&#8221; He also notes that invention isn&#8217;t only an innate talent; it can also be a learned skill. &#8220;We train many people, and I would say that everyone can invent. Believe in yourself, relax, find a problem, come up with a solution, keep going. It&#8217;s not a complicated thing. Just believe in yourself and try. Trying is probably 90% of it.&#8221; (<a href="#t=315">05:15</a>)</p>
<p>To effectively get the creative juices flowing, Jorasch recommends ditching large meetings, as they allow people to avoid contributing by simply hiding in the crowd. &#8220;When you bring a meeting down to just two people, there&#8217;s no hiding, there&#8217;s no, &#8216;Well, I&#8217;m going to be on my cell phone. We&#8217;re working on this.&#8217; There&#8217;s no getting away from what you&#8217;re there to do. It is that sense of focus that you get from two people that really ignites the imagination process.&#8221; That focus, he says, is key to addressing the new challenges coming. &#8220;There&#8217;s a lot that can be accomplished from creative pairs. It is a purpose driven, very focused way of tackling problems, and tackling very complicated and very deep problems. It takes away everything else—you&#8217;re lasered in on that one thing for, potentially, hours at a time. And that&#8217;s what it takes, right? 10-second solutions are not going to cut it in this world.&#8221; (<a href="#t=449">07:29</a>)</p>
<p>The data Science House has gathered from large companies over the years has afforded interesting insights into the changing nature of management, Jorasch says. For instance, in our increasingly Agile approaches to business and systems, the well-established, traditional hierarchy of individual contributor, manager, director, VP, SVP, and so forth, is no longer a great fit. &#8220;We have rules around the standard hierarchy,&#8221; he observes. &#8220;We don&#8217;t really have rules, per se, around Agile. And we&#8217;re seeing a collision of managers and directors now saying, &#8216;I&#8217;ve been a director for 15 years—what&#8217;s my role now with these Agile teams?&#8217; People are starting to question what it is they&#8217;re supposed to do.&#8221; And it&#8217;s not only evolving cultures and approaches challenging leaders, but evolving technologies, too. &#8220;The idea of using microservices, for example, is a very different way of thinking,&#8221; he notes. &#8220;Those managers and directors and VPs are evolving from managing people to managing a process or managing mindsets and skills of the workers, and managing problems or managing the information flow into these groups. That&#8217;s going to require a very different set of skills and new types of training.&#8221; (<a href="#t=790">13:10</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/great-leaders-inspire-innovation-and-creativity-from-within-their-workforces/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Strong leaders forge an intersection of knowledge and experience</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/strong-leaders-forge-an-intersection-of-knowledge-and-experience/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/strong-leaders-forge-an-intersection-of-knowledge-and-experience/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 09:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Webb]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Big Systemic Thinking]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=10839</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Craig Lemasters, CEO of Global Executive Group, about what companies face when navigating the digital transformation. They [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Rita J. King, co-director and EVP for business development at Science House, recently conducted a series of interviews with business leaders, exploring the challenges and hurdles companies face in evolving business landscapes. In this interview, King chats with Craig Lemasters, CEO of Global Executive Group, about what companies face when navigating the digital transformation. They also talk about the power of humility and what it means to be an agile leader.</p>



<p>Here are some highlights from their conversation:</p>



<p>&#8220;Digital transformation&#8221; means something different to every company. The key to successfully traversing the transformation, Lemasters explains, is to identify specifically what it means to a particular company. In his case, he was running a global insurance company called Assurance Solutions, and he identified two specific areas of focus: &#8220;we knew we needed to have a digital relationship with the end consumer. &#8230; [And] we knew we needed to have some type of digital distribution model.&#8221; (<a href="#t=153">02:33</a>)</p>



<p>To succeed in a new space, Lemasters came to realize, requires both knowledge and experience—an intersection Lemasters uses to define &#8220;wisdom.&#8221; This realization led to Lemasters&#8217; big &#8220;ah-ha!&#8221; moment: &#8220;The stumbling block for digital was, quite frankly, that we didn&#8217;t have either knowledge or experience on digital, and it started with me. I mean, it started with me even as a CEO. I started looking at my team and realized none of us really had a lot of knowledge and experience on this thing called digital. The whole &#8220;ah-ha&#8221; experience was that speed bump. What if we inserted knowledge and experience into the room—could we get to the point much quicker? That&#8217;s what&#8217;s become my passion &#8212; how do we interject this thing called wisdom into the conversation, into the process, just to get us there faster?&#8221; (<a href="#t=340">05:40</a>)</p>



<p>Lemasters argues that humility is key to being a strong, agile leader. Being able to make decisions at the rate of speed required today takes, if not a village, at least <em>some</em> additional expertise. &#8220;The &#8216;humility quotient&#8217; is the willingness for leaders to literally embrace outside thinking,&#8221; Lemasters explained. &#8220;Some would call it criticism; it really isn&#8217;t. I mean, most of this work is about the unknown, and you just haven&#8217;t been there yet. What I found is if we just have enough humility to accept that and actually invite in some people who have the wisdom in these swim lanes, increasing the speed at which we learn, we get over ourselves pretty quickly.&#8221; (<a href="#t=676">11:16</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/strong-leaders-forge-an-intersection-of-knowledge-and-experience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>It’s an unprecedented crisis: 8 things to do right now</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-an-unprecedented-crisis-8-things-to-do-right-now/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-an-unprecedented-crisis-8-things-to-do-right-now/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cynthia Owens]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=12485</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Even with a stellar crisis plan, the COVID-19 pandemic presents a set of challenges unprecedented in our lifetimes. We don’t know what’s going to happen, and we’re dealing with something growing exponentially, creating uncertainty on a global scale. I managed a team of 40 in Singapore during SARS. That crisis was different, hitting Singapore and [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even with a stellar crisis plan, the COVID-19 pandemic presents a set of challenges unprecedented in our lifetimes. We don’t know what’s going to happen, and we’re dealing with something growing exponentially, creating uncertainty on a global scale. I managed a team of 40 in Singapore during SARS. That crisis was different, hitting Singapore and a handful of other cities. But plenty of parallels exist: it was a health crisis, and the lessons learned might serve you and your organization well now. Here are some things to do immediately, including addressing issues around remote work, to ensure that business continues as usual.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>This <em>is</em> your full-time job right now</strong>. Whatever was on your priority list last month, isn’t anymore. This is your full-time job right now. That means you may need to tell the C-suite that their pet project has been delayed, and you may need to tell employees that performance reviews and team meetings are on hold. You and your team may be working very long days in the coming weeks.</li>
<li><strong>Push communications twice a day</strong>. In the arc of a crisis, we don’t know quite where we are—and that uncertainty can cause panic for some employees. News is coming out fast and good information is hard to come by. Create a morning and late afternoon update so your people know you are paying attention to their well-being. Share new information and repeat facts you already know. As we move from crisis to recovery—and we will recover—your updates can move from twice a day back to once a day and, then, less often.</li>
<li><strong>Let go of perfection</strong>. It’s better to send out a revised set of rules everyday rather than being silent for days while executives try to land on the perfect policy and ideal language. Modify standard policies and make exceptions to long-held rules. Be transparent—it’s OK not to have all the answers because there are few definitive answers. Be transparent and say what you know and admit what you don’t know.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor the CDC and your state health authorities</strong>. There will be rumors, fake news, and speculation. The only thing we know is that we have never been through this before. In 1918 during the Spanish Flu, it took days to cross the Atlantic and antibiotics hadn’t been invented. Because this is unprecedented in our modern world, the CDC and your state health authorities are doing admirable work providing the most reliable and trustworthy information.</li>
<li><strong>People will respond very differently—prepare for that to cause problems</strong>. Some people may begin refusing to come to work—others might seem cavalier about COVID19. That divide may create serious friction in your organization. People who come to work begin to resent those who don’t. Those who stay home begin to believe that some of their co-workers don’t care about the health of families. After SARS, it took a long time to heal this split in the office. Acknowledge the split and that both points of view are valid.</li>
<li><strong>Create new remote work guidelines—today</strong>. It doesn’t matter if you change these guidelines (see #3), just put out some basics. Is there a daily meeting? Will teams need to check in every day? What tools should they use? Should all meeting participants turn on their video? Whatever you decide—put out some guidelines so people have a place to start. You can modify these tomorrow and completely rewrite them when the crisis passes.</li>
<li><strong>We may not return to “business as usual.”</strong> You are going to want to reassure people, and that may be an important part of your job. Tell people it will be OK—because it will. But be careful: don’t make any promises, because “OK” may not mean what it used to mean. Companies will likely make changes during the crisis or as things begin to recover. And, this may be an opportunity to change how your organization works. You are going to learn things about how your people learn, adapt, and improvise that will inform the new future.</li>
<li><strong>Take care of yourself</strong>. This is a marathon not a sprint. And, to carry that metaphor forward, we don’t know the course of the marathon. We know some of you have been working around the clock—that’s not going to end tomorrow. If you aren’t healthy and grounded, you can’t see your team through this. Ground yourself; whatever gives you peace and contentment—you need that now, for you, for your family, and for the demands of your work.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-an-unprecedented-crisis-8-things-to-do-right-now/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 ways to get untapped talent in your organization to contribute</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/10-ways-to-get-untapped-talent-in-your-organization-to-contribute/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/10-ways-to-get-untapped-talent-in-your-organization-to-contribute/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pamela Rucker]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Your Company's Talent]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=11940</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Every day, leaders actively look for ways to use their employees’ capabilities, but as they do this, research indicates that the bulk of organizational talent still goes untapped. This could occur for a myriad of reasons. Perhaps: You don’t recognize the value of talent that exists in your current workforce. The people are there, but [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Every day, leaders actively look for ways to use their employees’ capabilities, but as they do this, research indicates that the bulk of organizational talent still goes untapped. This could occur for a myriad of reasons. Perhaps:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>You don’t recognize the value of talent</em> that exists in your current workforce. The people are there, but you don’t see them.</li>
<li><em>Your workers don’t recognize the value of their talent</em> as it relates to your strategy. The opportunity is there, but they don’t see it.</li>
<li><em>Your workers haven’t been sufficiently trained to reach their highest levels</em> of potential when performing their work. They don’t know how to turn raw talent into a competitive capability.</li>
<li><em>Your workers haven’t been sufficiently inspired to bring their best talents to work with you</em>, so they are offering them to another organization. In today’s gig economy, that could be devastating for you. That means your people are learning, but you aren’t leveraging them, so someone else is reaping the reward as they grow.</li>
</ul>
<p>A big part of your leadership success is understanding how to reimagine the way you operate in your own role so that you focus on the organization’s biggest priorities. That will help you know what power to unleash for yourself and what capabilities to foster in others. A good rule of thumb is for you to find the right mix of:</p>
<ul>
<li>Teaching: coaching and mentoring your people on strategic priorities and using their capabilities correctly</li>
<li>Telling: sharing stories, statistics, and strategies about where you’re going, what’s expected, and what’s worked in the past</li>
<li>Trusting: delegating work to others so you’ll have time to be far more strategic in your own work efforts</li>
<li>Trying: exploring new innovation opportunities as you look for new ways to grow the business or become more efficient</li>
</ul>
<p>In order to get untapped talent in your organization to contribute, consider helping your people with 10 key things:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Understanding that you value many different types of talent</strong>Many organizations struggle with identifying and using the talents of their people, so they often don’t know when to use what they have in-house versus investing in outside resources. Before you launch on a large reskilling or outsourcing campaign, start by communicating the value you see in people having a variety of different talents. For instance, instead of focusing on purely technical or business roles, start looking for those people who are great collaborators, those who are great negotiators or deal brokers, those who can visualize enterprise or societal problems, those who are great visionaries, and those who are great orchestrators. You will start to see multiple people step up to new opportunities if you focus on getting the right fit for a person who&#8217;s already in your organization. Remember: just because a person <em>can</em> do a role (which is about capability) doesn’t mean that’s what that person <em>should</em> be doing now (which is about fit). Look at people’s experiences, competencies, capabilities, and interests as they all relate to your current business needs. Then validate various types of talent so you can draw on all of them to fulfill your strategic priorities.</li>
<li><strong>Accurately assessing their potential</strong>Organizations can sometimes struggle with two distinct types of people. One group is full of very talented individuals, but they do not understand how and why their talent is valuable to the organization’s strategy. They know how to fulfill the requirements of their job description, but they are unable to connect their work back to the broader success of the business. The second group is also comprised of talented individuals, but in this case, they know their experiences and capabilities, and they’re able to make connections to creative opportunities for their talent in countless ways. Their challenge lies in the fact that you don’t see their potential. You’re so accustomed to seeing people one way that you can’t see the forest for the trees. Learn to be more intentional and inclusionary in the way you assess team members and apply their skills to your overall goals.</li>
<li><strong>Using multiple approaches to match talent to work</strong>Typically, organizations look at their strategy first and then try to find the talent and capabilities that give them a competitive advantage. One alternative is to assess the existing talent you have in your organization, and then, given that talent, ask yourself what you might be able to produce. Consider case #1, where you might contemplate building a new system. You identify a need for new architects, coders, infrastructure team members, etc. Now consider case #2, where you still evaluate your entire team, but find that in addition to architects, coders, and infrastructure team members, you have artists, communicators, historians, security experts, gamers, and even digital laggards. Given your team makeup and your customers’ needs, ask yourself what kind of solutions you could offer if you have all of those skills at your disposal. There is a vast array of offerings waiting to be exposed by the untapped capabilities of your team.</li>
<li><strong>Making it exciting to do something different</strong>Your people have taken a long time to build their reputations, so occasionally you may find that some of them are reluctant to step out into a new role. In order to help them take the risk to use hidden talents in new ways, generate some energy around the effort you’re offering. Create a buzz in the office that makes this a hot opportunity, one that everyone wants to be involved in. By promoting the project and whipping up enthusiasm both inside and outside your team, you can emphasize cool new opportunities and roles that those who sign on will be building something bigger than themselves, a project so rewarding they won&#8217;t want to miss out.</li>
<li><strong>Branding their work in new ways</strong>Start to think about your work more abstractly, and teach your direct reports to think that way as well. For instance, instead of looking at your group as an infrastructure team responsible for setting up servers, give your team a tagline that brands their efforts in an abstract, yet inventive way. For instance, migrate their thinking about their job from pure infrastructure work to “helping the organization move at the speed of light.” This becomes a simple, yet powerful reminder that you are no longer doing business as usual, and new skills are required to help you be successful. People will naturally start to determine ways they can use their hidden talent to help the organization move faster, they’ll start to have different conversations with their colleagues, and you will see innovative solutions that wouldn’t occur with your normal modes of working.</li>
<li><strong>Creating multiple ways to become a rock star</strong>Recognize that most people won’t move on to lead departments or huge numbers of people. Create paths where talent can grow and be recognized because of their deep knowledge and collaborative efforts, even if they don’t request or receive a promotion. Develop “Unsung Hero” awards for those who work behind the scenes to make everything run smoothly. Recognize individual players who develop solutions as well as those who have become the glue that holds everything together, and recognize those who develop ideas on the fringe to help you work through a really tough delivery.</li>
<li><strong>Creating a culture where it’s easy for people to speak up</strong>We often ask people to speak up, but then force them to work in cultures where it’s virtually impossible for them to actually do it. That creates an environment where most of your employees are not their best versions of themselves every day. They’ve learned that it’s smart to be quiet, even when they have knowledge that might help you win. People may see opportunities you can capitalize on, capabilities they could offer, or competitive advantage they could create, but because of the way your culture works, they’ve learned to be quiet. They cage those thoughts within because they do not have a voice, or they are not allowed to have vision on your team. Demonstrate the value of every person’s contribution by intentionally creating space (in meetings, in email, at the watercooler, etc.) for everyone to develop influence on the team.</li>
<li><strong>Making it easy and okay for people to build coalitions of support</strong>Allow team members to reach out to others in the company who think and act like them, or who are interested in the same subject matters. Provide an autonomous environment where they can pursue their ambitions with others. These places can serve as incubators for ideas and sandboxes for new innovation. You’ll see new opportunities emerge as people collaborate to solve problems, or start to recognize commonality in roles and processes. Instead of stifling these conversations, encourage them, because they are a sign that a coalition is forming and your productivity could soon be rising.</li>
<li><strong>Bringing a strategic focus to their work</strong>Rather than focusing on a job description, help team members understand the real job to be done, and recognize that their future work might be performed in a different way than their work is completed today. Give them a mission, a vision, a way to fit in to the overall strategic priorities of the business. Help them find a dream that is strong enough for them to take ownership of known and unknown tasks and want to individually push them forward. Give them time to develop capabilities today that you know you’ll need tomorrow. But then stick to your word. Often, people are promised the moon when they take on a job and then find themselves stuck working in the basement. This can lead to enormous levels of disengagement because, while employees still have to do the work, they have no real outlet for their innovation. That will force them to look elsewhere to solve their problem.</li>
<li><strong>Rethinking your own work and ways of working</strong>Go back to the drawing board for your own role. Understand what your real work is. Often, as people stay with an organization, the <em>work</em> changes, but they don’t change the <em>way they work</em>. You might be doing different work today than you did a few years ago, but your thought processes and work patterns can be essentially the same. Step back and take a look at your current role. What you are trying to accomplish, and who will you need for support in that effort? Are you doing the right work? Are you intentional about the way you use the time you spend with your leaders, peers, and directs? How do you use the mix of your time? How do you use their time?</li>
</ol>
<p>By using these 10 techniques, you will be able to harness the power of your organization’s untapped talent, capitalize on your people’s capabilities, and create a culture that motivates them to partner with you to create long-term success for your organization.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/10-ways-to-get-untapped-talent-in-your-organization-to-contribute/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Use your people as competitive advantage</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-your-people-as-competitive-advantage/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-your-people-as-competitive-advantage/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pamela Rucker]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Your Company's Talent]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=11068</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In a fast-paced digital world, it is tempting to suppose that deploying the latest technology is the lynchpin to competitive advantage. Extremely powerful digital technologies are now accessible to most companies—meaning you must find new ways to distinguish yourself in a crowded field. One very effective method for unearthing strategies that differentiate your organization from [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In a fast-paced digital world, it is tempting to suppose that deploying the latest technology is the lynchpin to competitive advantage. Extremely powerful digital technologies are now accessible to most companies—meaning you must find new ways to distinguish yourself in a crowded field.</p>



<p>One very effective method for unearthing strategies that differentiate your organization from everyone else is to leverage your people as a competitive advantage. “Using people,” in this context, means placing an emphasis on any full-time employee, contractor, partner, supplier, gig worker, etc., who is part of your extended ecosystem of strategy and delivery. These are the groups and individuals who provide the fuel to make your technology engine work. You will find them interspersed inside and outside your organization, and it is your task to harness their collective power to build a coalition of support for your business. If you do this well, you can use ecosystem engagement as a way to build stickiness between your organization and employees. As we progress through this latest digital era, we are starting to see more strength in numbers—particularly from unexpected partnerships that provide different perspectives and allow ideas and innovation to originate from a variety of sources. By embracing cognitive diversity, these partnerships thrive because they’ve learned how to tap into a variety of players in order to design and deliver a compelling solution. Each time you tap into it, your people ecosystem presents a blank canvas of potential innovation, and capitalizing on their insight and adaptability creates new opportunities for unique advantage.</p>



<p>Organizations that struggle to keep or fully engage their people ecosystem may find themselves facing the quandary of having people who once worked with them or for them easily becoming foes. History shows us that <em>not</em> recognizing the latent talent in your untapped, disengaged employees creates a hazard for your organization: a cohort of employees who understand your strategic priorities and what you value and use that knowledge to compete, providing new services aimed at dissatisfied customers looking for new options. Armed with the quick and easy tools that make spinning up a startup or a competitive initiative effortless, former employees can quickly wreak havoc on your best-laid plans—something that it used to take a much larger organization to accomplish. What can you do? Go on the offense, pursuing a strong people-based competitive advantage to build a vibrant ecosystem of employees and partners who feel valued and aligned with your organizational goals.</p>



<p>A significant challenge you might face when you are looking to strengthen your people ecosystem is the temptation to continue operating within your traditional mode of working, and within your traditional types of relationships. Your old ways of working required one level of engagement, but to exploit the power of the digital economy, you have to bring new players into the ecosystem and be far more intentional about the way you interact with them to use their capabilities. As you do this, you will quickly find that what it takes to make one group or person happy is not what it takes to make another group or person happy, and you will constantly negotiate outcomes to ensure everyone feels like they are in a win-win scenario. The digital economy moves at a frenetic pace and causes massive changes in personal and societal expectations. Solutions that worked just a few years ago will no longer keep customers and partners happy. That’s why it’s vital that you maintain an environment where people feel they are in a win-win relationship and they see your success as something that&#8217;s good for them. Leaders who assume they have good relationships with freelancers, contractors, or suppliers can quickly find themselves struggling with the same concerns vocalized by disengaged employees, and this type of disconnect can dramatically impact your level of output. You lose a great deal of innovation capacity when you can no longer count on people to give the extra effort that comes because they are autonomously motivated to succeed. To keep everyone happy and excited at the same time, you will need an agile engagement approach. That means the painstaking work you do today to build a high degree of engagement with your people may have to be revisited often to keep them invested in your organization.</p>



<p>If you want to develop a strong, competitive advantage built on the expertise of people in your ecosystem, you should focus on five key strategies:</p>



<ol><li><strong>Discover what your customers deeply value</strong>. Develop a cross-functional, inside-out team that focuses intensely on this issue. Nothing works better to discover what your customers value than to have a diverse group of people who can relate to and reflect the customer base. For instance, rather than using all of your talent to concentrate on delivering better features to existing customers, use some of your talent to uncover and solve new problems. This will help you move from a product-centric approach to a customer-centric approach.</li><li><strong>Have a value proposition that people can engage with.</strong> Creating a company identity, placing your company in the marketplace, making clear what you hope to accomplish, the future you want to achieve, and communicating all of that to those you work with provides the raw materials for engagement, for helping those employees, partners, contractors, and even gig workers find a place for themselves in your company’s future.</li><li><strong>Recognize that great people are everywhere in your organization, tucked away where you can&#8217;t see them.</strong> Look for talent spread out through every level in your company and start to use that talent in new ways. Some of your best opportunities for ideation will come from crowdsourcing innovation up, down and across your team. For instance, when leading a technical team, use traditional technical skills like understanding objects, understanding layers, or understanding components in a LEGO-like architecture, and use those functional skills as analogs to the soft skills that help team members understand leadership and how the different parts of the organization relate to each other. Help team members recognize that there are layers to the way that the business works, layers to the way that people work, or layers to relationships. Help people with high potential understand how all parts of the business work together and demonstrate how to conceptualize new ways to use old processes. Transform team knowledge from solely a functional or technical capability to a business capability, and work with your staff to be very deliberate about the roles and opportunities they take or the places where they invest their time.</li><li><strong>Build teams with cognitive diversity.</strong> Deliberately look for people and partners who come to the table from different paths in life. Have multi-generational, multi-ethnic, geographically dispersed teams that understand how to work well together by leaving bias at the door. Have multi-disciplinary teams pour through your data with the express assignment of finding new problems to solve. Recognize that just because you invited everyone to the table, that does not mean they all have the courage to speak up. Provide prompts and cues to ensure team members participate, describing their findings, testing their ideas, and sharing insights into their thought processes. This will spur collaboration, spark innovative ideas within others, and remove the stigma associated with failure. To help move this forward, design your meetings to enable every voice in the group. Talk openly about great attempts that failed, share team successes, and give room for even the most silent participants to open up and share their thoughts. People can often believe the smartest person in the room is also the most confident person in the room, and that&#8217;s not always the case. You can frequently have very astute team members with a wealth of knowledge built from their path in life and professional experiences, but they might lack the confidence or interest in speaking up in front of a group. Create a standard knowledge sharing process so team members can exchange discoveries and discuss ideas in open and honest ways.</li><li><strong>Allow employees to move around in order to develop different capabilities.</strong> You&#8217;ll want to discover early in your team members&#8217; careers what they might want to do later in life. This is true for your partners and suppliers just as it is for your employees. Spend some time discovering their capabilities. Some people might transition into great business leaders, others might become great technical leaders, and others might become strong master contributors who really know your customers and your business well. Regardless of the track they choose, you want use their capabilities strategically so they stay engaged and excited about solving your most pressing business problems. Whether it&#8217;s working as a coder, designing a strategy, or understanding the bowels of the enterprise and how to get things to move when they are stuck, allow team members to grow and be useful in ways that create opportunities in a variety of places. Give them a chance to travel, take on choice assignments, work remotely, change jobs and roles, dabble in fringe interests, or work together on pet projects. This means you will have to hand off commodity work to more junior staff so your senior leaders can grow organically in ways that work for them and the organization. If you overlook this, your people can feel stagnant and will look to create opportunities for movement on their own, which means they will likely look for employment elsewhere.</li></ol>



<p>As you focus on these areas, you will naturally see new and different capabilities emerge. Recognize these capabilities in your people not just for what they can do for you now, but for what they can do for you in the future, and then strategically position them so they can help you transform the business. Placing people in flexible roles helps them come up with autonomous innovation because the deeper they get into technology, the content, or their knowledge of the business, the more they uncover opportunities for you to get better, to modernize, to offer new solutions, or to have the next big thing that might transform the industry. Instead of looking at your people solely as tools to fulfill your current work, look at them as opportunities to uncover new jobs, expand your offerings, design new partnerships, discover a new mission, and recognize new customers. By doing that, you will have a talent advantage that cannot be duplicated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/use-your-people-as-competitive-advantage/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s important to cultivate your organization&#8217;s collective genius</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-important-to-cultivate-your-organizations-collective-genius/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-important-to-cultivate-your-organizations-collective-genius/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 05:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Webb]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Foo Camp '19]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=10231</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In this interview from O&#8217;Reilly Foo Camp 2019, Pamela Rucker, president of The Rucker Group, discusses the challenges people face when they&#8217;re entering into management roles for the first time, and how CxOs can help mitigate some of those challenges. She also talks about the future of work and how nurturing talent is going to [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this interview from O&#8217;Reilly Foo Camp 2019, Pamela Rucker, president of The Rucker Group, discusses the challenges people face when they&#8217;re entering into management roles for the first time, and how CxOs can help mitigate some of those challenges. She also talks about the future of work and how nurturing talent is going to be more important than ever.</p>



<p>Highlights from the interview include:</p>



<p>One of the biggest challenges new managers face is asking for help or clarification during the transition to their new management role. Rucker says the issue has more to do with company culture and leadership than with shy managers. &#8220;There are some organizations where even the most expressive people have difficulty speaking up because the culture is such that you don&#8217;t go against the grain. You don&#8217;t say anything. I remember working at a large legacy organization and we had done a great job setting the tone in the room, talking about all the things that people need to work on, how they need to be able to express their challenges, and maybe where they don&#8217;t get it. So I said, &#8216;Tell me some of the things you&#8217;re concerned about right now.&#8217; I saw on the people&#8217;s faces that they were ready to speak, and the C-level executives chose that moment to step up and say, &#8216;I really wonder who&#8217;s going to say anything.&#8217; Instantly, everyone shut down. So, I do think it&#8217;s situational. There are times when you might have people who would be brave enough to say something, but the leader has the responsibility to enable the voice. The leader has a responsibility to let people have enough power to say something in that moment that maybe they don&#8217;t agree with, and to recognize that it&#8217;s not saying anything about them as an individual leader as much as it is about the person who might need help walking that bridge.&#8221; (<a href="#t=160">02:40</a>)</p>



<p>Rucker also discusses the concept of &#8220;dual paths&#8221;—not everyone is cut out to be a manager; there are other paths to fulfilling career goals, and to rewarding outstanding work. &#8220;If you think about how people transition and become more valuable over time to organizations, typically, there&#8217;s this belief that the only way for me to show additional value is for me to become a manager. &#8230; There&#8217;s an opportunity not just to progress as a manager, but maybe to go deep in your expertise, and then demonstrate how you might be well-connected in the organization or well-connected in the industry, and show how that adds value to the company&#8217;s strategic priorities. That&#8217;s just as important as being able to manage people. Talking to an organization about how they can create those types of roles is important as well because it shouldn&#8217;t be that the only way you can achieve the things you want to achieve in life is to be forced into the ability to manage people or manage projects, which may not align with your capabilities.&#8221; (<a href="#t=348">05:48</a>)</p>



<p>The future of work is going to raise more issues than navigating remote work or gig economies—Rucker says leaders will need a vastly different skill set. &#8220;It&#8217;s not just about technology, but also about how to look at your staff and figure out what their capabilities are and then figure out how to attach that to your capability and really use the power of collective genius. Your competitive advantage is going to come from what you know about your customers, what you know about the products and services you offer, and what you know about your people, and then how you put those things together to come up with an incredible recipe that cannot be duplicated because you have talent equity. &#8230; A leader will need to foster an environment where they all can come together and raise up those hidden talents and then collectively put them together into some type of new talent.&#8221; (<a href="#t=427">07:07</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/its-important-to-cultivate-your-organizations-collective-genius/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>AI is an opportunity to redefine entire ecosystems</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/ai-is-an-opportunity-to-redefine-entire-ecosystems/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/ai-is-an-opportunity-to-redefine-entire-ecosystems/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:20:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Wong and Roger Magoulas]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AI & ML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blockchain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5437</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[O’Reilly’s Roger Magoulas sat down with Jeff Wong, global chief innovation officer at EY, to discuss the impact of artificial intelligence (AI). Wong talked about how organizations are grappling with emerging technologies, why your company should make AI a priority, and how to train for jobs that don’t yet exist. Highlights from Wong and Magoulas’ [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>O’Reilly’s Roger Magoulas sat down with Jeff Wong, global chief innovation officer at EY, to discuss the impact of artificial intelligence (AI). Wong talked about how organizations are grappling with emerging technologies, why your company should make AI a priority, and how to train for jobs that don’t yet exist.</p>
<p>Highlights from Wong and Magoulas’ discussion include:</p>
<p>Company boards aren’t asking the right questions because they lack the diversity that reflects the things they need to know about the world. Wong says board members tend to be hired for what they&#8217;ve done for the past 30 years, which would be fine if the next 10 years was going to look like the last 30. (<a href="#t=101">1:41</a>)</p>
<p>Automation and AI are changing things quickly. The question for companies is whether to embrace these changes or feed into the dialogue of fear. Wong argues that every industry should look at this an opportunity to redefine themselves and their entire ecosystem. (<a href="#t=404">6:44</a>)</p>
<p>Hollywood reactions like “the world&#8217;s going to end” and “the robots are going to come get us” aside, the reality is that AI as a set of technologies has the potential for an immediate return on investment. (<a href="#t=783">13:03</a>)</p>
<p>Wong’s company is working to apply blockchain concepts to the enterprise with research around things like zero knowledge proofs, which allow private transactions to “ride the public blockchain rails,” he says. In conjunction with Microsoft, they built a royalties management system for Microsoft’s gaming group, which at scale might be the highest volume blockchain in the world. It will be bigger than bitcoin and ethereum combined on a daily basis, Wong estimates. (<a href="#t=852">14:12</a>)</p>
<p>Looking ahead to the jobs our kids will have, Wong cites a statistic that around 80% of the jobs kids will be able to consider haven&#8217;t yet been created. That speaks to how organizations need to change. He says companies now need to look for young people who can solve complex problems in uncertain environments, because that&#8217;s really the issue at hand. How do we train employees for jobs that don’t yet exist? How do we train our kids to think about a world that we cannot define for them? Wong notes specific skill sets &#8212; like being able to code or learning math &#8212; are important, but what&#8217;s more important is the “learning how to learn” aspect of that. (<a href="#t=1006">16:46</a>)</p>
<p>You can see Wong’s complete presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/ai-is-an-opportunity-to-redefine-entire-ecosystems/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why grit and kindness are necessary for digital transformation</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/why-grit-and-kindness-are-necessary-for-digital-transformation/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/why-grit-and-kindness-are-necessary-for-digital-transformation/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:19:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katie Verducci]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5446</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Grit and kindness, two emotional soft skills, are also necessary for companies to succeed in the digital age, says Katie Verducci, PR lead at Bitwise Industries. These characteristics are not only possessed by many members of traditionally marginalized communities but help companies grow and thrive thanks to the talents of a diverse workforce. Highlights from [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Grit and kindness, two emotional soft skills, are also necessary for companies to succeed in the digital age, says Katie Verducci, PR lead at Bitwise Industries. These characteristics are not only possessed by many members of traditionally marginalized communities but help companies grow and thrive thanks to the talents of a diverse workforce.</p>
<p>Highlights from Verducci’s presentation include:</p>
<p>Diversity and inclusion are not technology trends, but they are trends affecting the technology industry. Tech loses out when smart and capable people from backgrounds different than the ones usually represented in Silicon Valley, New York City, Boston, or Austin, Texas, are not given the opportunity to participate. These people bring different values and perspectives that help make technology better. (<a href="#t=56">00:56</a>)</p>
<p>Each year, there are only 60,000 computer science graduates from college, but there are more than a million job openings in technology needed to be filled. This is why companies will need to look outside the places they traditional look to fill these roles. (<a href="#t=461">7:41</a>)</p>
<p>Diversity and inclusion are not just good talking points, they are good business decisions. Research from MIT has shown that teams with women are more likely to attack problems faster and solve complex tasks more efficiently. African-Americans and Latinos represent half as much of the tech industry as they do other industries. Hiring from diverse talent pools enhances a company’s ability to think creatively, execute well, and increase revenue. (<a href="#t=591">9:51</a>)</p>
<p>You can see Verducci’s complete presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/why-grit-and-kindness-are-necessary-for-digital-transformation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to get things done in a large organization</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:19:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Cutts]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5396</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The nature of work and how business gets done is rapidly changing in the digital age. In this presentation, Matt Cutts, acting director for the United States Digital Service and former software engineer at Google, reminds people it is possible to cut through the red tape at large organizations to get stuff done for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The nature of work and how business gets done is rapidly changing in the digital age. In this presentation, Matt Cutts, acting director for the United States Digital Service and former software engineer at Google, reminds people it is possible to cut through the red tape at large organizations to get stuff done for the betterment of customers and end-users.</p>
<p>Highlights from Cutts’ presentation include:</p>
<p>It’s crucial for large organizations to choose a North Star &#8212; a vision and reason for why they uniquely exist. This North Star informs the company’s strategies and goals. For example, at Google it was to organize the world’s information and make it accessible. Every project and effort by the people employed at Google was in service of this vision. Without this, employees are just reactive and working in a vacuum. (<a href="#t=57">00:57</a>)</p>
<p>Emotion plays a large role in the collective ability to get things done. Emotions, such as fear, can create obstacles and prevent an organization from accomplishing its goals. Strong negative emotions can make organizations risk averse, or create incentives for people to not want the responsibility of failure. The fear of risk ends up being worse than the actual risk. Trust and empathy, on the other hand, can lead to powerful results. (<a href="#t=144">02:24</a>)</p>
<p>Talking to your users is the most powerful hack you can deploy in the fight to get things done within large organizations. Veterans’ Affairs (VA) discovered there was a gap between its mission to deliver an exceptional customer experience and what veterans had to say about actually navigating the bureaucracy. But, by finally talking to veterans, it allowed the VA to take action in the service of its mission. (<a href="#t=413">06:53</a>)</p>
<p>You can see Cutts’ complete presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/how-to-get-things-done-in-a-large-organization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Digital transformation is a people problem, not a technology problem</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/digital-transformation-is-a-people-problem-not-a-technology-problem/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/digital-transformation-is-a-people-problem-not-a-technology-problem/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:18:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Bersin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5387</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Technology problems tend to be the main focus of discussions around digital transformation. In this talk, industry analyst and researcher Josh Bersin presents an alternate take, explaining that the more advanced technology becomes, the more complicated—and important—the people part of business becomes. Investing in employee growth and engagement will be at least as important as [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Technology problems tend to be the main focus of discussions around digital transformation. In this talk, industry analyst and researcher Josh Bersin presents an alternate take, explaining that the more advanced technology becomes, the more complicated—and important—the people part of business becomes. Investing in employee growth and engagement will be at least as important as technology investments.</p>
<p>Highlights from Bersin’s presentation include:</p>
<p>The problems companies run into once they decide on a digital strategy—how to organize, how to build agility in teams, and how to build a service-centric organization—aren’t technology problems; they’re people problems. (<a href="#t=87">1:27</a>)</p>
<p>Even though automation is creating new opportunities, there&#8217;s a significant number of people who need to re-skill. The World Economic Forum and a company called Burning Glass looked at the future jobs being created by artificial intelligence (AI). They found that most people can be re-trained in about 18 to 24 months, but companies haven&#8217;t figured out how to do that yet. Bersin notes that tools like O&#8217;Reilly Learning and other solutions will help fill these gaps. (<a href="#t=193">3:13</a>)</p>
<p>It&#8217;s hard to build an organization that’s a great place to work for everybody. If you look at the data on engagement and at the companies getting it right, the only thing unique about those companies is their leadership, their focus, their understanding, and their belief that people are the product. (<a href="#t=437">7:17</a>)</p>
<p>Companies don&#8217;t operate like hierarchies anymore. An organization might be managed like a hierarchy in job titles and levels, pay, and leadership models, but people actually work in small groups and iterate on small teams. This is a significant change to the world of work. HR folks need to rethink how they manage, train, support, and hire people around that shift. (<a href="#t=549">9:09</a>)</p>
<p>In talking with a highly engaged bank in Canada, Bersin discovered a good example of how companies are changing the ways they think of themselves. When he asked an HR leader at the bank what made it such a great place to work, she said, “we&#8217;re not a bank. We&#8217;re actually here to promote the health and wellness of our communities. We just happen to sell mortgages and have checking accounts as the way we do that, but that&#8217;s not our mission.” This is a new way of thinking that’s starting to catch fire—the way businesses manage people is really about rethinking the value proposition of the business they’re in. (<a href="#t=838">13:58</a>)</p>
<p>You can see Bersin’s complete presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/digital-transformation-is-a-people-problem-not-a-technology-problem/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Balance your ecosystem to succeed at business</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 21:10:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Baldwin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Next Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Insights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radar Event]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/?p=5410</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[In this talk, O’Reilly President Laura Baldwin describes how O’Reilly’s mission-driven approach works, and she outlines why companies should apply a balanced strategy for running their organizations. Highlights from Baldwin’s presentation include: Many companies think about their businesses as a set of three things: customers, employees, and shareholders. These are important, but if you&#8217;re only [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this talk, O’Reilly President Laura Baldwin describes how O’Reilly’s mission-driven approach works, and she outlines why companies should apply a balanced strategy for running their organizations.</p>
<p>Highlights from Baldwin’s presentation include:</p>
<p>Many companies think about their businesses as a set of three things: customers, employees, and shareholders. These are important, but if you&#8217;re only thinking about these things in isolation, you&#8217;re not considering your entire ecosystem. (<a href="#t=217">3:37</a>)</p>
<p>An ecosystem approach means the communities O’Reilly serves need to be part of the thought process. This includes customers, contributors, business partners, vendors, and competitors. O’Reilly aims to keep all of these constituents in balance. (<a href="#t=515">8:35</a>)</p>
<p>O’Reilly’s online learning platform has an ecosystem of talent because the company thinks about what the talent needs, not just what O’Reilly needs. This focus ultimately benefits customers. (<a href="#t=968">16:08</a>)</p>
<p>Baldwin is an an avid reader of business books, but she says many of them over-complicate things. Paying attention to your whole ecosystem and keeping it in balance is the way you succeed. (<a href="#t=1184">19:44</a>)</p>
<p>Watch Baldwin’s full presentation in the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/balance-your-ecosystem-to-succeed-at-business/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Future of the firm</title>
		<link>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/future-of-the-firm/</link>
				<comments>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/future-of-the-firm/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Bersin, Tim O’Reilly, Roger Magoulas and Mike Loukides]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Future of the Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Dive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O'Reilly Radar Analysis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.oreilly.com/radar/future-of-the-firm/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The “future of the firm” is a big deal. As jobs become more automated, and people more often work in teams, with work increasingly done on a contingent and contract basis, you have to ask: “What does a firm really do?” Yes, successful businesses are increasingly digital and technologically astute. But how do they attract [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The “future of the firm” is a big deal. As jobs become more automated, and people more often work in teams, with work increasingly done on a contingent and contract basis, you have to ask: “What does a firm really do?” Yes, successful businesses are increasingly digital and technologically astute. But how do they attract and manage people in a world where two billion people work part-time? How do they develop their workforce when automation is advancing at light speed? And how do they attract customers and full-time employees when competition is high and trust is at an all-time low?</p>
<p>When thinking about the big-picture items affecting the future of the firm, we identified several topics that we discuss in detail in this report:</p>
<p><strong>Trust, responsibility, credibility, honesty, and transparency.</strong><br />
Customers and employees now look for, and hold accountable, firms whose values reflect their own personal beliefs. We’re also seeing a “trust shakeout,” where brands that were formerly trusted lose trust, and new companies build their positions based on ethical behavior. And companies are facing entirely new “trust risks” in social media, hacking, and the design of artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) algorithms.</p>
<p><strong>The search for meaning.</strong><br />
Employees don’t just want money and security; they want satisfaction and meaning. They want to do something worthwhile with their lives.</p>
<p><strong>New leadership models and generational change.</strong><br />
Firms of the 20th century were based on hierarchical command and control models. Those models no longer work. In successful firms, leaders rely on their influence and trustworthiness, not their position.</p>
<p><strong>Big systemic thinking.</strong><br />
The firm of the future must be able to adapt to changing environments, changing interactions with its customers, and changing communications patterns within the organization. Every firm must understand their business is a complex system, and that it’s impossible to change one aspect of the organization without affecting everything else.</p>
<p><strong>New kinds of partnerships between people and machines.</strong><br />
AI and ML are changing almost every job. This shift raises many questions: Who manages the machines, and how? What skills do those new managers need, and how are they acquired? What kinds of compensation are appropriate?</p>
<p><strong>From hierarchies to networks.</strong><br />
Firms of the future are trending toward networked marketplaces where organizations build on their core competencies and outsource the rest to a network of contractors and free agents. Increasingly, these networks are managed by centralized algorithmic systems.</p>
<p><strong>Free agency, personal brands, and the evolving employer/employee relationship.</strong><br />
Employees are free agents, which means hiring and retaining talent is difficult. Firms need to help employees meet their career goals, satisfy employees’ ethical concerns, and more.</p>
<p><strong>Compensation beyond pay.</strong><br />
The nature of compensation is changing, with firms offering alternate work relationships, more flexible workplaces, training opportunities, additional perks and benefits, and more of a sense of “taking care” of workers.</p>
<p><strong>Diversity, inclusion, and fairness at work.</strong><br />
It’s well known (but not well practiced) that diverse teams produce better results. But achieving diversity is more than a matter of filling the pipeline with new hires. Diversity requires solving compensation problems, creating a safe workplace, inclusion, and ensuring everyone knows their opinions will be respected.</p>
<p><strong>Board governance and diversity.</strong><br />
Board independence and increased diversity can help improve board governance. Diverse boards provide broader perspectives and ask better questions, helping improve outcomes and adapting to rapidly changing business environments.</p>
<p>This is only a preliminary map of the territory, with some topics appearing across multiple regions. Our high-level view tries to distinguish the cities from the fields, mountains, rivers, and oceans that surround them.</p>
<p>Whatever the future of the firm, rest assured, it won’t be business as usual.</p>
<h2>Setting the context</h2>
<p>Before diving into the details, let’s look at the factors that have influenced our perspective on the future of the firm.</p>
<p>The economist <a href="http://bit.ly/2NcgUtm">Milton Friedman claimed</a> that “there is one and only one social responsibility of business—to use its resources&#8230;to increase its profits.” This formula no longer works. Today, driven by technological, social, and political factors, success requires broad systemic thinking about all the players the organization affects—employees, customers, society, the environment, fairness, inequality, and purpose. The context, the milieu, the incentives, the scale, and the workforce expectations that organizations operate in have all changed in a world with increasingly sophisticated automation, with massive social connectivity, and with issues of inequality and climate change. More and more people are questioning whether the basic tenets of capitalism work best for everyone, whether automation will wipe out jobs, what millennial and younger employers want and demand from the companies they work for.</p>
<p>There’s a lot going on, a lot to digest, and a lot to process. For example, Seth Klarman, <a href="http://bit.ly/2GPtz4l">in a recent (and rare) interview</a> with Evan Osnos at <em>The New Yorker</em>, explains how his focus on value investing helped him evolve his thinking—that a short-term profit focus is the wrong perspective for organizations, that they need to focus on customers, on employees. <a href="https://wapo.st/2SfnX5L">Recent reporting from the Davos World Economic Summit</a> highlights the “clueless” response from billionaire attendees that “upskilling” for a digital age is all that’s needed, that wealth inequality is not the problem. And for citizens, the situation is worse: the latest research shows that only <a href="https://www.edelman.com/trust-barometer">20% believe</a> “the system is working for me.”</p>
<p>These observations and many more help inform this compendium of topics. In the sections that follow, we address what business leaders, tech leaders, and decision-makers can expect; how they can prepare; and what they should learn to shape the future of their own firms. These are lessons that affect much more than the bottom line.</p>
<h2>Trust, responsibility, credibility, honesty, and transparency</h2>
<p>From our perspective, we see society undergoing a trust shakeout, with formerly trusted brands losing that trust and new trust intermediaries ascending to positions of trust and influence. Organizations can take advantage of the shakeout to focus on building trust and earning a trust premium that both customers and employees value.</p>
<p>As Laura Baldwin, President of O’Reilly Media, likes to say, “Your customer (your user) is your conscience.” Not only do your customers let you know when you’ve let them down, they let the world know. And increasingly, there are some with a much bigger megaphone than others. In particular, there are people who understand what Jeremy Heimans and Henry Timms call <a href="https://hbr.org/2014/12/understanding-new-power">“New Power”</a>. Donald Trump rode social media power all the way to the White House; Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez has become a congressional powerhouse even as a freshman because she too knows how to work the levers of internet visibility and vitality.</p>
<p>Concerns around trust and credibility swirl around many of the major social media companies—concerns that are amplified by the newness of the companies and the newness of online social media. For example, it is easy to blame tech companies like Facebook and Google for spreading fake news and hate speech, while giving traditional companies a pass on behavior that is at least as egregious. Facebook’s systems failed to stop fake news from spreading; too often, traditional media sources spread it intentionally. (See Yochai Benkler’s <a href="https://amzn.to/2GJnXc4">fascinating book on internet propaganda</a> and the role that traditional media outlets have played in legitimizing and amplifying content that was once shut down by those with journalistic integrity.)</p>
<p>Even within tech, Facebook and Twitter get most of the attention while YouTube and Reddit, doing a far worse job of addressing misinformation, generally receive little scrutiny. Uber uses low-paid temporary workers with uncertain schedules and incomes—so do Walmart, McDonald&#8217;s, and the Gap. Why do the tech firms get so much more heat while traditional companies often get a pass? Any attempt to come to grips with these problems needs an even-handed analysis of system-wide problems, not scapegoating of particular firms or industries.</p>
<p>But consider the fate of tech companies as a taste of things to come. The ability to shape or even to manipulate public opinion via social media is reaching a new level, not just in the hands of talented human practitioners but of those wielding new tools of algorithmic manipulation.</p>
<p>We can expect notions of trust to expand to include trust in machine learning and artificial intelligence algorithms far beyond social media. When these algorithms go bad—when results are biased, unfair, inexplicable—the results can shake a firm’s reputation and erode trust. Facebook and Google are in the crosshairs because AI and ML are at the heart of their businesses, but more and more companies will be swept up into scrutiny. And it can happen fast! Consider the <a href="http://bit.ly/2K3RcIx">failure of Microsoft’s chatbot experiment Tay</a>, where trolls were able to game the application to create a PR disaster of offensive remarks on its very first day of operation.</p>
<p>Increasingly, organizations planning on public-facing or customer-affecting ML/AI services need to make fairness, accountability, and transparency primary design objectives, not things to be tacked on at the end of projects. (See <a href="https://fatconference.org/">fatconference.org</a> and <a href="https://fatml.org/">fatml.org</a> for more information on research into fairness, accountability, and transparency [FAT] in ML.)</p>
<h2>The search for meaning</h2>
<p>The increased demand for trust and fairness covered in the previous section is part of a broader search for meaning—a topic of increasing interest and importance to organizations as they grapple with what motivates and inspires their employees, customers, and suppliers. The last few years of economic, political, organizational, technological, and social turmoil that helped fuel the trust shakeout have also intensified the search for meaning across the culture.</p>
<p>As the global economy has recovered from the 2008 meltdown, there has been a frightening increase in income inequality around the world. In 2017, <a href="http://bit.ly/2IlzuR6">eight men</a> owned more wealth than the poorest half of the world, and in the US, wages after inflation have <a href="https://read.bi/2NcxCsR">barely budged for 30 years</a>. This trend, coupled with the need to deal with issues of global warming and migration and immigration in most developed economies, has created a crisis in trust.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.edelman.com/trust-barometer">New research by Edelman</a> shows that in developed markets, only one-third of citizens believe their family will be better off in the next five years. Nationalism in the US, Brexit in the UK, and similar populist movements in France, Germany, and other countries show that the people are “rising up,” forcing political and business leaders to focus on making their lives better.</p>
<p>The impact on corporations has been enormous. <a href="http://bit.ly/2SIaOqN">Research by Gallup</a> shows that more American millennials have a positive view of socialism (51%) than capitalism (45%), and a <a href="http://bit.ly/2XchvQl">Shelton Group survey</a> found that 64% of US consumers believe it is &#8220;extremely important&#8221; that companies take a stand on current social issues and adjust their purchasing behavior based on those commitments. There is also a <a href="http://bit.ly/2trWQtU">growing backlash against plutocratic philanthropy</a>: while people appreciate wealthy “winners” of the economy for their gifts, they now want government to step back in and fix problems like infrastructure, rampant growth in CEOs&#8217; profits, and misbehavior.</p>
<p>This has given rise to a search for meaning in the boardroom. Even Davos, the global meeting of business leaders, has lost its sense of purpose, as companies now sit around discussing the fourth industrial revolution but seem to have no consensus about how to regulate privacy, data security, ethics, and global warming among nations.</p>
<p>For CEOs, this has created a dilemma: while they feel beholden to stockholders who want steady increases in short-term profits, they now realize they must take a position on the value of their companies&#8217; products and services to society. And they are struggling to find their footing.</p>
<p>Companies like Unilever, Patagonia, and Johnson &amp; Johnson have been mission-driven from their founding. They have always operated on the premise of “doing well by being good” and have a long track record of taking care of their employees, keeping their supply chains clean and sustainable, and making sure they practice ethical behavior in their product design, customer service, and operations. They are truly “conscious capitalists” at their core. But there is a new class of winners (Apple, Facebook, Google, Amazon, Alibaba) that are amassing enormous profits and market share in the digital economy, and are struggling to understand the consequences of their attention-driven business models.</p>
<p>And for all other firms, trust is now a way to differentiate themselves. Allbirds, a fast-growing shoe company that has the potential to threaten Nike or Adidas, builds its shoes entirely from sustainable products; it focuses on health and comfort for its young buyers, and its brand has skyrocketed in popularity because of its “good” way of doing business.</p>
<p>Consumer packaged goods companies like Unilever, P&amp;G, Nestlé, and General Mills have been operating in this world for decades. They face constant criticism over water treatment practices, food quality, and other social issues, so they are vigilant and have mature ways of staying ethical as needs and problems change.</p>
<p>Others, like banks, insurance companies, and investment firms, are not sure what to do. Larry Fink, the CEO of BlackRock, the largest investment firm in the US, has told his investors two years in a row that if they and he don’t focus on responsibility in their strategy, the firm will cease to thrive. CEO after CEO is finding new language to sell purpose and mission, forcing managers and senior leaders to think the same way.</p>
<p>At the firm level, this is an existential issue with employees. Employees of all ages no longer want to work for companies that “do bad things.” Facebook’s Glassdoor ratings, for example, have <a href="https://cnb.cx/2InxPuu">dropped</a> 30% in the last six months because of the ethical missteps and controversies that have been exposed, with its ranking in the list of &#8220;Best Places to Work&#8221; slipping from #1 to #7. Google employees stage protests for #MeToo, against defense department contracts and other corporate behavior. And it’s not just Facebook and Google: <a href="http://story.californiasunday.com/tech-revolt">“The Tech Revolt”</a> documents other manifestations of tech worker activism. While tech workers may have better facility with the tools for organizing, that knowledge can spread to others looking for employers that “do good to do well.” In this tight labor market, nearly every company should focus on its purpose to burnish its employment brand.</p>
<p>Apple, Microsoft, and IBM are now spending a lot of time talking about how to build technologies we can trust. Uber has changed its corporate advertising to talk about quality of life and self-fulfillment. This move toward becoming a “trusted player” in the world, acting like a global citizen, and truly defining one&#8217;s business in the context of its value to society is an enormous new trend that CEOs, CTOs, and CHROs now face all around the world.</p>
<h2>New leadership models and generational change</h2>
<p>In a recent study by Deloitte<a href="#_ftn1"><sup>[1]</sup></a>, 81% of senior leaders said they need new models of leadership. The characteristics most cited are the ability to lead during ambiguity (82%), leading through influence instead of hierarchy (68%), managing a wide variation in work arrangements (51%), and understanding how to leverage technology and new jobs created by machines (46%).</p>
<p>The entire concept of leadership has come under question. Witness the company with the iconic leadership model of the late 20th century: GE. GE is the subject of many books discussing its leadership model, the strong persona of its former CEO Jack Welch, the drive to reduce bureaucracy and hold people accountable, and the objective to be number one or two in a market or get out of the business. Today GE is a fallen giant that failed to leverage digital business models and has now been taken off the Dow Jones Index. How did this happen?</p>
<p>There are a series of changes taking place.</p>
<p>First, leaders are everywhere. Even the youngest employees are leading initiatives, teams, and organizations. (Mark Zuckerberg was thrust into leadership in his 20s.) The idea that you must “wait your turn” and experience a wide variety of roles before you lead is no longer valid. Today, leaders learn to lead on the job, so they need to be coached all the time.</p>
<p>Second, leaders now lead through influence, not position. In the GE and older hierarchical models, the leader was the boss. You did what they said, and the boss wielded power over you. Today, the pyramid is inverted: technical and functional experts make decisions on behalf of the company; leaders are here to coach, align, and help people succeed. They gain followers because of their reputations, not their job titles or levels.</p>
<p>Third, we now lead in diverse, multigenerational organizations. More than 55% of college graduates are women; <a href="http://bit.ly/2TV9VYl">the fastest-growing segment of the workforce is now people over the age of 50</a>. If you are not able to lead a team of men and women, people of many cultures, and people of many ages and demographic groups, you will not succeed. <a href="http://bit.ly/2IBbYQr">Deloitte’s research on highly inclusive teams</a> shows that groups that feel “included” perform at about 1.8x the rate of those that feel “left out.” This is a model of leadership.</p>
<p>Fourth, we need leaders who can iterate, experiment, and learn to quickly solve problems. The days of 3- to 4-year product cycles, long development plans, and years of market study are over. Today’s high-performing companies develop products in an agile way, they show them to customers early, they fail fast and repair mistakes, and they iterate using data and experimentation. Today’s leaders must be hands-on and they must support this process of continuous, customer-driven improvement.</p>
<p>There are some significant challenges for leaders ahead. Can your leadership team adapt to gender equality, pay fairness, and a truly global culture? Can your leadership team attract and assemble smart, empowered people and keep them aligned and performing toward your goal? Can your leadership team reorganize and revitalize the business as it changes, without being tied to old models that have fallen out of date? And can your leadership team adopt a growth mindset, designed to help everyone in the organization learn?</p>
<p><!-- BEGIN SIDEBAR --></p>
<aside data-type="sidebar" id="beyond-perks-new-leaders-model-work-life-balance-6LbSM">
<h5>Beyond perks: New leaders model work-life balance</h5>
<p><em>The following is a nice example of how embracing a modern benefit works to set cultural norms in an organization, and also gets noticed, becoming part of the story the organization can use to attract and retain the workforce it needs.</em></p>
<p><em>Note: The comments come from <a href="http://bit.ly/2NfT5RI">Bill Higgins’s personal Twitter account</a> and represent his own views, not the views of his employer.</em></p>
<p>I&#8217;d like to give a public kudos to April Underwood (<a href="https://twitter.com/aunder">@aunder</a>) for teaching me about the importance of intentionally modeling good, ethical behavior to reinforce the right cultural norms in your areas of influence.</p>
<p>Here’s the story, which I don’t think April will mind me sharing.</p>
<p>In a previous job at IBM, I was responsible for deploying Slack for the company, which made us the largest and possibly the most iconic enterprise adopter of Slack. Through this job, I had the privilege of getting to know April and other excellent leaders at <a href="https://twitter.com/SlackHQ">@SlackHQ</a>.</p>
<p>At the first Slack Frontiers conference closing party, I walked up to April to congratulate her on the successful conference and her then soon-to-be-born first child. I asked her how long she planned to take off work and, while I don&#8217;t recall the exact duration, it was longer than I would have expected for such a critical leader. I told her that I thought it was personally awesome that she was going to take such a leave and how I thought she&#8217;d always be glad that she did, later in life.</p>
<p>She told me that she was also doing it because she wanted to model the right cultural norms for Slack (i.e., people watch what you do, not what you say). And she wanted to use her position of influence to make it safe and even encouraged other Slack folks to take advantage of Slack’s generous and humane policy to allow new mothers and fathers to take a significant leave of absence after the birth of a new child.</p>
<p>While I have always tried to act morally and ethically at work, April&#8217;s comment really raised my consciousness that as a leader, one of my explicit responsibilities is to publicly model the right behaviors. These days, it&#8217;s quite an explicit and important part of my personal approach to leadership, and something I explicitly require my leaders to do as well.</p>
<p>Thank you April for teaching me this important lesson, and know that I am helping to spread it. Even though you are no longer at Slack, I hope we can stay connected so that I can continue to learn from you, and so that I continue to support you and your good deeds.</p>
<p data-type="attribution"><em>—Bill Higgins (<a href="https://twitter.com/BillHiggins">@BillHiggins</a>), IBM Distinguished Engineer, AI for Developers</em></p>
<p>PS: My company, IBM, also has a generous policy for paternity and maternity leave, and this is one of the many reasons I am proud to work there.<br />
</aside>
<p><!-- END SIDEBAR --></p>
<h2>Big systemic thinking</h2>
<p>There is nothing simple about business. It’s easy to get trapped by simple business models—for example, optimizing by doing more of what you know. “We’re doing well selling widgets, so let’s make more” is a good decision only if you know that the market for widgets is growing, that you can maintain or increase your market share, and that there isn’t something you can do even better. While it may be necessary to simplify the components of a business to best understand and apply them, taking the time to do big systemic thinking could be the most important factor to an organization’s sustained existence and success.</p>
<p>Today, as products become services (every product now has a digital footprint, which itself provides service revenue), companies have to understand the ecosystems in which they live. Cummins, for example, one of the leading providers of diesel engines, has been studying its ecosystem for decades. Today, the company sells not only engines but online diagnostics, services to dealers and resellers, and continuous digital services to its users. In time, Cummins may become a “digital services” company with revenue streams as large as its machines.</p>
<p>How do you skate to where the puck is headed, rather than where it is? Firms have to understand and participate in their entire business ecosystem. Those that don’t do this often disappear in a flash. Digital Equipment Corporation&#8217;s machines were absolutely central to the university and industry researchers who developed both the Unix operating system and the internet, but the company failed to realize that its own VAX/VMS operating system was a dead end. It was unwilling to sacrifice a popular but declining product for the future. If Digital had really understood the ecosystem in which it was engaged, the company might have seen this trend.</p>
<p>By way of contrast, consider Amazon, one of the best “systems thinking” companies in the world. As it built its retail business, the company realized that its many elements could be unbundled. Its massive internet infrastructure was a product in itself. Now Amazon Web Services (AWS), the unbundled services that power Amazon.com, is a leader in the cloud computing market, enabling even Amazon competitors. Not only that, but Amazon realized it could be more than one online retailer among many—it turned itself into a marketplace by unbundling its web catalog, its warehousing, and its delivery services and making them available to other merchants, reducing its own costs and taking a share of everyone else’s profits. And now, because of the scope of its marketplace offerings, it has built a large and fast-growing advertising business, taking away a meaningful fraction of what seemed to be Google’s unchallengeable share in one of the most profitable areas of search.</p>
<p>Sometimes, thinking holistically means deciding what not to do. For example, O’Reilly Media closed its online retail store not because the store was failing, but because the store got in the way of the company’s strategic decision to pivot from retail book sales to <a href="http://bit.ly/2BB8182">becoming a learning marketplace</a>.</p>
<p>None of these are simple decisions you could arrive at just by doing more of what’s working. They also aren’t decisions you can arrive at by decomposing an organization into its component parts and analyzing them separately. They don’t come from simplistic and reductionist models of how the business works. Rather, they require a broad understanding and intuitive sense of the business and its environment: its customers, its competencies, its competitive situation, and how forces are constantly shaping and reshaping all of these. The decisions themselves, like “sell computing infrastructure as a service,” sound simple in retrospect. But getting through the complexity to those decisions isn’t simple.</p>
<p>There are no silver bullets; big systemic thinking can go just as wrong as any other thought process. Getting through the noise to communicate those decisions to employees, to customers, and to the board of directors isn’t simple, either. But without that kind of thinking, you can’t be right.</p>
<h2>New kinds of partnerships between people and machines</h2>
<p>At internet companies like Google, Facebook, and Amazon—and any other company delivering software-based services—we need an inversion of perspective. It’s easy to think that programmers are simply workers, assembling code like a previous generation assembled manufactured goods, but in fact, much of the actual work these companies do to serve their customers is done by software agents. At Amazon, one piece of software shows you your buying options. Another takes your order. Another queues it up for shipping. The software developers and “DevOps” staff are the <em>managers</em> of this new generation of workers. Every day, the managers are checking on their digital workers, A/B testing new approaches, and giving their workers feedback in the form of new code releases.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the central job of massive, real-time coordination of people and resources—formerly done by human managers—is increasingly done by machine learning and artificial intelligence systems. The humans creating these systems are more like their teachers than their managers. They create them and train them, then turn them loose on the problem. When something goes wrong, those with a 20th-century perspective expect the company management to step in to fix the problem directly, but in a 21st-century company like Facebook, Google, or Amazon, the company’s programmer-managers must actually retrain the systems, or build new ones to compensate for their failings. The humans no longer run the operations directly. Managing the unintended side effects of poorly designed systems becomes the principal focus of human managers.</p>
<p>For a purely digital company like Google or Facebook, the analogy stops there. But at companies like Walmart, Amazon, or Uber, which provide physical-world services, the software bots are intermediaries between the managers and humans. When a customer requests a ride from Uber or Lyft, a software agent routes a driver to the pickup, and from there to the destination. But the driver isn’t the only one in the workflow. In what Microsoft researcher Mary Gray calls <a href="https://amzn.to/2GPuulj">“Ghost Work”</a>, a pieceworker in India may be performing a security check on the driver via Amazon’s Mechanical Turk service. Uber is a single vast machine made up of humans and software working in a complex dance.</p>
<p>Machines also upskill the drivers. It is no longer necessary for a driver to know their way around the city. The app knows that. This is one of the key enablers of a model in which anyone can drive for pay. This is also the new face of learning on demand: learning by doing, with the machine guiding you along the way. Autodesk, the engineering and construction management company, is exploring this same concept, building tools that increasingly help humans to do complex jobs not just by teaching them new skills but by partnering with them in new ways.</p>
<p>While we don’t know all the implications of automation and AI, we know people will still have important roles. Already, as AI enters roles like retail and customer service, companies like IBM and American Express are hiring people to monitor decisions made by software, improve social cues, and translate machine recommendations into more meaningful recommendations. Just as we “train” our computers to think through software and instructions, people will “train” their robots to be more successful through feedback.</p>
<h2>From hierarchies to networks</h2>
<p>Ever since Ronald Coase wrote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Nature_of_the_Firm">“The Nature of the Firm”</a> in 1937, the general understanding has been that the command and control systems within a single organization have lower transaction costs than the cost of finding, vetting, and contracting from among a marketplace of small independent businesses. That system peaked with the lifetime employment and generous benefits of the golden age of industrial concentration. But for the last 30 years, companies have been building two-tier organizations (with a highly compensated core of dedicated employees and a far larger base of fungible contractors) and outsourcing relationships, usually to large outsourcing companies that hide the churn of workers at the fringe.</p>
<p>The internet and big data added the last pieces of the puzzle, providing capabilities for companies to directly manage large networks of individuals (though intermediaries may also still play a role). A company such as Uber or Airbnb displays this pattern in its fullness: asset light, algorithm heavy. Human-scale marketplaces and management processes have been replaced by algorithmic, internet-scale marketplaces in industries such as advertising, where Google is only the largest of the algorithmic advertising networks that have threatened “Mad Men”–style agencies. Amazon only looks like a retailer; once you realize that it carries more than three billion SKUs worldwide (600 million in the US alone), many of them from third-party sellers who themselves carry all of the inventory risk, you understand that it, like Uber or Google, is an algorithmic matching marketplace, pairing up buyers and sellers in real time.</p>
<p>Systems like these preserve the appearance of free market economies, but in reality they are centrally planned economies, where the designers of the algorithms ultimately choose who gets what and why. As these platforms achieve near monopoly status, it vastly increases their power relative to their marketplace participants. We need a new theory of antitrust: one that measures the health of platform marketplace ecosystems, and the extent to which marketplaces compete with their suppliers, rather than simply looking at consumer benefit.</p>
<p>Building platforms that take better care of suppliers, not just their users, can create a critical strategic advantage. You can already see this, for example, in Apple’s position on privacy (treating its users as data suppliers to be valued, whereas Google and Facebook treat them as resources to be exploited).</p>
<p><!-- BEGIN SIDEBAR --></p>
<aside data-type="sidebar" id="it-isnt-just-internet-giants-who-manage-networks-jzSlX">
<h5>It isn’t just internet giants who manage networks</h5>
<p>O’Reilly Media can be seen as a case study in how to build competitive advantage by recognizing a business as a two-sided marketplace of suppliers and customers. Twenty years ago, the company was primarily a publisher of computer books. Realizing its success depended not only on its community of authors as suppliers but also on the communities of open source and internet software developers who created the technologies they wrote about, the company added a <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/conferences/">conference business</a> to bring together and evangelize the work of those developer communities. O’Reilly also launched an online ebook platform to which it invited even its biggest competitors, because the company leaders understood they had to grow the whole market and not just their own share of it. As new online learning modalities like video and live training became possible, they morphed their platform to embrace them, not just because they are popular with users but because they provided new revenue opportunities for their suppliers.</p>
<p>Thinking beyond simple compensation, O’Reilly offers authors the opportunity to speak, provide training, and participate in live online events on its <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/online-learning/">learning platform</a> and at the many conferences the company puts on. By providing these opportunities for authors, O’Reilly helps those authors bolster their credibility and reputations, and they in turn help the company maintain its reputation as a top destination for those interested in teaching what they know about cutting-edge technology. This is a major benefit to the company’s customers, but its business strategy was triggered by understanding what would make the marketplace more vibrant for its suppliers.<br />
</aside>
<p><!-- END SIDEBAR --></p>
<p>Perhaps the biggest change taking place is the rapid evolution away from management hierarchies to networks of highly empowered teams. More than two decades ago, software engineers realized that large, hierarchical software teams were underperforming, so they developed the concept of small, multifunctional teams. (The book <a href="http://bit.ly/2Ew3xTm"><em>The Mythical Man-Month</em></a> by Frederic P. Brooks, Jr., first pointed this out.)</p>
<p>Since then, the business concepts of “Agile,” “teams,” “Scrum,” and “iterative development” have exploded in all areas of business, shattering the corporate hierarchy. Yes, companies still have job levels, managers, and executives, but more and more companies now realize that people do not perform well when they are “told what to do.” What really makes companies thrive is letting people “solve problems,” “serve customers,” and “invent” in their own personal ways.</p>
<p>In a recent <a href="http://bit.ly/2X7VUc5">study published in the <em>Harvard Business Review</em></a>, 83% of R&amp;D departments, 82% of operations, 79% of marketing, and 78% of sales, HR, and finance teams reported that they believed they were using some form of “Agile” in their business operations. While the true application of Agile principles in non-software operations is still emerging, the trend is clear and unstoppable. The firm of the future is a network, not a functional hierarchy.</p>
<p>This has implications in many areas of management. Should we promote people “up” or “across”? Should we pay people for individual performance or team results? Should we promote leaders who are good at direction and strategy or those who thrive at coaching and development? Should we develop goals from the top down or bottom up?</p>
<p>Every management principle can now be questioned, and as we see companies like GE fall behind in their growth and profitability, we can question decades of management philosophies based on the industrial organization of business. We believe the future of the firm is an empowered, bottom-up structure—and one that operates like a network, not a directed hierarchy.</p>
<h2>Free agency, personal brands, and the evolving employer/employee relationship</h2>
<p>As the bonds of loyalty fray between companies and their employees, there are two countervailing trends. First, relatively low-skilled employees, who might once have had secure jobs, have joined what Guy Standing calls <a href="https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/the-precariat-9781474294164/">“the Precariat”</a>, living lives of continuous partial employment. In contrast, highly sought-after employees (such as AI professionals in Silicon Valley) have become the equivalent of movie or sports stars. The ability of such people to build reputations through open source software, blogging, and other forms of internet visibility gives them free agency. This leads to a tension in which some companies seek to hide their talent, while others let them display it freely. You can see this in the difficulty Amazon and Apple had in recruiting AI talent because of their cultures of secrecy, while Google and Facebook allowed employees to publish their research. Amazon was forced to open up, and Apple is starting to.</p>
<p>Skills and capability far outweigh seniority and tenure for determining free agent compensation. In highly stratified organizations, this can cause serious dislocations in pay and status. For example, in order to appropriately compensate cybersecurity professionals, the White House Office of Personnel Management <a href="http://bit.ly/2S9Ix7j">had to create entirely new compensation guidance</a>, authorized by an act of Congress! If this can happen in government, expect (for now) that salary parity rules at private companies will also be selectively tossed out—until the equity issues get thorny enough for a broad reassessment.</p>
<p>Top talent (executive or technical) commands superstar salaries, just as in movies and sports. Astonishingly high levels of compensation are funded not with dollars, but with stock options and grants, which pass at least some of the costs to investors and hide the true cost of employee compensation. Some companies correctly report stock grants as employee costs, but many continue to bury these costs in footnotes and report non-GAAP financials. This has led to a vast compensation imbalance between companies with sky-high stock valuations based on growth momentum and those that are living in the more mundane world of real cash flow and profits. This creates increasingly a winner-takes-all race for talent.</p>
<p><a href="https://economics.mit.edu/files/12979">The Superstar Firms theory</a>, put forth by David Autor and others, posits that eventually these higher wages will spread through the corporation and into the broader market, bringing up compensation levels for ordinary employees. This is something to be hoped for. In the meantime, companies without highly inflated stock must compensate employees in other ways. One such approach is through brand, mission, values, and purpose (we’ll come back to this in the next section). Macroeconomic factors may eventually also bring profitless growth stocks to a more reasonable level.</p>
<p>Even at lower levels, though, there is far more job mobility, again through online platforms. Temporary work through a platform like Upwork can even be a way of gaining new skills in an environment with less risk than at a person’s current employer. Data from O’Reilly’s online learning platform shows that employees often seek additional training before changing jobs, and after moving to a new internal job or receiving new responsibilities. Training is no longer something employees are sent to; it is something they seek out.</p>
<p>It is also worth noting there is a new labor movement building, but it’s not focused on the old labor issues. It’s more concerned with topics covered in <a data-type="xref" class="missing_xref" title="This is a cross reference. It is not available in this excerpt.">not available</a>. When Google employees walked out, it was about Google’s failures of social conscience, not about higher wages or working conditions. They were protesting Google’s involvement in providing AI for military purposes, and rewards to a top executive who, facing multiple charges of sexual harassment, had been forced out of his job but still received a massive severance stock payout. On a humbler level, when 30,000 Starbucks baristas used the coworker.org platform to raise issues with management, the first issue was not higher wages but the dress code, which required all employees to cover up any tattoos!</p>
<h2>Compensation beyond pay</h2>
<p>One of the fast-changing parts of organizations is the way people are paid. As <a href="http://bit.ly/2V8H5UO">increasing numbers of workers engage in contract, contingent, or gig work</a>, organizations are rethinking their rewards. <a href="https://on.mktw.net/2TW0Dvo">Economic data shows</a> that US workers’ wages are not keeping up with inflation, leading an estimated <a href="http://bit.ly/2InZJ9G">40% of American workers to take on “side hustles”</a>. How does the firm of the future think about pay?</p>
<p>Research shows this is a re-engineering process taking place now. A <a href="http://bit.ly/2X85Ou6">2018 study by Deloitte</a> found that only 12% of companies strongly agreed that their pay practices were fully aligned with their business strategies. In most cases, companies compete for talent, so pay is driven by market wages. But when you dig deeper, the data shows something different.</p>
<p>In any given job family, there are employers who pay less (perhaps even “underpay”) but offer more career development opportunities, a more flexible workplace, and more benefits. Others, with more competitive cultures, may pay more—but they expect more. This new bifurcation of pay is letting firms think about all their people as independent agents, and they can now create the optimal mix of pay and benefits for their employees.</p>
<p>We’re seeing a shift in the composition of compensation toward perks, benefits, and non-cash rewards. In the US, benefits have grown from <a href="http://bit.ly/2Xbpeyo">28% of payroll in 1998</a> to <a href="http://bit.ly/2Ele4Q7">32% in 2018</a>, increasing the burden employers are taking on. This increase is largely due to a rise in medical costs, leading employers to increase focus on well-being programs and other health benefits that reduce health care expenses. In fact, there is now an entire industry of corporate well-being programs in place, creating an escalating war for the best, most innovative, most modern types of well-being benefits. This goes beyond yoga classes and includes offerings such as programs for fertility, pet care, elder care, and free lunch; allowances for commuting; programs to help with student loans, financial fitness, and healthy diet; and mental health counseling. And that’s leaving out a huge extension in parental leave, exemplified by a CEO as central to his company as Mark Zuckerberg taking advantage of his company’s liberal parental leave policy to <a href="http://bit.ly/2SM4SMN">step away from his job for a full two months</a>.</p>
<p>This shift in pay to a more customized, integrated set of holistic offerings is forcing companies to be more competitive and accommodate flexible working styles. The firm of the future is one that truly takes care of its workers, trying to entice employees to stay put, as more and more options become transparently available on the internet. If we see a recession, much of this may slow down, but we see this as being a permanent shift in the way companies pay their people.</p>
<p>Finally, in the new race for skills and continuous learning, companies are starting to realize that learning, development, and career opportunities are a huge surrogate for salary. Companies that invest in strategic learning and development (L&amp;D) offerings, internships, and a culture of development can pay people less yet still attract the best and most motivated candidates because everyone is worried about falling out of date.</p>
<h2>Diversity, inclusion, and fairness at work</h2>
<p>Diversity, inclusion, and fairness are among the most critical issues facing business leaders today. The #MeToo movement set off a steady disclosure of gender bias and mistreatment in business. The passage of the CEO pay disclosure act set off a discussion about pay fairness. The Black Lives Matter movement sensitized non-white workers to their low levels of pay and relatively fewer roles in senior jobs. And now people are starting to wonder if AI and algorithmic decision systems are going to take all these decades of bias and institutionalize the problem in hiring, promotion, pay, and other talent-related decisions.</p>
<p>At the Davos conference in 2019, there were a series of sessions discussing the need for wealthy people to take responsibility for philanthropy and social equality. As we noted earlier, <a href="http://bit.ly/2SIaOqN">51% of millennials</a> have a favorable view of socialism, and the percentage of Generation Xers and Boomers who favor capitalism is declining. While many wealthy individuals have set up foundations and other philanthropies, there is a movement against this kind of giving. The book <a href="http://bit.ly/2trWQtU"><em>Winners Take All</em></a>, by <em>New York Times</em> reporter Anand Giridharadas, argues quite persuasively that it is now time to put our trust back into government and political systems because no matter how hard we try, profit-making enterprises will never do what’s right for society.</p>
<p>We believe the future of the firm is a new form of responsible capitalism. It is not enough to have social responsibility programs and sustainability programs: companies must gladly pay taxes, they must support and give to political institutions, and they must support the infrastructure-based systems in their communities.</p>
<p>This is a tricky new space for CEOs and business leaders. More than 45% of executives <a href="http://bit.ly/2Sg7Q80">recently surveyed by Deloitte</a> believe their new &#8220;social purpose&#8221; products and services are revenue generating opportunities. That may be true, but it&#8217;s the wrong reason to do it. Companies that don&#8217;t truly act responsibly will be found out, and the social backlash can be tremendously damaging: when United Airlines mistreated an animal, when Volkswagen cheated on its emissions tests, when Equifax leaked sensitive data—these are brand-damaging events.</p>
<p>Right now, we have very uneven economic growth around the world. Developed economies are becoming unequal—the Gini index (a statistical measure of income distribution) is getting higher in major democracies than in autocratic countries. This means workers and buyers of products feel upset, frustrated, and angry at “wealthy firms.” While the firm is not a person, it represents a persona—and when the CEO and leaders do not take an active position on social and political topics they can risk long-term brand damage.</p>
<p>We know all companies must make money to survive. We know that profits fuel economic and business success. But despite the stock market’s short-term focus, we believe companies that do not specifically focus on trust, fairness, inclusion, social responsibility, and building a sense of internal community are going to suffer in the long run. If we experience a recession and buying slows, consumers will be even more sensitive—and Generation Zers and millennials are already very sensitive to company brand when they buy products.</p>
<p>Companies must inspect and audit fairness in all their new AI and algorithmic digital systems. If bias is discovered, it must be fixed promptly and openly; it’s not OK to find out later that a mortgage company was discriminating against black homeowners or a well-being company was overpricing products to low-income neighborhoods just because the AI recommended it. Every AI-based decision needs to be validated with a human lens—and this is a new burden and an expertise companies have to develop.</p>
<p>Issues of gender, race, and age diversity must be addressed. Yet, <a href="http://bit.ly/2NefvTk">an employee survey</a> shows most companies do not have programs that enable women and others to openly report on harassment or unfair treatment. This is woefully inadequate given the increase in the diversity of the workforce and the sensitivity of employees. With companies more service-dependent than ever, despite the growth of automation, diversity becomes a tool for increasing the pool of resources for these important roles. Fairness must be part of the blood of the firm, with constant, consistent attention to rooting out inequities.</p>
<p><a href="http://bit.ly/2DRN9Kh">Research also now shows</a> that college degrees and GPAs are not predictive of career success. Companies must expand the aperture of their hiring, opening up the lens of talent acquisition to people of all ages and backgrounds. New AI-based assessments now make this easier than ever; however, as we&#8217;ve mentioned, these systems need vigilance and care to ensure fairness.</p>
<p>Another issue related to both fairness and compensation is the huge increase in CEO pay inequity. Despite new laws in the US and UK to force companies to disclose CEO pay ratios, the amount paid to CEOs keeps going up. <a href="https://on.wsj.com/2NeExS5">In the US, the average salary for S&amp;P 500 CEOs reached 373 times the average median income in 2014</a>, with some companies paying CEOs 400–500 times the median employee salary. This inequality is having a negative effect on many employees, and we suspect it contributes to those <a href="http://bit.ly/2SIaOqN">51% of millennials</a> now preferring a socialist form of economy. We believe CEO pay has gone high enough, and companies have to realize that CEOs are not gods: they are replaceable, and many organizations have successors waiting in the wings.</p>
<p>For a more detailed look at issues related to equality and freedom, including the link between respect and policy to ensure freedom, see <a href="http://bit.ly/2V5DvKR">“The Philosopher Redefining Equality”</a> by Nathan Heller.</p>
<h2>Board governance and diversity</h2>
<p>What is the board’s responsibility for the future of the firm, or the firm of the future? Boards are responsible for setting direction and overseeing the day-to-day managers. They’re responsible for ensuring the firm is managed responsibly. Yet, for too long, boards have been hired, bought, and paid for by management. The concept of an “independent director” is a convenient fiction. Given that directors are typically paid with generous stock grants, and that the shareholder value hypothesis posits that the directors’ primary fiduciary duty is to increase shareholder value, both pecuniary incentives and legal directives ensure there is little effective representation for workers, customers, or other stakeholders. This is an area ripe for reform.</p>
<p>Corporate boards are also lagging in digital sophistication. Areas like cybersecurity, social media marketing, AI, big data, and algorithmic management are all becoming table stakes for the modern company. A new kind of directors’ college is needed. When Tim O’Reilly attended Stanford Directors’ College a decade ago, most of the information provided was about how directors can avoid liability, rather than how to engage in a proper corporate governance role.</p>
<p>More broadly than digital sophistication, board members concerned about the future of the firm must think carefully about the big picture, about <em>all</em> the components of the firm’s success, not just the bottom line. That includes items affecting societal good, reputation, customers, employees, and even contractors. For example, a board with an elected employee representative only reflects employee concerns if all board members think employees are important. Board responsibilities like ethics, not just compliance liability, are often complex, with no “right answer”—which is precisely why the board needs to be involved.</p>
<p>Given the scope of a board’s responsibilities, one would expect organizations to constitute a board structured to give the best, most prescient advice. Yet, boards made up of “elder statesmen” from the business world notoriously lack independence and diversity—factors that affect board relevancy during this time of great organizational disruption.</p>
<p>At the O’Reilly Radar Conference in November 2018, Jeff Wong, Head of Innovation at EY, spoke about the lack of diversity on corporate boards—not just physical diversity (i.e., race and gender) but cognitive diversity—for tackling difficult issues like digital sophistication, employee welfare, ethics, and trust. Boards need to do a better, more confident job of asking the right questions—about change, digital transformation, cultural changes in the workforce, social media, artificial intelligence, and other (sometimes uncomfortable) topics that boards should address. Board members often miss these questions because they lack the diverse backgrounds that accurately reflect the state of the world.</p>
<p>As Wong noted, many organizations select board members based on what they&#8217;ve done over the last 30 years, which would be fantastic if the next 10 years were expected to look like the last 30. That’s not the situation most organizations face. To address a future of change, boards should hire people who look different, think different, have different tenures, earned their wealth in different ways, and have different academic and professional backgrounds, but who bring the right perspectives and right questions to the boardroom.</p>
<p>Another benefit of creating more diverse corporate boards is the finding <a href="https://amzn.to/2SJsimC">from Scott E. Page</a> that more diverse groups tend to make better decisions. This topic is well covered by Steven Johnson in his book <a href="https://amzn.to/2TXDE2O"><em>Farsighted</em></a>. For corporate board activities like evaluating risk and scenario planning, we consider Johnson’s advice for groups in general relevant: that “the most important element is the <em>diversity</em> of perspectives&#8221; assembled—an effect strong enough that “it appears to apply even when the diverse perspectives&#8230;have no relevant expertise.” Johnson goes into more detail as to why diversity helps: homogeneous groups “tend to come to decisions too quickly,” settling early on the most likely scenarios and not spending the energy to question assumptions.</p>
<p>Like the rest of the firm, the future of boards is likely evolving, rewarding firms that turn their boards into true assets that bring broad, diverse perspectives, independent thinking, and guidance to help navigate and anticipate a dynamic and disruptive future. Independent, diverse boards bring a healthy dose of real-world perspective and are good for the bottom line.</p>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>If there’s one idea to take away from this report, it’s this: if you think you can run the firm of the future the same way businesses ran in the past, you’re wrong, and perhaps fatally wrong. The next 10 years won’t be like the last 30 years, and won’t be remotely like the last 60. Technological fluency isn’t optional: it’s table stakes, all the way to the board level. Your employees will be changing, and they will value opportunities to learn and to make a difference. Integrating different ways of thinking and different kinds of experience is a must. Above all, businesses are complex systems, and simple, reductionist approaches are doomed to fail. There are plenty of opportunities for success, perhaps more than ever before; it’s the path toward those opportunities that has changed.</p>
<p>As we said at the start, whatever the future of the firm is, it won’t be business as usual.</p>
<p><!-- BEGIN FOOTNOTE --></p>
<aside data-type="sidebar" id="id-JESm4">
<div id="_ftn1">
<p><sup>[1]</sup> Data is from the forthcoming <em>2019 Global Human Capital Trends</em> report from Deloitte.</p>
</div>
</aside>
<p><!-- END FOOTNOTE --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://www.oreilly.com/radar/future-of-the-firm/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
